<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-model href="REED.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="REED.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="hthtp://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
 
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:base="tei/records/" xml:lang="eng" xml:id="nwbts">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">Newington Butts Playhouse</title>
        <funder><orgName>Jackman Foundation, Toronto, Canada</orgName></funder>
        <funder><orgName>National Endowment for the Humanities, Washington, DC, United States of
            America</orgName></funder>
        <funder><orgName>Social Sciences and Humanities Research Council, Ottawa,
          Canada</orgName></funder>
        <editor>Sally-Beth MacLean</editor>
        <respStmt>
          <persName xml:id="JC">James Cummings</persName>
          <orgName>Newcastle University</orgName>
          <resp>TEI Schema Designer</resp>
          <resp>Technical Consultant</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName xml:id="PG">Patrick Gregory</persName>
          <orgName>Records of Early English Drama (REED)</orgName>
          <resp>Paleographer</resp>
          <resp>Translator</resp>
          <resp>Glossarian</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Tanya Hagen</persName>
          <orgName>Records of Early English Drama (REED)</orgName>
          <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
          <resp>Copy Editor</resp>
          <resp>Project Manager</resp>
          <resp>Proofreader</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Stephanie Hovland</persName>
          <orgName>Records of Early English Drama (REED)</orgName>
          <resp>UK Paleographer</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Sally-Beth MacLean</persName>
          <orgName>Records of Early English Drama (REED)</orgName>
          <resp>Principal Investigator, SSHRC grant</resp>
          <resp>Director of Research</resp>
          <resp>General Editor</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Byron Moldofsky</persName>
          <orgName>University of Toronto</orgName>
          <resp>Cartographer</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Illya Nokhrin</persName>
          <orgName>Records of Early English Drama (REED)</orgName>
          <resp>Research Associate</resp>
          <resp>Indexer, Entity Tagger</resp>
          <resp>REED EATS taxonomy developer</resp>
          <resp>REED EATS database maintainer</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName xml:id="JN">Jamie Norrish</persName>
          <resp>Programmer</resp>
          <resp>TEI Schema Designer</resp>
          <resp>Technical Consultant</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Rose Grant</persName>
          <orgName>Records of Early English Drama (REED)</orgName>
          <resp>Bibliographic Researcher</resp>
          <resp>Content Checker</resp>
          <resp>Copy Editor</resp>
          <resp>Indexer</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <!-- Release date to be changed here prior to publication -->
        <edition> Version 1, released <date when-iso="2025-06-19">19 June 2025</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority><orgName>Records of Early English Drama (REED)</orgName>
          <address>
            <addrLine>University of Toronto</addrLine>
            <addrLine>170 St George Street, Suite 810</addrLine>
            <addrLine>Toronto, Ontario, Canada</addrLine>
            <addrLine>M5R 2M8</addrLine>
          </address>
        </authority>
        <availability>
          <p>Copyright <orgName>Records of Early English Drama (REED)</orgName>,
            <date>2018</date></p>
          <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">Distributed under a
            Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA
            4.0) licence.</licence>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <seriesStmt>
        <title>Records of Early English Drama</title>
      </seriesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Born digital. Information on original sources for transcriptions can be accessed via
          taxonomy.xml.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <listPrefixDef>
        <prefixDef ident="eats" matchPattern="([0-9]+)"
          replacementPattern="http://ereed.library.utoronto.ca/eats/entity/$1/">
          <p>URIs using the <code>eats</code> prefix are references to EATS entities.</p>
        </prefixDef>
        <prefixDef ident="gloss" matchPattern="([\S]+)" replacementPattern="../glossary.xml#$1">
          <p>Private URIs using the <code>gloss</code> prefix are pointers to entities in the
            glossary.xml file. For example, <code>gloss:histrio-1</code> dereferences to
              <code>glossary.xml#histrio-1</code>.</p>
        </prefixDef>
        <prefixDef ident="taxon" matchPattern="([A-Za-z0-9_-]+)"
          replacementPattern="../taxonomy.xml#$1">
          <p>Private URIs using the <code>taxon</code> prefix are pointers to entities in the
            taxonomy.xml file. For example, <code>taxon:church</code> dereferences to
              <code>taxonomy.xml#church</code>.</p>
        </prefixDef>
      </listPrefixDef>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="eng">English</language>
        <language ident="lat">Latin</language>
        <language ident="ita">Italian</language>
        <language ident="fra">French</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <facsimile>
    <graphic url="images/nwbts/NBPL14.jpg" xml:id="NBPL14">
      <desc>By kind permission of the More-Molyneux family and Surrey History Centre</desc>
    </graphic>
    <graphic url="images/nwbts/LMA/NBSKCSf87v.jpg" xml:id="NBSKCSf87v">
      <desc>© The London Archives: City of London, SKCS/018</desc>
    </graphic>
    <graphic url="images/nwbts/LMA/NBSKCSf95v.jpg" xml:id="NBSKCSf95v">
      <desc>© The London Archives: City of London, SKCS/018</desc>
    </graphic>
    <graphic url="images/nwbts/LMA/NBSKCSf105v.jpg" xml:id="NBSKCSf105v">
      <desc>© The London Archives: City of London, SKCS/018</desc>
    </graphic>
    <graphic url="images/nwbts/LMA/NBSKCSf172.jpg" xml:id="NBSKCSf172">
      <desc>© The London Archives: City of London, SKCS/018</desc>
    </graphic>
    <graphic url="images/nwbts/LMA/NBSKCS294av.jpg" xml:id="NBSKCS294av">
      <desc>© The London Archives: City of London, SKCS/018</desc>
    </graphic>
    <graphic url="images/nwbts/TNA/NBPCL3p84.jpg" xml:id="NBPCL3p84">
      <desc>The National Archives (UK), ref. PC2/14</desc>
    </graphic>
    <graphic url="images/nwbts/TNA/NBPCL3p86.jpg" xml:id="NBPCL3p86">
      <desc>The National Archives (UK), ref. PC2/14</desc>
    </graphic>
    <graphic url="images/nwbts/TNA/NBPCO7p300.jpg" xml:id="NBPCO7p300">
      <desc>The National Archives (UK), ref. PC2/12</desc>
    </graphic>
    <graphic url="images/nwbts/TNA/NBPCO7p348.jpg" xml:id="NBPCO7p348">
      <desc>The National Archives (UK), ref. PC2/12</desc>
    </graphic>
    <graphic url="images/nwbts/TNA/NBPL13p10.jpg" xml:id="NBPL13p10">
      <desc>The National Archives (UK), ref. PC2/13</desc>
    </graphic>
    <graphic url="images/nwbts/TNA/NBCRSH3.jpg" xml:id="NBCRSH3">
      <desc>The National Archives (UK), ref. REQ 2/266</desc>
    </graphic>
    <graphic url="images/nwbts/TNA/NBCRSH2.jpg" xml:id="NBCRSH2">
      <desc>The National Archives (UK), ref. REQ 2/266</desc>
    </graphic>
    <graphic url="images/nwbts/TNA/NBCRSH1.jpg" xml:id="NBCRSH1">
      <desc>The National Archives (UK), ref. REQ 2/266</desc>
    </graphic>
    <graphic url="images/nwbts/CCA/NBCCDCf36v.jpg" xml:id="NBCCDCf36v">
      <desc>Reproduced courtesy of the Chapter of Canterbury, CCA-DCc-Register/W, ff 36v–7</desc>
    </graphic>
    <graphic url="images/nwbts/CCA/NBCCDCf37r.jpg" xml:id="NBCCDCf37r">
      <desc>Reproduced courtesy of the Chapter of Canterbury, CCA-DCc-Register/W, ff 36v–7</desc>
    </graphic>
    <graphic url="images/nwbts/CCA/NBCCABf184.jpg" xml:id="NBCCABf184">
      <desc>Reproduced courtesy of the Chapter of Canterbury, CCA-DCc-CA/3, f 184</desc>
    </graphic>
    <graphic url="images/nwbts/CCA/NBCCABf27v.jpg" xml:id="NBCCABf27v">
      <desc>Reproduced courtesy of the Chapter of Canterbury, CCA-DCc-CA/3, f 27v</desc>
    </graphic>
    <graphic url="images/nwbts/CCA/NBCCDCf266v.jpg" xml:id="NBCCDCf266v">
      <desc>Reproduced courtesy of the Chapter of Canterbury, CCA-DCc-Register/W, ff 265v–6v </desc>
    </graphic>
    <graphic url="images/nwbts/CCA/NBCCDCf266r.jpg" xml:id="NBCCDCf266r">
      <desc>Reproduced courtesy of the Chapter of Canterbury, CCA-DCc-Register/W, ff 265v–6v</desc>
    </graphic>
    <graphic url="images/nwbts/CCA/NBCCDCf265v.jpg" xml:id="NBCCDCf265v">
      <desc>Reproduced courtesy of the Chapter of Canterbury, CCA-DCc-Register/W, ff 265v–6v</desc>
    </graphic>
    <graphic url="images/nwbts/CCA/NBCCA2f32v.jpg" xml:id="NBCCA2f32v">
      <desc>Reproduced courtesy of the Chapter of Canterbury, CCA-DCc-Register/U6, ff 32v–3v</desc>
    </graphic>
    <graphic url="images/nwbts/CCA/NBCCA2f33.jpg" xml:id="NBCCA2f33">
      <desc>Reproduced courtesy of the Chapter of Canterbury, CCA-DCc-Register/W, ff 32v–3v</desc>
    </graphic>
    <graphic url="images/nwbts/CCA/NBCCA2f33v.jpg" xml:id="NBCCA2f33v">
      <desc>Reproduced courtesy of the Chapter of Canterbury, CCA-DCc-Register/W, ff 32v–3v</desc>
    </graphic>
    <graphic url="images/nwbts/CCA/NBCCA1.jpg" xml:id="NBCCA1f68">
      <desc>Reproduced courtesy of the Chapter of Canterbury, CCA-DCc-CA/1, f 68</desc>
    </graphic>
  </facsimile>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div xml:id="acknowledgments">
        <head>Acknowledgments</head>
        <div>
          <p>Every edition in the Records of English Drama series benefits from the collaborative
            enterprise that forms the core of REED's mission. This collection -- small though it may
            be -- is no exception.</p>

          <p>It has been my privilege to work with REED's expert editorial team who have efficiently
            brought the Newington Butts Playhouse records to publication: Tanya Hagen, managing
            editor and master bibliographer; Patrick Gregory, senior paleographer and Latinist; and
            Illya Nokhrin, senior indexer responsible also for the timeline feature. Rose Grant, our
            graduate student assistant for playhouse editions, deserves special recognition for the
            very professional job she has done as bibliographic researcher, content-checker,
            copy-editor and indexer. As ever, I have had ongoing pleasure in collaborating with
            cartographer Byron Moldofsky as we continue to expand the GIS mapping of the London area
            to include Newington and its local roads.</p>

          <p>In the early days of research for this collection, I had the overseas help of Stephanie
            Hovland, who initiated work in the Canterbury archives. When Covid struck and I was
            unable to travel to UK archives, I had the unique opportunity to commission research
            help in the London area archives, thanks to Professor Sue Wiseman at Birkbeck College,
            whose graduate student Robert Stearns pursued leads in parish records so frustratingly
            out of reach for me.</p>

          <p>There are three scholars who have served as inspiration along the way. William Ingram
            continues to be the authority on the records of Newington Butts -- his pioneering study
            of the neglected playhouse and key evidence for its ownership in the Canterbury
            Cathedral Archives has not yet been superseded. I have deeply appreciated his generous
            mentorship of my own work. Further stimulation came from Laurie Johnson, who shared with
            me his enthusiasm and draft sections of his remarkable book-length study,
              <title>Shakespeare's Lost Playhouse: Eleven Days at Newington Butts</title>. A
            surprising bonus this past year came from Dave Kathman whose exciting and consequential
            discovery of early records for the Curtain Playhouse shed illuminating light on Richard
            Hickes, the leaseholder of the Lurklane property in Newington. Although Dave has not yet
            published his discoveries, he has, with typical generosity, shared them with me and
            contributed to the chapter on the History of the Property.</p>

          <p>I have also benefitted in many ways (including acquisition of MS images) from the help
            of staff at the Canterbury Cathedral Archives, The London Archives, The National
            Archives and the Surrey History Centre in Woking. Travel to the archives was made
            possible by two Social Sciences and Humanities Research Council Insight Grants as well
            as Victoria College, for which I remain forever grateful. The second SSHRC Insight Grant
            has provided essential support for the publication of this edition.</p>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div xml:id="property">
        <head>History of the Property</head>
        <div>
          <p>The small village of <rs ref="eats:231618" type="Place_PA_Settlement">Newington</rs>
            lay about a mile south of the River Thames on a road running from <rs ref="eats:229053"
              type="Place_F_Bridge">London Bridge</rs> through the <rs ref="eats:229015"
              type="Place_F_Street">High Street</rs> in <rs ref="eats:36966"
              type="Place_PA_Settlement">Southwark</rs> to Arundel and Chichester on the west <rs
              ref="eats:2309" type="Place_County">Sussex</rs> coast. This route through Clapham and
            Dorking to Chichester was a heritage Roman road known as Stane Street. It was first
            surveyed in detail as a strip map (Plate 4) by John Ogilby in his
              <title>Britannia</title> road atlas in 1675, one of the two earliest maps of the area
            (see below). Another strip map (Plate 30) details a second 'principal' road just south
            of St Mary's Church turning west to Kingston upon Thames that ran through Guildford to
            Portsmouth on the Hampshire coast.</p>
          <figure>
            <graphic url="/images/OgilbyBritannia.jpg"/>
            <figDesc>Strip map from John Ogilby's Britannia depicting the road from London to
              Arundel and Chichester.</figDesc>
            <head>John Ogilby, <hi rend="italic">Britannia</hi> (1675), Plate 4: London to Arundel
              and Chichester.</head>
          </figure>
          <p>A later seventeenth century map of <rs ref="eats:490693" type="Place_PA_Manor ">Walworth manor</rs> in the Canterbury Cathedral Archives
            shows another road converging to create a triangular centre at Newington (see below).
            This road, also surveyed by Ogilby (Plate 29), connected Newington to the south through
            Walworth and Camberwell to Streatham, Croydon and beyond to Lewes and Newhaven on the
            east Sussex coast. As Laurie Johnson points out, the triangle created by the converging
            roads was known in the period as Newington Butts, possibly because of the archery butts
              nearby.<note type="foot">See <title>Shakespeare's Lost Playhouse</title>, pp
              61–2.</note></p>
          <figure>
            <graphic url="/images/WalworthManor.png"/>
            <figDesc>17th century map of Walworth manor, showcasing the meeting of three roads
              converging in a triangle in Newington</figDesc>
            <head>Manor of Walworth, 1681. Canterbury Cathedral Archives: Map 19/1.</head>
          </figure>
          <p>Like that of neighbouring Southwark, the land around Newington was low-lying and
            marshy, its maintenance requiring a drainage system, described as follows by William
            Ingram: '... at times of heavy rain, the marshes and other low areas would be covered
            with water which might remain for weeks. Drainage of this recurring surface water was
            accomplished by a variety of small ditches leading into a system of common sewers, and
            from the sewers into one or another of the main sluices which emptied into the Thames at
            points sufficiently downstream, protected by barriers to prevent backflow....' <rs
              ref="eats:357230" type="Place_F_WaterFeature">One</rs> of these ran east from Lambeth
            Marsh under the road at Newington Butts and beyond to join the <rs ref="eats:487062"
              type="Place_F_WaterFeature">sluice system</rs> on Kentish Street (now Old Kent
              Road).<note type="foot">See Ingram, “The Playhouse at Newington Butts,” p
            388.</note></p>

          <p>Newington and its parish of St Mary were contiguous with the manor of Walworth, which
            was detailed on the 1681 plan. The manor belonged to the prior and convent of Christ
            Church, Canterbury, from the eleventh century until the dissolution when it became the
            property of the <rs ref="eats:489184" type="Collective_Clergy">dean</rs> and chapter of
              <rs ref="eats:234616" type="Place_F_Church">Canterbury Cathedral</rs>, where many of
            its administrative records remain in the archives. From a Dean and Chapter Act Book
            therefore comes a damaged and elliptical notice of agreement in 1566 with <rs
              ref="eats:487271" type="Person_Male">Richard Hickes</rs> to lease a property known as
              <rs ref="eats:489100" type="Place_F_Property">Lurklane</rs> in Newington for sixty
              years.<note type="foot">For the lease see <ref
                target="https://ereed.org/records/nwbts-rid26/">Canterbury Cathedral Act
                Book</ref>.</note> Hickes was a grocer of <rs ref="eats:36947"
              type="Place_PA_Settlement">London</rs> and yeoman of the queen's guard, known to have
            had other property in St Olave's parish, Southwark.<note type="foot">Hickes died
              intestate early in 1585: see E.A.J. Honigmann and Susan Brock, <title>Playhouse Wills,
                1558–1642: An Edition of Wills by Shakespeare and His Contemporaries in the London
                Theatre </title> (Manchester, 1993), 227, and TNA: PROB 6/3, f 132v. See also
              Ingram, <title>Business of Playing</title>, 165.</note> He apparently built a house
            with enclosures at Lurklane around the time of his lease, though no evidence survives to
            show that he lived there. The exact date of this first lease (26 November 1566) and the
            extent of the property are provided by later leases: the lands involved totalled
            thirty-five acres, of which Lurklane was one of six plots.<note type="foot">For details
              of the other pieces of the property leased, see Ingram, <title>Business of
                Playing</title>, p 156.</note> Lurklane was the most western, approximately ten
            acres, bounded on the west by the main road south through Newington and on the east by
            the rest of the property. The drainage sewer leading to Duffield sluice ran along its
            southern edge.</p>

          <p>On 29 September 1573 the lease to Hickes was surrendered and a new lease redemised, for
            thirty-five acres, including Lurklane, for the shorter period of twenty-one years,
            beginning at Michaelmas 1573 (running to 1594). The reason for the redemise is not
            explained but Hickes committed to the responsibility of maintaining the sewer and any
            bridges over it along its southern boundary.<note type="foot">For the lease see <ref
                target="https://ereed.org/records/nwbts-rid27/">Canterbury Cathedral Act
                Book</ref>.</note></p>

          <p>The first evidence to indicate that Hickes subleased the plot of land known as Lurklane
            survives in a <ref target="https://ereed.org/records/nwbts-rid7/">bill of
              complaint</ref> submitted in 1577 to the Court of Requests by <rs ref="eats:202508"
              type="Person_Male">Jerome Savage</rs>, a leading player in the <rs ref="eats:12706"
              type="Collective_Troupe">earl of Warwick's troupe</rs>.<note type="foot">The bill is
              only dated 1577 but the defendants' responses were recorded in May of the same
              year.</note> The dispute in question was between Savage, then resident in Newington,
            and Richard Hickes and his son-in-law <rs ref="eats:133645" type="Person_Male">Peter
              Hunningborne</rs>. The details provided in the bill reveal that on 25 March 1576
            Hickes had agreed to a thirty-year sublease of Lurklane to Savage that replaced a
            nineteen-year lease Savage had previously purchased from a former tenant, the silkweaver
            <rs ref="eats:490791" type="Person_Male">Richard Thompson</rs>.<note type="foot"
              >Thompson may have acquired his lease from someone other than Hickes, who had only
              held the property for ten, not nineteen years, as Ingram has suggested
                (<title>Business of Playing</title>, p 163).</note> The exact year when Savage took
            up residence at Newington is therefore not on record as none of the relevant subleases
            have been discovered. However, within the year of the renewed sublease, Hickes seems to
            have changed his mind and attempted to evict Savage in favour of his son-in-law. The
            success or failure of the lawsuit is not on record but other sources for maintenance of
            the sewer along the southern edge of the property show that Savage continued his tenancy
            at least until 1578 and possibly beyond.<note type="foot"> Jerome Savage and his
              neighbour to the south, <rs ref="eats:486905" type="Person_Male">John Hilles</rs>,
              were cited in the minutes of the Surrey and Kent Commissioners for Sewers’ Court and
              required to clean the common sewer they shared several times between July 1576 and
              November 1578. See <ref target="https://ereed.org/search/?amp;facet_people_named_s=202508&amp;start=0&amp;facet_record_type_local_gov=County">Surrey and Kent Commissioners for Sewers’ Court Minutes and
              Orders</ref>.</note> By 1582 at the latest he moved to the parish
            of St Peter Westcheap, London, where Anne, one of his four daughters, was baptised on 19
            March 1581/2.<note type="foot">St Peter Westcheap Parish Register (1540–97), LA:
              P69/PET4/B/006/MS00645/001. For Jerome Savage's marriage in November 1577 to Anna
              Lansenberg and further traces of his life after 1580 see Ingram, <title>Business of
                Playing</title>, pp 177–81. His five children were named in his will, 31 January
              1586/7, TNA: PROB 11/70/119.</note> Unfortunately, the earliest St Mary Newington
            parish register does not record baptisms after 1577 so we cannot trace any other of his
            five children who might have been born in Newington after Savage's marriage that year.
            Although we lack conclusive evidence, it appears that Savage either chose to move from
            Lurklane after the breakup of Warwick's men in 1580 or that Richard Hickes finally
            succeeded in evicting him in favour of his son-in law, Peter Hunningborne, around that
            time. In June 1582 Hunningborne was granted the rest of the garden and grounds adjoining
            the <rs ref="eats:227741" type="Place_F_Playhouse">'playe house'</rs> not comprised in
            his former lease, for twenty-one years starting on 29 September 1582.<note type="foot">
              See the <ref target="https://ereed.org/records/nwbts-rid3/">Canterbury Cathedral
                Act Book</ref>.</note> The date and record of the 'former' sublease to Hunningborne
            have not been found.</p>

          <p>It is worth noting that a 'playhouse' is so named for the first time in 1582. Savage's
            1577 bill of complaint indicates that there was 'one messuage with the app<hi
              rend="italic">ur</hi>tenan<hi rend="italic">au</hi>nc<hi rend="italic">es</hi>' on the
            Lurklane site when he assumed the sublease from Richard Thompson. He also mentions that
            an orchard and garden were on the premises. Similarly, Hunningborne and Hickes in their
            answers refer to 'one messuage or tenement' but neither refers to a playhouse as such or
            to a second building that might have been erected for the purpose at Lurklane. It is
            clear, however, that they were linking Savage's occupation at the property with his
            profession as a player and suggesting that his neighbours objected to his residency
            because of his playmaking activities.<note type="foot">See <ref
                target="https://ereed.org/records/nwbts-rid7/">Court of Requests: Jerome Savage
                v. Peter Hunningborne et al</ref>.</note></p>

          <p>The name of Peter Hunningborne is therefore associated with the Lurklane property from
            the early 1580s.<note type="foot">See <ref
                target="https://ereed.org/records/nwbts-rid3/">Canterbury Cathedral Act
                Book</ref>.</note> He is also named as occupant there in the next lease on record in
            the Canterbury archives although the lease for the rest of the thirty-five acre property
            held by Hickes had been granted to <rs ref="eats:486966" type="Person_Male">Thomas
              Cuckowe</rs>, a Southwark <rs ref="eats:21077" type="Collective_Occupations">innholder</rs>, on 30 September 1582. That section of the
            property was subsequently redemised to his son, <rs ref="eats:487187" type="Person_Male"
              >Richard Cuckowe</rs> on 30 November 1590.<note type="foot">See the 1590 <ref
                target="https://ereed.org/records/nwbts-rid5/">Indentures of Lease</ref>.</note>
            The evidence suggests that Hunningborne remained at Lurklane until 1594 when the dean
            and chapter agreed to lease the property to <rs ref="eats:488277" type="Person_Male"
              >Paul Buck</rs> for twenty-one years on condition that 'he shall convert the
            playehouse to some other [house] vse vppon the saide grownde and not suffer anie plaies
            there after michelmas nexte.'<note type="foot"> See the 1594 <ref
                target="https://ereed.org/records/nwbts-rid4/"> Canterbury Cathedral Chapter Act
                Book</ref>.</note></p>

          <p>It remains to outline what can be discerned from the limited evidence about the fate of
            the early playhouse that ceased to function as such after Buck met the terms of the new
            lease. Paul Buck's new lease of the property in 1594 depended on the conversion of the
            playhouse for other uses but as late as 1599, a Kent and Surrey Commission of Sewers
            report recalled the building as follows: 'Item we fynd that the sewar leadinge from the
            houses where the old playe house did stand att Newington all alongest vnto the Bridge
            goyng from Barmondsey cross the high waye vnto saint Thomas Watering<hi rend="italic"
              >es</hi> is needefull to be cast clensed and scowred...'<note type="foot">See the <ref
                target="https://ereed.org/records/nwbts-rid17/">report for 5 October
              1599</ref>.</note> It would seem, therefore, that the 'old playe house' may have been
            demolished by that time, with other houses built on the site.</p>

          <p>Disappointingly, archaeological discoveries on the site are unlikely as it lies below
            the demolished Elephant and Castle shopping centre by the busy traffic roundabout, an
            area now completely redeveloped.<note type="foot">See Julian Bowsher,
                <title>Shakespeare's London Theatreland: Archaeology, History and Drama</title>
              (London, 2012), 54.</note> Laurie Johnson has pinpointed the entrance to the playhouse
            on the frontage along what is now Walworth Road: 'public entry to the Playhouse would
            have been gained at the same location a modern shopper would find the market stalls
            along one corner of the Elephant and Castle shopping centre, south of the ring
              road.’<note type="foot">Johnson, <title>Shakespeare's Lost Playhouse</title>, pp
              62–73, assesses the evidence, proposing that the geolocation coordinates would be
              51.4946-0.0999 (51o 29'41" N, 0o 06'00" W (p 73).</note></p>
          <figure>
            <graphic url="/images/Lurklane.png"/>
            <figDesc>A close-up of the Walworth manor map, with an added red square to highlight the
              site of the Lurklane property</figDesc>
            <head>The Lurklane site on the 1681 Walworth manor plan, as confirmed by Laurie Johnson,
                <hi rend="italic">Shakespeare’s Lost Playhouse</hi>. Canterbury Cathedral Archives:
              Map 19/1.</head>
          </figure>

          <p>A description of the playhouse building has not been discovered but Buck's 6 April 1595
            lease provides the dimensions of the Lurklane property as a whole. Both the northern
            edge and the southern edge along the common sewer were 48 yards, while the boundary at
            the west along the main Newington road was 33 yards and the eastern edge a longer
            stretch of 42 yards.<note type="foot">See the 1595 <ref
                target="https://ereed.org/records/nwbts-rid6/">Indenture of Lease</ref>, f
              266.</note> While Savage was in residence, there is only evidence of one house or
            messuage on the site. When Hunningborne succeeded in taking over the lease, the house at
            Lurklane was referred to as 'the playe house' with a garden and grounds adjoining but no
            other building on the grounds was referred to.<note type="foot">See <ref
                target="https://ereed.org/records/nwbts-rid3/">Canterbury Cathedral Chapter Act
                Book</ref>, f 27v.</note></p>

          <p>However, almost a decade later, in 1590, the lease to Richard Cuckowe of the original
            thirty-five acre property exempting Lurklane indicates more buildings, now cited as
            '...the sayd land<hi rend="italic">es</hi> now called the playhowse w<hi rend="italic"
              >i</hi>th all howses gardens or orchard<hi rend="italic">es</hi> thervnto
            adioyninge...and in thoccupac<hi rend="italic">i</hi>on of one Peter Honingborne or his
              assignes.'<note type="foot">See the 1590 <ref
                target="https://ereed.org/records/nwbts-rid5/">Indenture of Lease</ref>.</note>
            We know from different sources around the same time, that the playhouse was functioning,
            presumably under Hunningborne's management, but whether he had built a separate
            residence on the property between 1582 and 1590 is not on record.</p>

          <p>Who built the playhouse at Newington Butts and whether it was converted from an
            original building or newly erected remains subject for speculation. Ida Darlington's
            suggestion that Richard Hickes built the playhouse at some point between 1566 and 1580
            is questionable but the house that he did build may have been adapted for performance
              purposes.<note type="foot">See Darlington, 'The manor of Walworth,’ in <title>Survey
                of London:</title>, pp. 81–90. <title>British History Online </title><ref
                target="http://www.british-history.ac.uk/survey-london/vol25/pp81-90"
                >http://www.british-history.ac.uk/survey-london/vol25/pp81-90</ref>, accessed 23
              February 2024.</note> Ingram argued, based on later records, that Hickes' original
            house remained a residence, with its entrance as cited in the 1576 sewer commission
            record by the grate of the common sewer at the south end of the Lurklane property.<note
              type="foot">See the 13 July 1576 entry in the <ref
                target="https://ereed.org/records/nwbts-rid13/">Surrey and Kent Commissioners
                for Sewers’ Court Minutes and Orders </ref>. See also Ingram, <title>Business of
                Playing</title>, pp 162, 243–5.</note></p>

          <p>David Kathman has discovered new evidence about Richard Hickes' involvement in the
            origins of the <rs ref="eats:228083" type="Place_F_Playhouse">Curtain Playhouse</rs>
            north of the river that teases further thought about Hickes' attempt to evict Savage
            from Newington Butts in the same period. A relevant detail has emerged from his search
            of Common Pleas lawsuits. In Trinity term 1571, Thomas Frampton, citizen and
            clothworker, brought debt cases against George Gascoigne of London or of Walthamstowe,
            Essex, gentleman, and 'Ric<hi rend="italic">ard</hi>um Hickes nuper de london Inholder
            alias d<hi rend="italic">ictu</hi>m Rychard Hyckes of Newington in the countye of Surrey
              Inholder’.<note type="foot">TNA: CP40/1298, rot. 1878. Quoting from note 70 in
              Kathman's unpublished paper, 'The Origins and Early History of the Curtain Playhouse':
              'The case appears at least twice in the plea rolls: in Michaelmas term 1571, when the
              court issued a capias writ against Gascoigne and Hickes ... and in Hilary term 1572,
              when the court issued an exigent writ against them (TNA CP40/1301, rot. 1031).'</note>
            Although Hickes' inn is not specifically identified with the Lurklane property, a good
            case can be made for that site on the principal road south from Southwark rather than on
            the other acres to the east leased from the Dean and Chapter. In fact, many decades ago,
            T. Fairman Ordish suggested, given its location, that the playhouse at Newington Butts
            would have been 'a well-frequented inn'.<note type="foot"><title>Early London Theatres.
                In the Fields</title> (London, 1899), 146.</note> However, Ingram noted that 'The
            suitability of Savage's location was attested by the later success of the famous inn and
            coaching house, the <rs ref="eats:49072" type="Place_F_VictuallingHouse">Elephant and Castle</rs>, located only a few yards away from the site of
            the playhouse' but discounted Ordish's conjecture for lack of corroborating evidence at
            the time.<note type="foot">Ingram, <title>Business of Playing</title>, 170, n
            37.</note></p>

          <p>If the 'house' at Lurklane subleased by Jerome Savage was indeed an inn, this type of
            venue could have been familiar to him as an actor with provincial or London performance
            experience. Kathman has written about the use of four London inns by acting troupes in
            the 1570s, and although period evidence for provincial inns is sporadic – innkeepers'
            records are among the less likely to survive – we know that both innyards and upper
            indoor rooms were used.<note type="foot">See Kathman, 'Inn-Yard Playhouses,'
                <title>Oxford Handbook of Early Modern Theatre</title> (Oxford, 2009), 153–67. For
              sixteenth and early seventeenth-century provincial inns, see, eg, <ref
                target="https://library2.utm.utoronto.ca/otra/reed/content/red-lion-inn">the use of
                the innyard at the <rs ref="eats:228711" type="Place_F_VictuallingHouse">Red Lion</rs> at Norwich</ref>, and for indoor space, an inn at
              Ludlow, REED: <title>Shropshire</title>, J.A.B. Somerset (ed), vol 1 (Toronto, 1994),
              110–12.</note> We cannot document appearances at Lurklane by Jerome Savage's troupe,
            Warwick's men, but it seems likely that they might well have used the space, especially
            in the autumn season leading up to their regular appearances at Court between 1575 and
            1580. It is possible that the house was adapted for performance purposes at the time.
            Both Hunningborne and Hickes mention the former's attempt to view reparations in
            progress there in 1577, though the door was shut tight against him by its
              occupants.<note type="foot">See <ref
                target="https://ereed.org/records/nwbts-rid7/">Court of Requests: Jerome Savage
                v. Peter Hunningborne et al</ref>, mbs 1 and 2. Ingram, <title>Business of
                Playing</title>, p 167 describes the scene vividly, though he assumes that there was
              both a playhouse and a dwelling house on the site by that time.</note> Were both the
            repairs and the protective occupants connected with Savage's residence there and some of
            his fellow actors?</p>

          <p>We might ask whether much adaptation would have been needed for Savage and his company
            to use such a building in the mid-1570s? While resident there, Savage was assessed in a
            lay subsidy at £3 in goods and in 1582 at £3 3s, this time at his new location in St
            Peter Westcheap parish.<note type="foot">See TNA: E179/185/310 (11 July 1576), for
              Newington and E179/251/16 (August 1582) for St Peter's, London.</note> By contrast,
            Richard Hickes, assessed at £18 in fees at Newington in 1576, was a wealthier man
            according to Ingram who has documented other instances and other sources for Hickes'
            prosperity. That financial capacity as well as his personal interest in theatre business
            uncovered by Kathman could be considerations as we revisit the question of the
            development of a dedicated playhouse at Newington Butts.<note type="foot">See Ingram,
                <title>Business of Playing</title>, pp 154–5.</note></p>

          <p>It now seems possible that Richard Hickes may have had the motivation and funding to
            undertake such a building <hi rend="italic">c</hi> 1580 in collaboration with his
            son-in-law who continued to manage its use for performance until the 1590s. Unless more
            relevant discoveries are made, perhaps we should think of Newington Butts as a converted
            inn playhouse at Lurklane, rather than as a second building erected for that specific
            purpose, with Hunningborne residing in one of the other houses on the site mentioned in
            the 1590 lease to Richard Cuckowe.</p>

          <p>Johnson has written at greater length about the physical characteristics of the
            playhouse which he suggests was converted around 1575 by Savage from a second house on
            the property built earlier by Hickes. Without corroborating documents, his description
            of the size, interior structure and seating capacity remains speculative, and he admits
            to making 'some bold claims.'<note type="foot">See <title>Shakespeare's Lost
                Playhouse</title>, pp 75–81.</note> More conservatively, it is possible to agree
            that the original building was likely rectangular in structure rather than polygonal, as
            some purpose-built playhouses were. The next chapter will pick up the history of the
            playhouse as a twenty-year entertainment venue.</p>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div xml:id="playhouse">

        <head>History of the Playhouse</head>
        <div>

          <p>Although the <rs ref="eats:227741" type="Place_F_Playhouse">playhouse</rs> at <rs
              ref="eats:231618" type="Place_PA_Settlement">Newington</rs> was one of the first on
            record in the wider <rs ref="eats:36947" type="Place_PA_Settlement">London</rs> area,
            its location used to be dismissed too easily as 'less advantageous than the Theatre's'
            or known for 'the tediousness of the way.'<note type="foot">Gurr, <title>Shakespearian
                Playing Companies</title>, p 171; 'the tediousness of the way' has been often cited
              from a <ref target="https://ereed.org/records/rosep-ridm90700072"><hi rend="italic"
                  >c</hi> 1590 privy council order</ref> (Dulwich College: MS I, box C). See for
              example, E.K. Chambers, <title>Elizabethan Stage</title>, vol 2, p 405.</note>
            However, anyone writing on the history of the playhouse owes a debt of gratitude to
            William Ingram, whose groundbreaking work on the varied documentary evidence surviving
            for personnel associated with the playhouse was published in definitive form in
              <title>The Business of Playing: The Beginnings of the Adult Professional Theater in
              Elizabethan London</title> (Ithaca and London, 1992), 150–81, 243–5. Laurie Johnson's
            full-length study of <title>Shakespeare's Lost Playhouse: Eleven Days at Newington
              Butts</title> (New York and London, 2018) has contributed further and persuasively
            located the playhouse site with more precision after extensive study of
            seventeenth-century and later maps, as well as contemporary leases.</p>

          <p>Admittedly, the playhouse history is clouded by gaps in our knowledge of its
            establishment, some of the troupes who used it, and most of the plays that were
            performed there. The leaseholders did not leave us any memoranda, account books, or
            letters to detail the years of activity before the <rs ref="eats:489184"
              type="Collective_Clergy">dean</rs> and chapter of Canterbury determined to make its
            demolition a condition of the new lease on the property granted to <rs ref="eats:488277"
              type="Person_Male">Paul Buck</rs> in 1595. Furthermore, the parish of St Mary
            Newington, where it was situated, has left us only one year of vestry minutes (1583–4)
            from the sixteenth century<note type="foot">Southwark Local History Library: MN/1/1/1.
              Churchwardens' accounts begin in 1632.</note> and its parish registers of baptisms and
            burials cover only the years 1561–77 before lapsing until 1609.<note type="foot">LA:
              P92/MRY/001 includes marriages. P92/MRY/002, a register of marriages only, runs from
              1561–1611.</note> Following Ida Darlington's lead,<note type="foot"> See 'The Manor of
              Walworth,' <title>St George's Fields, The Survey of London</title>, pp 81–90.</note>
            Ingram described in more detail several important leases for the property in the
            archives of the Dean and Chapter at <rs ref="eats:234616" type="Place_F_Church"
              >Canterbury Cathedral</rs>. A fresh examination of available sources there has turned
            up only one addition, for 1582. A destructive fire at the Cathedral Audit House in 1670
            has left us with some relevant chapter act books and registers, seriously damaged, and
            others too fragile for access at this time. Given the limitations of the documentary
            evidence surviving, the historical outline of the playhouse history that follows is
            necessarily tentative while the temptation to speculate beyond the clues provided by
            records available has been resisted as much as possible.</p>

          <p>Fifteen-seventy-five was probably a significant year in the life of the actor, <rs
              ref="eats:202508" type="Person_Male">Jerome Savage</rs>. With his fellow players in
            the <rs ref="eats:12706" type="Collective_Troupe">earl of Warwick's troupe</rs>, he was
            invited to perform before Queen Elizabeth, first during the Shrovetide season at <rs
              ref="eats:227912" type="Place_F_Residence">Richmond</rs>, and then twice during the
            Christmas season, on 26 December and 1 January 1575/6 at <rs ref="eats:228103"
              type="Place_F_Residence">Hampton Court</rs>. When Warwick's men received their reward
            for both of these, Savage was named as a payee, together with the actor brothers, <rs
              ref="eats:180666" type="Person_Male">John</rs> and <rs ref="eats:180596"
              type="Person_Male">Laurence Dutton</rs>, a signal that all three were regarded as the
            lead players in the company.<note type="foot">For payments to Warwick's Men in
              Shrovetide 1574/5 and the year following, 1575/6, see David Cook and F.P. Wilson
              (eds), <title>Collections</title> 6 (Oxford, 1962), 9–11. A third performance in
              Shrovetide 1575/6 was on 5 March but only Laurence Dutton was named as payee.</note>
            The plays are not named but their inclusion on the Court calendar marks the beginning of
            a steady run of royal favour until 1580.<note type="foot">See John H. Astington,
                <title>English Court Theatre 1558–1642</title> (Cambridge, 1999), 227–9.</note></p>

          <p><rs ref="eats:12536" type="Person_Nobility">Ambrose Dudley</rs>, earl of Warwick, is
            known to have patronized an acting troupe between 1561 and 1564 but a decade had elapsed
            since their appearance at Court and on the road in the provinces so we may assume that
            the troupe of 1575 was a relatively new formation.<note type="foot">For the first troupe
              patronized by Warwick see <ref
                target="https://library2.utm.utoronto.ca/otra/reed/content/earl-warwicks-players"
                  ><title>Patrons and Performances</title> website</ref>, Troupe itinerary.</note>
            The invitation to perform at Court came about a year after the date of Dudley's
            appointment to the privy council in September 1573. As Ingram has pointed out, other
            influential members of the privy council, including his brother, <rs ref="eats:44753"
              type="Person_Nobility">the earl of Leicester</rs>, patronized playing troupes, perhaps
            providing incentive for him to do the same.<note type="foot"> Ingram, <title>Business of
                Playing</title>, p 172.</note> His players can be found in the provinces at several
            locations in 1575 as well, at Coventry, nearby Stratford and Leicester, possibly among
            expenses related to the Queen's progress through the West Midlands that summer.<note
              type="foot">See REED's <ref
                target="https://library2.utm.utoronto.ca/otra/reed/content/earl-warwicks-players"
                  ><title>Patrons and Performances</title> website</ref>, for the Troupe itinerary
              and <ref target="https://ereed.org/records/staff-ridm58197920/"><title>REED
                  Online</title></ref>. The payment to Warwick's players that survives only through
              John Nichol's transcription of expenses paid by the city of <rs ref="eats:3702"
                type="Place_PA_Settlement">Lichfield</rs> at the time of the royal visit, 27 July to
              3 August, is somewhat ambiguous, noted as among other extracts for the year's charges
              'appearing to be connected with the Queen's Visit.' The appearance at Stratford has
              not yet been published in the REED series but can be found in the <title>Minutes and
                Accounts of the Corporation of Stratford-upon-Avon and Other Records
                1553–1620</title>, Richard Savage (ed), Publications of the Dugdale Society, vol 2
              (Oxford, 1924), 105. Worth noting also is an earlier payment to Warwick's 'servants'
              for a play at Tavistock in Devon sometime during the Michaelmas 1572–3 accounting
              year.</note></p>

          <p>Intriguingly, in the same period Jerome Savage apparently decided to take over the
            sublease of the Newington property at <rs ref="eats:489100" type="Place_F_Property"
              >Lurklane</rs> from the previous resident, the silk weaver, <rs ref="eats:490791"
              type="Person_Male">Richard Thompson</rs>. Furthermore, he found cause to negotiate new
            terms for a thirty-year extension on the lease, starting 25 March 1576.<note type="foot"
              >See <ref target="https://ereed.org/records/nwbts-rid7/">Court of Requests: Jerome
                Savage v. Peter Hunningborne et al</ref>, Bill of Complaint by Savage, mb 3.</note>
            As noted in the previous chapter, he was clearly held responsible for cleaning the sewer
            along its southern boundary there by July 1576, when he first appears ordered to do so
            along with his neighbour, <rs ref="eats:486905" type="Person_Male">John
              Hilles</rs>.<note type="foot">See the <ref
                target="https://ereed.org/records/nwbts-rid13/">Surrey and Kent Commissioners
                for Sewers’ Court Minutes and Orders</ref> entry for 13 July, f 87v.</note></p>

          <p>William Ingram was the first to make the persuasive case for Jerome Savage, actor and
            lease-holder, as the originator of performances at Newington Butts. Although we cannot
            document appearances there by his troupe, Warwick's Men, it seems likely that they might
            have used the space by one of the principal main roads south from London, especially in
            the autumn season leading up to their regular appearances at Court between 1575 and
            1580. In the spring of 1577, Savage was compelled to defend his right to the tenancy at
            Lurklane against <rs ref="eats:487271" type="Person_Male">his landlord</rs>'s claim that
            he had defaulted on the first rental payment required that year. After he filed his bill
            of complaint to the Court of Requests, both Richard Hickes and his son-in-law, <rs
              ref="eats:133645" type="Person_Male">Peter Hunningborne</rs> responded, in defence of
            their position, that he was culpable and should vacate the premises so that Hunningborne
            could move in. In his answer, Hunningborne referred to Savage as a 'verrie lewed
            feallowe and liveth by noe other trade then playinge of staige plaies and Interlevd<hi
              rend="italic">es</hi> to the knoledge of this defend<hi rend="italic">an</hi>t and for
            his lewde and lose lief hath Comaundement from the ordenarye as is Crediblie reported to
            avoide out of that parishe w<hi rend="italic">hi</hi>ch his lewed behavior would sone
            make an honest man werie of so weked ... tenant And so muche the more because [the mor
            because] the honest neighboures in that place doe so mislike his behavior as they will
            not suffer hime to Dwell there anie longer....'<note type="foot">See the <ref
                target="https://ereed.org/records/nwbts-rid7/#nwbts-rid7-mb2">Answer of Peter
                Hunningborne, 10 May 1577</ref>.</note></p>

          <p>Whether or not Savage's activities at Newington were subject to so much local
            disapproval can be debated: both Hunningborne and Hickes may have been arguing in their
            own defence without scruples. Subsequent developments suggest that neither man was
            opposed to the emerging business of entertainment. Although the court records are not
            explicit that the building was being used as a performance venue, it seems likely that
            this may have been the case. A privy council letter sent in May 1580 to the <rs
              ref="eats:160152" type="Collective_Office">JPs of Surrey</rs> reiterating their order
            for restraint of playing during time of plague is more direct: '...certen players do
            playe sunderie daies eu<hi rend="italic">er</hi>y weeke at newington butt<hi
              rend="italic">es</hi> on that p<hi rend="italic">ar</hi>te of Surr<hi rend="italic"
              >ie</hi> w<hi rend="italic">i</hi>thout the Iurisdicc<hi rend="italic">i</hi>on of the
            said L<hi rend="italic">or</hi>d Maior contrary to therr l<hi rend="italic"
              >ordships</hi> order....'<note type="foot">See the <ref
                target="https://ereed.org/records/nwbts-rid11/">Privy Council Letter to the JPs
                of Surrey</ref>.</note> Who the players were is less certain but it is worth noting
            that the last recorded performance at court by the earl of Warwick’s players was 1
            January 1579/80, so Savage and his troupe might still have been using the venue during
            the spring immediately following.<note type="foot">For the Court performance payment see
              TNA: E351/542, f 8.</note></p>

          <p>As outlined in the previous chapter, Savage remained on record as a tenant at Lurklane
            at least until late 1578 so it would seem that Hickes' attempt to oust him had not been
            successful, initially at least. Warwick's Men disappear from the provincial and Court
            records after 1580 and Savage himself relocated to London at some point by 1582.<note
              type="foot">For Savage's marriage and later life see Ingram, <title>Business of
                Playing</title>, pp 177–81. There is no indication from records available that he
              continued his acting career after moving to London.</note> Was the restraint of
            playing during the time of infection from spring until Michaelmas in 1580 a deciding
              factor?<note type="foot">The privy council moved to restrict playing on 17 April 1580
              (TNA: PC2/12, p 812).</note> As David Kathman has outlined, the opening of this decade
            was a difficult time for those in the acting profession: the five-month plague closure
            of 1580 was followed by another in 1581 that ran from 10 July until early December.<note
              type="foot">Kathman, 'The London Playing Bust of the Early 1580s and the Economics of
              Elizabethan Theater,' <title>Shakespeare Studies </title> 45 (2017), 47–8.</note> The
            Dutton brothers are known to have moved to another troupe, newly formed under the
            patronage of <rs ref="eats:50556" type="Person_Nobility">Edward de Vere, seventeenth
              earl of Oxford</rs>, by April 1580 when Laurence Dutton was committed to the <rs
              ref="eats:228426" type="Place_F_PlaceOfPunishment">Marshalsea</rs> for <rs
              ref="eats:45465" type="CrimesMisdemeanors">his involvement in an affray</rs> at the
              <rs ref="eats:228217" type="Place_F_Playhouse">Theatre</rs>.<note type="foot">See
              Chambers, <title>Elizabethan Stage</title>, vol 2, p 100.</note> By June <rs
              ref="eats:50533" type="Collective_Troupe">Oxford's Men</rs> were on the provincial
            road at Cambridge but they were not invited to play at Court in this year or those
            immediately following.<note type="foot"> For Oxford's players on tour in the provinces
              see REED's <ref
                target="https://library2.utm.utoronto.ca/otra/reed/content/earl-oxfords-players"
                  ><title>Patrons and Performances</title> website</ref>; Gurr, <title>Shakespearian
                Playing Companies</title>, pp 307–8, 313–14; and Johnson, 'Who Performed at
              Newington Butts in 1586?' <title>Early Theatre</title> 21.2 (2018), 32–3.</note></p>

          <p>Ingram has suggested that Oxford's men may have used the performance space at Newington
            Butts after Warwick's company disbanded, given the Duttons' familiarity with the venue,
            but this remains a possibility that cannot be verified.<note type="foot">Ingram,
                <title>Business of Playing</title>, pp 174–5. Johnson agrees but notes that Chambers
                (<title>Elizabethan Stage</title>, vol 2, p 100), and Gurr (<title>Shakespearian
                Playing Companies</title>, pp 307–8) differ: 'One school of thought holds that the
              newly formed Oxford’s Players relocated their business to <rs ref="eats:226943"
                type="Place_PA_Settlement">Shoreditch</rs>, since Laurence Dutton and Robert Leveson
              were imprisoned on 13 April for their part in an affray at the Theatre three days
              earlier, supposedly indicating their occupation of that venue' ('Who Performed at
              Newington Butts?,' pp 31–2).</note> In fact, the number and identities of the
            companies performing at the playhouse during the 1580s are unknown. Laurie Johnson has
            proposed, by process of elimination of other known candidates, that <rs ref="eats:48635"
              type="Collective_Troupe">Leicester's Men</rs> was the company that may have been the
            target for the privy council's restraint in May 1586 by playing there.<note type="foot">
              Johnson, 'Who Performed at Newington Butts in 1586?,' pp 29–48.</note> While the privy
            council letter to the JPs of Surrey does not name a particular company, it does indicate
            that the playhouse was still in use, the first evidence that Peter Hunningborne may have
            taken up its management after Jerome Savage departed for London.<note type="foot">See
                <ref target="https://ereed.org/records/nwbts-rid9/">Privy Council Orders
                regarding Newington</ref>.</note></p>

          <p>Lacking an equivalent to <rs ref="eats:129736" type="Person_Male">Henslowe</rs>'s diary
            during the first decade of operations at Newington, we can only speculate about the
            plays that might have been performed there. Those generally known from the repertory of
            Warwick's Men are limited to the plays performed at Court between 1575–80. There are
            five whose titles are recorded, though their texts and the names of their authors have
            been lost: <rs ref="eats:490962" type="Drama_TitledWork"><title>The Painter's Daughter</title></rs> (26 December 1576), <rs ref="eats:490982" type="Drama_TitledWork"><title>The Irish
                Knight</title></rs> (18 February 1577), <rs ref="eats:491002" type="Drama_TitledWork"><title>The Three Sisters of Mantua</title></rs> (26
            December 1578), <rs ref="eats:491022" type="Drama_TitledWork"><title>The Knight in the Burning Rock</title></rs> (1 March 1579) and
            <rs ref="eats:491042" type="Drama_TitledWork"><title>The Four Sons of Fabius</title></rs> (1 January 1580).<note type="foot">See further
              Wiggins and Richardson (eds), <title>British Drama</title>, vol 2: 1567–1589: 'The
              Painter's Daughter' (#600), 'The Irish Knight' (#608), 'The Three Sisters of Mantua'
              (#652), 'The Knight in the Burning Rock' (#659), and 'The Four Sons of Fabius'
              (#678).</note> If the building there was used during the usual rehearsal period for
            these prestigious performances before the Queen, then we at least have a glimpse of what
            Warwick's troupe might have offered to the general public.</p>

          <p>At the end of the first decade more direct evidence is available, thanks to the
            remarkable archive of Henslowe-Alleyn papers at Dulwich College. An undated privy
            council warrant directed to the JPs and other authorities in Surrey survives there to
            reveal that a restraint on playing at the <rs ref="eats:157260" type="Place_F_Playhouse"
              >Rose</rs> (opened in 1587) had forced the resident <rs ref="eats:153197"
              type="Collective_Troupe">Lord Strange's Men</rs> to relocate for three days to the
            only other playhouse south of the Thames, at Newington, although for unknown reasons.
            Both the players and the London <rs ref="eats:137174" type="Collective_Occupation"
              >watermen</rs> ardently petitioned members of the privy council, including the
            watermen's patron, the <rs ref="eats:25940" type="Collective_Office">lord admiral</rs>,
            to allow them to return to the Rose. The warrant grants release from the temporary
            restraint, noting '...wee are satisfied that by reason of the tediousnes of the waie and
              y<hi rend="italic">a</hi>t of longe tyme plaies haue not there bene vsed on working
            daies' among their reasons for doing so.<note type="foot">See <ref
                target="https://ereed.org/records/rosep-ridm90700072/">Warrant from the Privy
                Council</ref>. See, for example, Chambers, <title>Elizabethan Stage</title>, vol 4,
              p 311, who suggests a date of July 1592 following the restraint of playing at the Rose
              from 23 June 1592, after the <rs ref="eats:361644" type="Event_PublicDisturbance"
                >Feltmakers' apprentices' recent riot</rs> in <rs ref="eats:36966"
                type="Place_PA_Settlement">Southwark</rs>.</note> The speculative dating of 1592 or
            1593 has been typically assigned to the petition from Strange's Men to the privy council
            and the watermen's companion petition to the <rs ref="eats:25845" type="Person_Nobility">lord admiral</rs>, as well as the privy
            council's response.<note type="foot">See further <title>Rose Playhouse</title>, <ref
                target="https://ereed.org/records/rosep-ridm90916024/">Petition to the Privy Council
                by Lord Strange's Men</ref> and <ref
                target="https://ereed.org/records/rosep-ridm90877112/">Petition to the Lord Admiral
                by the Watermen</ref>.</note> However, Alan H. Nelson has studied the seventeen
            signatures on the watermen’s petition, discovering from his St Saviour's parish register
            research that two of those signing were dead by 1591.<note type="foot"> Nelson has not
              yet published his 2012 conference paper, ‘Philip Henslowe and the Bankside Watermen: A
              Fresh Look at Three Familiar Documents.’ For now, see further Manley and MacLean,
                <title>Strange’s Men</title>, pp 50–1.</note> Given that the earliest of the two
            men's death dates was January 1590/1, the previous summer of 1590 therefore becomes a
            viable date for the petitions and just possibly, the year before.</p>

          <p>The circumstances for negotiating temporary use of the playhouse at Newington and the
            plays performed are not recorded, unlike the later details available for several days of
            performances there by the <rs ref="eats:223085" type="Collective_Troupe">lord
              chamberlain's</rs> and <rs ref="eats:25827" type="Collective_Troupe">lord
              admiral's</rs> troupes in 1594. It is possible that the difference in the
            documentation can be attributed to the dating of the earlier petitions and the privy
            council warrant to the period before Philip Henslowe began to record dates and
            performances in his diary, which only starts in 1591.<note type="foot">See further
                <title>Rose Playhouse</title>, <ref
                target="https://ereed.org/collections/rosep/background-henslowe/">Introduction:
                History of the Playhouse</ref>.</note> We know that Peter Hunningborne remained the
            leaseholder at Lurklane until 1594, so presumably he would have been responsible for any
            rentals of the playhouse at Newington but the cost to Henslowe or Strange's Men cannot
            be discovered.<note type="foot">For the plays in Strange's Men's repertory, see
                <title>Rose Playhouse</title>, <ref
                target="https://ereed.org/collections/rosep/appendix-3/">Appendix 3</ref>. See the
              Introduction: History of the Property for the dates of Hunningborne's tenancy at
              Lurklane.</note></p>

          <p>In June 1594 more substantial evidence reveals that the companies, newly patronized by
              <rs ref="eats:123685" type="Person_Male">Henry Carey, the lord chamberlain</rs>, and
              Charles Howard, the lord admiral,
            played for ten days between 3 and 13 June at Newington Butts. After that date Admiral's
            Men moved to longer-term residence at the Rose and the Chamberlain's Men found a home
            north of the river at the Theatre. Laurie Johnson has written a book-length study of
            this remarkable final chapter in the life of the playhouse at Newington, to which the
            reader is referred for more extensive discussion of the companies at this time of their
            formation and the plays performed during this brief period: <title>Shakespeare's Lost
              Playhouse: Eleven Days at Newington Butts</title>. He ventures the intriguing, if
            admittedly speculative, suggestion that adverse weather conditions in the spring season
            of April and May 1594 may have spurred Henslowe to look for an alternative venue on
            higher ground, less vulnerable to the flooding of the River Thames at Bankside. Based on
            research in other period witnesses such as Stow's <title>Annales</title> and the diarist
            Richard Stonley, he suggests that 'ongoing rain and spates of high waters took their
            toll on Henslowe's Bankside venue, forcing him to consider viable alternatives, and
            Newington's indoor venue on high ground would seem to have been just that.'<note
              type="foot">See further <title>Shakespeare's Lost Playhouse</title>, pp
            140–5.</note></p>

          <p>The plays offered during the brief period at Newington were varied, including three
            tragedies, two histories, a comedy and a biblical play. Four of the texts are lost but
            three survive and two of these can be surely identified as the work of Marlowe and
            Shakespeare. Marlowe's <rs ref="eats:199979" type="Drama_TitledWork"><title>The Jew of Malta</title></rs>, performed twice, was one of the
            most popular plays in the period, originally in the possession of Strange's Men before
            moving to Admiral's by May 1594. Shakespeare's <rs ref="eats:199938" type="Drama_TitledWork"><title>Titus Andronicus</title></rs>, also
            performed twice, may have originated with <rs ref="eats:199956" type="Collective_Troupe"
              >Pembroke's Men</rs> though its title page also named <rs ref="eats:175847" type="Collective_Troupe">Derby's Men</rs> and <rs ref="eats:175555"
              type="Collective_Troupe">Sussex's Men</rs>, a puzzling attribution that remains a
            subject for debate, whether the three companies named performed the play in succession
            or in temporary amalgamation.<note type="foot">For details of the debate, see Manley and
              MacLean, <title>Lord Strange</title>, pp 106–10, and Johnson, <title>Shakespeare's
                Lost Playhouse</title>, pp 153–60.</note>
            <rs ref="eats:489374" type="Drama_TitledWork"><title>The Taming of a Shrewe</title></rs> may have been Shakespeare's play, for Pembroke's
            Men originally, but another play by that title survives as a possible candidate.<note
              type="foot">See further Wiggins and Richardson (eds), <title>British Drama</title>,
              vol 2: 1567–1589, #916, #955 and Johnson, <title>Shakespeare's Lost Playhouse</title>,
              pp 191–200.</note> Repertory scholars generally agree that the <rs ref="eats:489534" type="Drama_TitledWork"><title>Hamlet</title></rs>
            performed once was more likely the lost play attributed to Thomas Kyd than Shakespeare's
            later play on the same subject.<note type="foot"> Johnson, however, disagrees, arguing
              for an earlier, now lost version of the play by Shakespeare; see <title>Shakespeare's
                Lost Playhouse</title>, 184–90.</note></p>

          <p>There has been some debate about whether the new companies performed individually on
            separate days or together, in temporary amalgamation.<note type="foot">See, for example,
              Johnson, <title>Shakespeare's Lost Playhouse</title>, pp 145–6. Carol Chillington
              Rutter has taken an opposing view, <title>Documents of the Rose Playhouse</title>, p
              83.</note> Henslowe's wording is admittedly ambiguous but it seems less likely during
            this period of reconstitution and recruitment that the players would join forces and
            pool some of their playtexts before moving to establish themselves at separate theatres.
            Following the brief performance schedule at Newington, <rs ref="eats:191047" type="Drama_TitledWork"><title>Belin Dun</title></rs> and
            <rs ref="eats:490856" type="Drama_TitledWork"><title>Guthlac</title></rs> moved on with <title>The Jew of Malta</title> to the Rose with
            Admiral's Men. Shakespeare's <title>Titus Andronicus</title> and <title>The Taming of
              the Shrew</title> became part of the Chamberlain's Men repertory, initially at the
            Theatre before <rs ref="eats:227836" type="Place_F_Playhouse">the Globe</rs> was built
            in 1599.<note type="foot">See further the <ref
                target="https://ereed.org/collections/nwbts/appendix/"
            >Appendix</ref>.</note></p>

          <p>Earlier reference to the 'tediousness of the way' could have been a factor in the
            markedly reduced profits taken by Henslowe for the ten days of performance at Newington
            Butts, especially given ongoing inclement weather conditions in June outlined by
              Johnson.<note type="foot">See Johnson, <title>Shakespeare's Lost Playhouse</title>, pp
              136–45.</note> What we cannot know is whether Henslowe might have had to deduct daily
            rental fees before recording his share of the gate. Another factor might have been the
            smaller audience capacity at the older playhouse, whose size might not have been
            comparable to that of the second phase of the Rose.</p>

          <p>A month after this flurry of activity featuring the two new playing companies destined
            to dominate the theatre scene in London and at Court for the next decade, the playhouse
            at Newington was closed and either converted for another use or demolished. How
            frequently it had been used between 1580 and 1594 cannot be reliably documented though
            the available evidence suggests that Peter Hunningborne, Hickes' intrusive son-in-law,
            must have rented the space periodically. Frustratingly his name has not yet surfaced
            elsewhere as a participant in the Elizabethan entertainment business.</p>

          <p>As an epitaph, in 1632, Edmund Howes' Continuation of Stowe's <title>Annales</title>
            recalled the memory of the playhouse at Newington among the 'Theatres, set Stages, or
            Playhouses' known during the previous sixty years, as follows: 'Fiue Innes, or common
            Osteryes turned to Play-houses, one Cock-pit, S. Paules singing Schoole, one in the
            Black-fryers, and one in the White-fryers, which was built last of all, in the yeare one
            thousand sixe hundred twentynine, all the rest not named, were erected only for common
            Play-houses, besides the new built Beare garden, which was built as well for playes, and
            Fencers prizes, as Bull Bayting besides, one in former time at Newington Buts....'<note
              type="foot"><ref target="https://ereed.org/records/bghop-ridp258075656/">Howes'
                Continuation of Stowe's, <title>Annales</title></ref>.</note></p>
        </div>
      </div>
    </front>
    <group>
      <text ana="taxon:CentralGov_PC" type="record" xml:id="nwbts-rid12">
        <body>
          <head><rs ref="eats:2111" type="Place_County">Middlesex</rs>, <rs ref="eats:228103"
              type="Place_F_Residence">Hampton Court</rs>
            <date when-iso="1574">1574</date>
            <seg ana="taxon:NBPL14">NBPL14</seg></head>
          <div xml:lang="eng" type="transcription" xml:id="nwbts-rid12-transcription">
            <div>
              <head>f [1] <supplied>(15 November) (Hampton Court)</supplied></head>
              <pb n="[1]" type="folio" facs="#NBPL14"/>

              <ab>After our very hartie commendac<ex>i</ex>ons ffor so much as yt is found by
                experience that very great perill and incouenienc<ex>es</ex> hath fallen vppon
                soundry of the Queenes Ma<ex>ies</ex>t<ex>es</ex> subiect<ex>es</ex> by the
                sufferance of great assemblies of people to come together at <rs ref="eats:40453"
                  type="Drama_Type">plaies</rs> and shewes neare London in this tyme of Contagion
                and infection of the <!--IN: PLAGUE REF-->plague: And for the restraint thereof
                straicte order hath ben taken in the <rs ref="eats:36947" type="Place_PA_Settlement"
                  >Citie</rs> and the liberties of the same. Theis be to requier youe
                  forthw<ex>i</ex>th to giue commaundement, as so directed by vs that there be no
                playes shewes nor any such vnnecessarie assemblies vsed in that <rs ref="eats:2291"
                  type="Place_County">Countie</rs> w<ex>i</ex>thin ten myles of the Citie vntill <rs
                  ref="eats:41327" type="CalendarDay_Liturgical">Easter</rs> next vppon payne of
                imprisonement to such as shall in any wies offend to the contrarie. And thervnto
                youe must take spciall<note type="foot">spciall: <hi rend="italic">for</hi>
                  speciall</note> regarde. ffarre youe hartely well ffrom <rs ref="eats:228103"
                  type="Place_F_Residence">Hampton Court</rs> the xv<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>
                of Nouember 1574</ab>

              <ab><hi rend="right">
                  <damage><gap unit="chars" extent="4"/></damage> ffrendes</hi></ab>

              <table>
                <row>
                  <cell><damage><gap unit="chars" extent="3"/></damage>er C<ex>ustos</ex>
                      s<ex>igili</ex></cell>
                  <cell>
                    <rs ref="eats:130613" type="Person_Male">W<ex>illiam</ex> Burghley</rs></cell>
                  <cell><rs ref="eats:488164" type="Person_Male">E<ex>dward</ex> lyncon</rs>
                    <damage><gap unit="chars" extent="2"/></damage>undell</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell><rs ref="eats:12536" type="Person_Nobility">A<ex>mbrose</ex>
                    Warwyk</rs></cell>
                  <cell><rs ref="eats:44753" type="Person_Nobility">R<ex>obert</ex>
                    Leycester</rs>.</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <cell><rs ref="eats:68527" type="Person_Gentry">F<ex>rancis</ex>
                    Knollys</rs></cell>
                  <cell><rs ref="eats:488103" type="Person_Gentry">Iamys croft</rs></cell>
                  <cell><rs ref="eats:490499" type="Person_Male">T<ex>homas</ex> Smith</rs></cell>
                  <cell><rs ref="eats:121275" type="Person_Male">Fra<ex>ncis</ex>
                    Walsyngham</rs></cell>
                </row>
              </table>
            </div>
          </div>
          <div type="endnote">
            <p> An oblong tear on the left side of the manuscript has obscured some letters before
              the legible signatures. The first damaged signature may have been by <rs ref="eats:407476" type="Person_Male">Ralph Sadler</rs>,
              identified in the Acts of the Privy Council for the meeting on 15 November as present
              (see <title>Acts of the Privy Council</title>, vol 8, pp 301–26, <ref
                target="https://www.british-history.ac.uk/acts-privy-council/vol8/pp301-325"
                  ><title>British History Online</title></ref>, accessed 23 July 2024). William Bray
              has identified, in the nineteenth-century ink below, the signature of <rs ref="eats:444022" type="Person_Male">Nicholas Bacon</rs>,
              who appears to have signed with the initials 'C s' for 'C<ex>ustos</ex>
                s<ex>igili</ex>' (keeper of the seal). There is also an oblong tear in the
              manuscript where the seal was ripped off, obliterating the word before 'ffrendes' and
              the 'Ar' of Arundell, but possibly more letters for <rs ref="eats:173323" type="Person_Nobility">Henry Fitzalan</rs> (1512–80),
              twenty-fourth earl of Arundel.</p>

            <p> Besides the earl of Arundel, the privy councillors signing the letter are as
              follows: Sir Nicholas Bacon (1510–79), lord keeper of the Great Seal, 1558–79; Sir
              William Cecil (1520/21–98), first Baron Burghley, lord treasurer, 1572–98; Edward
              Clinton (1512–85), sixteenth earl of Lincoln, lord admiral, 1559–85; Ambrose Dudley
                (<hi rend="italic">c</hi> 1530–90), twenty-first earl of Warwick; Sir Francis
              Knollys (1511/12–96), treasurer of the Household, 1570–96; Sir James Croft (<hi
                rend="italic">c</hi> 1518–90), comptroller of the Household, 1570–90; Sir Thomas
              Smith (1513–77), secretary of State, 1572–7; Robert Dudley (1532/3–88), fourteenth
              earl of Leicester; and Sir Francis Walsingham (<hi rend="italic">c</hi> 1532–90),
              principal secretary, 1573–90. </p>
          </div>
        </body>
      </text>

      <text ana="taxon:LocalGov_County" type="record" xml:id="nwbts-rid13">
        <body>
          <head><rs ref="eats:2291" type="Place_County">Surrey</rs>, <rs ref="eats:227741" type="Place_F_Playhouse">Newington Butts Playhouse</rs>
            <date when-iso="1576">1576</date>
            <seg ana="taxon:NBSKCS">NBSKCS</seg></head>
          <div xml:lang="eng" type="transcription" xml:id="nwbts-rid13-transcription">
            <div>
              <head>f 87v <supplied>(13 July)</supplied></head>
              <pb n="87v" type="folio" facs="#NBSKCSf87v"/>

              <gap reason="omitted"/>

              <ab rend="center"><rs ref="eats:231618" type="Place_PA_Settlement">Newinton</rs></ab>

              <table>
                <row>
                  <cell>ffirste<note type="marginal" place="margin_left">Savage &amp; Hilles</note>
                      p<ex>re</ex>sente <rs ref="eats:202508" type="Person_Male">Ierome Savadge</rs>
                    &amp; <rs ref="eats:486905" type="Person_Male">Iohn Hilles</rs> to skowre &amp;
                    caste deeper x roddes of their com<ex>m</ex>on <rs ref="eats:357230"
                      type="Place_F_WaterFeature">shewer</rs> leadinge from the grate at <rs
                      ref="eats:227741" type="Place_F_Playhouse">newington Butt</rs><ex>es</ex> to
                    the ende of Ierome Savag<ex>es</ex> orchard corner beinge more or les to be done
                    by the x<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> daye of October nexte comynge vppon paine
                    of xx d. for euerye rod then vndone</cell>
                  <cell rend="right">xx d.</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell rend="right">x<hi rend="superscript">o</hi> Octob<ex>e</ex>r
                    don<ex>e</ex></cell>
                </row>
              </table>

              <table>
                <row>
                  <cell>It<ex>e</ex>m<note type="marginal" place="margin_left"
                        >thenhabitant<ex>es</ex> of Newinton</note>we p<ex>re</ex>sente
                    thenhabitance of ‸<add place="above">the p<ex>ar</ex>ishe of</add> Newington to
                    clense &amp; caste deeper one rodde before the grate of Ierome Savadges doore to
                    be done by the x<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> of October next comynge vpon
                    paine of vj s. viij d. yf it be then vndone</cell>
                  <cell rend="right"> vj s. viij d.</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell rend="right">xx<hi rend="superscript">o</hi> Octob<ex>e</ex>r
                    don<ex>e</ex></cell>
                </row>
              </table>

              <table>
                <row>
                  <cell>We<note type="marginal" place="margin_left">Hilles &amp;
                      Cockowe</note>p<ex>re</ex>sente Iohn hills &amp; <rs ref="eats:486966"
                      type="Person_Male">Thomas Cockowe</rs> to skowre &amp; caste deeper xv pooles
                    of the com<ex>m</ex>on shewer leadinge from Ierome Savag<ex>es</ex> orchard
                    corner to barl<add place="above">owes</add><del><damage><gap unit="chars"
                          extent="2"/></damage>es</del> grounde be it more or les to be done by the
                      x<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> daye of October next comynge vpon paine of xx
                    d. euery rod then vndone</cell>
                  <cell rend="right">xx d.</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell rend="right">xi<hi rend="superscript">o</hi> Octob<ex>e</ex>r
                    don<ex>e</ex></cell>
                </row>
              </table>

              <gap reason="omitted"/>
            </div>
          </div>
          <div type="endnote">
            <p>Jerome Savage (d. 1587) is known to have been an actor in the earl of Warwick's
              troupe between 1575–9. See further the <ref
                target="https://ereed.org/collections/nwbts/playhouse/">Introduction: History of
                the Playhouse</ref>.</p>

            <p>John Hilles' property apparently lay to the south of the 'common sewer,' which ran
              between them on the south edge of Savage's lot (Ingram <title>Business of
                Playing</title>, pp 160–2). For Thomas Cuckowe, named in the third entry, see the
                <ref target="https://ereed.org/records/nwbts-rid5/">1590 lease</ref>, CCA:
              Register W, CCA-DCc- Register/W, ff 36v–7.</p>

            <p>On 21 July 1576 (f 90v), Jerome Savage's name appears listed with others 'which
              performed' tasks.</p>

            <p>For an abstract of the document and details of its transcription history,  see the
              related EMLoT <ref target="https://emlot.org/db/record/event/404/index.html">event
                record</ref>.</p>

          </div>
        </body>
      </text>
      <text type="record" xml:id="nwbts-rid25" copyOf="rosep.xml#rosep-ridm90700072">
        <body>
          <p/>
        </body>
      </text>
      <text ana="taxon:LocalGov_County" type="record" xml:id="nwbts-rid14">
        <body>
          <head><rs ref="eats:2291" type="Place_County">Surrey</rs>, <rs ref="eats:227741" type="Place_F_Playhouse">Newington Butts Playhouse</rs>
            <date when-iso="1577">1577</date>
            <seg ana="taxon:NBSKCS">NBSKCS</seg></head>
          <div xml:lang="eng" type="transcription" xml:id="nwbts-rid14-transcription">
            <div>
              <head>f 95v <supplied>(5 July)</supplied></head>
              <pb n="95v" type="folio" facs="#NBSKCSf95v"/>

              <gap reason="omitted"/>

              <table>
                <row>
                  <cell>Imprimis <note type="marginal" place="margin_left">Newington St Georges
                      &amp; St Mary Magdalyns</note>we p<ex>re</ex>sent all thos p<ex>er</ex>sons
                    whose names are herevnder named hauing grounde w<ex>i</ex>thin the saied
                      p<ex>ar</ex>ishes to cutt &amp; dragge all theire seuerall p<ex>ar</ex>tes of
                    the Co<ex>m</ex>en <rs ref="eats:357230" type="Place_F_WaterFeature">shewer</rs>
                    begyninge at the grate at <rs ref="eats:227741" type="Place_F_Playhouse"
                      >Newington Buttes</rs> &amp; so all alonge to the bridge at the Lasier house
                    viz: <rs ref="eats:202508" type="Person_Male">Iohn</rs><note type="foot">Iohn:
                        <hi rend="italic">presumably an error for</hi> Ierome</note>
                    <rs ref="eats:202508" type="Person_Male">Savadge</rs> &amp; <rs
                      ref="eats:486905" type="Person_Male">Iohn Hilles</rs> x roddes<gap
                      reason="omitted"/></cell>
                  <cell rend="right">xiij d. don<ex>e</ex></cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell rend="right">xx<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> of Nouember</cell>
                </row>
              </table>

              <gap reason="omitted"/>
            </div>
          </div>
          <div type="endnote">
            <p> Savage's name continues to appear in combination with Hilles' in the Sewer
              Commission records until November 1578. </p>
          </div>
        </body>
      </text>
      <text ana="taxon:LocalGov_County" type="record" xml:id="nwbts-rid15">
        <body>
          <head><rs ref="eats:2291" type="Place_County">Surrey</rs>, <rs ref="eats:227741" type="Place_F_Playhouse">Newington Butts Playhouse</rs>
            <date when-iso="1578">1578</date>
            <seg ana="taxon:NBSKCS">NBSKCS</seg></head>
          <div xml:lang="eng" type="transcription" xml:id="nwbts-rid15-transcription">
            <div>
              <head>f 105v <supplied>(3 November)</supplied></head>
              <pb n="105v" type="folio" facs="#NBSKCSf105v"/>

              <ab rend="center">The p<ex>ar</ex>ishes of Newington St Georges <lb/>Reddereth &amp;
                Mary Magdalyns</ab>

              <table>
                <row>
                  <cell>It<ex>e</ex>m we p<ex>re</ex>sent all the landhoulders from <rs
                      ref="eats:487587" type="Place_F_Bridge">Newington bridge</rs> vppon both sydes
                    the Co<ex>m</ex>en <rs ref="eats:357230" type="Place_F_WaterFeature">sewer</rs>
                    &amp; so alonge to <rs ref="eats:487062" type="Place_Feature">Duffildes
                      sluce</rs> to Cutt pare &amp; dragge all &amp; euery man his seu<ex>er</ex>all
                      p<ex>ar</ex>te of the same sewer to be done by the laste daye of November next
                    comyng vppon payne of xij d. for euery rodde then vndone viz. </cell>
                  <cell rend="right">xij d.</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell rend="right">vlt<ex>imo</ex> Nov<ex>embris</ex> don<ex>e</ex></cell>
                </row>
              </table>

              <table>
                <row>
                  <cell><rs ref="eats:202508" type="Person_Male">Ierom Savadge</rs> &amp; <rs
                      ref="eats:486905" type="Person_Male">Iohn Hylles</rs></cell>
                  <cell>x poles</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <cell>&#160;</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <cell><rs ref="eats:486966" type="Person_Male">Thomas Cuckowe</rs></cell>
                  <cell>xv pole</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <cell>&#160;</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <cell><rs ref="eats:487396" type="Person_Female">Barlowes widdowe</rs> &amp;
                    Thomas Cuckowe</cell>
                  <cell>vij pole</cell>
                </row>
              </table>

              <gap reason="omitted"/>
            </div>
          </div>
        </body>
      </text>
      <text ana="taxon:Church_Admin" type="record" xml:id="nwbts-rid3">
        <body>
          <head><rs ref="eats:2291" type="Place_County">Surrey</rs>, <rs ref="eats:227741" type="Place_F_Playhouse">Newington Butts Playhouse</rs>
            <date when-iso="1582">1582</date>
            <seg ana="taxon:NBCCAB">NBCCAB</seg></head>
          <div xml:lang="eng" type="transcription" xml:id="nwbts-rid3-transcription">
            <div>
              <head>f 27v <supplied>(June)</supplied></head>
              <pb n="27v" type="folio" facs="#NBCCABf27v"/>

              <gap reason="omitted"/>

              <ab>It<ex>e</ex>m yt ys agreyd that <rs ref="eats:133645" type="Person_Male">peter
                    honybo<ex>u</ex>rne</rs> shall haue a lease of the resydue of the garden
                  <del>adioyni</del> and ground<ex>es</ex> adioynyng to the <rs ref="eats:227741"
                  type="Place_F_Playhouse">playe house</rs> in <rs ref="eats:231618"
                  type="Place_PA_Settlement">newyngton</rs> not comp<ex>ri</ex>sed in his former
                lease for xxj<hi rend="superscript">ti</hi> yer<ex>es</ex> to begynne at <rs
                  ref="eats:42598" type="CalendarDay_Liturgical">mich<ex>aelm</ex>as</rs> next and
                he to pay therefore yerely two shilling<ex>es</ex></ab>

              <gap reason="omitted"/>
            </div>
          </div>
          <div type="endnote">
            <p> The date of the chapter meeting on f 25 has been damaged by fire; the exact date in
              June is lost. The original foliation for the entry was 4v. </p>
          </div>
        </body>
      </text>
      <text type="record" xml:id="nwbts-rid1" copyOf="bghop.xml#bghop-ridp269496296">
        <body>
          <p/>
        </body>
      </text>
      <text type="record" xml:id="nwbts-rid22" copyOf="rosep.xml#rosep-ridm92788552">
        <body>
          <p/>
        </body>
      </text>
      <text type="record" xml:id="nwbts-rid19" copyOf="rosep.xml#rosep-ridm94970728">
        <body>
          <p/>
        </body>
      </text>
      <text ana="taxon:LocalGov_County" type="record" xml:id="nwbts-rid16">
        <body>
          <head><rs ref="eats:2291" type="Place_County">Surrey</rs>, <rs ref="eats:227741" type="Place_F_Playhouse">Newington Butts Playhouse</rs>
            <date when-iso="1591">1590/1</date>
            <seg ana="taxon:NBSKCS">NBSKCS</seg></head>
          <div xml:lang="eng" type="transcription" xml:id="nwbts-rid16-transcription">
            <div>
              <head>f 172 <supplied>(26 February)</supplied></head>
              <pb n="172" type="folio" facs="#NBSKCSf172"/>

              <gap reason="omitted"/>

              <table>
                <row>
                  <cell>We<note type="marginal" place="margin_left">Honningborne.</note>
                      p<ex>re</ex>sent <rs ref="eats:133645" type="Person_Male">Peter
                      Honningborne</rs> to open the <rs ref="eats:487044" type="Place_Feature"
                      >sluce</rs> by the <rs ref="eats:227741" type="Place_F_Playhouse">play
                      house</rs> that the water may hav a fre passage by our <rs ref="eats:72087"
                      type="CalendarDay_Liturgical">Ladyday</rs> next<note type="foot">our Ladyday
                      next: <hi rend="italic">feast of the Annunciation, 25 March</hi></note> vpon
                      pa<ex>y</ex>n of</cell>
                  <cell rend="right">v s.</cell>
                </row>
              </table>

              <gap reason="omitted"/>

              <table>
                <row>
                  <cell>We<note type="marginal" place="margin_left">Cuckow <lb/>exstreted</note>
                      p<ex>re</ex>sent <rs ref="eats:487187" type="Person_Male">Richard Cuckow</rs>
                    to make asluce or thorough at his gate leading in to his feild next adioyning to
                    the playhouse by our Lady day next. vppon paine of</cell>
                  <cell rend="right">v s.</cell>
                </row>
              </table>

              <gap reason="omitted"/>
            </div>
          </div>
          <div type="endnote">
            <p>For an abstract of the document and details of its transcription history,  see the
              related EMLoT <ref target="https://emlot.org/db/record/event/403/">event
              record</ref>.</p>
            <p>For Richard Cuckow see the <ref target="https://ereed.org/records/nwbts-rid5/"
                >1590 lease</ref>, CCA: Register W, CCA-DCc- Register/W, ff 36v–7. </p>
          </div>
        </body>
      </text>

      <text type="record" xml:id="nwbts-rid23" copyOf="rosep.xml#rosep-ridm91625448">
        <body>
          <p/>
        </body>
      </text>

      <text type="record" xml:id="nwbts-rid18" copyOf="rosep.xml#rosep-ridm90590584">
        <body>
          <p/>
        </body>
      </text>

      <text ana="taxon:CentralGov_PC" type="record" xml:id="nwbts-rid24" copyOf="rosep.xml#rosep-ridm92826968">
        <body>
          <p/>
        </body>
      </text>
      <text ana="taxon:Church_Admin" type="record" xml:id="nwbts-rid4">
        <body>
          <head><rs ref="eats:2291" type="Place_County">Surrey</rs>, <rs ref="eats:227741" type="Place_F_Playhouse">Newington Butts Playhouse</rs>
            <date when-iso="1594">1594</date>
            <seg ana="taxon:NBCCAB">NBCCAB</seg></head>
          <div xml:lang="eng" type="transcription" xml:id="nwbts-rid4-transcription">
            <div>
              <head>f 184 <supplied>(6 July)</supplied></head>
              <pb n="184" type="folio" facs="#NBCCABf184"/>

              <gap reason="omitted"/>

              <ab>Yt is agreed that Mr <rs ref="eats:488277" type="Person_Male">Paule Bucke</rs>
                shall have the leases of t<damage><gap unit="chars" extent="2"/></damage>
                <rs ref="eats:489100" type="Place_F_Property">ten<ex>emen</ex>te</rs> and <rs
                  ref="eats:227741" type="Place_F_Playhouse">plaiehouse</rs> thereto adioyninge in
                  <rs ref="eats:231618" type="Place_PA_Settlement">Newington</rs> renewed vp to xxj
                yeares w<ex>i</ex>th coven<ex>au</ex>nt<ex>es</ex> as before and w<ex>i</ex>th a
                clause that he shall convert the playehouse to some other <del>house</del> vse vppon
                the saide grownde and not suffer anie plaies there after <rs ref="eats:42598"
                  type="CalendarDay_Liturgical">michelmas</rs> nexte</ab>

              <gap reason="omitted"/>
            </div>
          </div>
          <div type="endnote">
            <p>For an abstract of the document and details of its transcription history,  see the
              related EMLoT <ref target="https://ereed.org/records/nwbts-rid4/">event
                record</ref>.</p>
          </div>

        </body>
      </text>
      <text ana="taxon:Family_Personal" type="record" xml:id="nwbts-rid8">
        <body>
          <head><rs ref="eats:2291" type="Place_County">Surrey</rs>, <rs ref="eats:227741" type="Place_F_Playhouse">Newington Butts Playhouse</rs>
            <date when-iso="1594">1594</date>
            <seg ana="taxon:NBHEDY">NBHEDY</seg></head>
          <div xml:lang="eng" type="transcription" xml:id="nwbts-rid8-transcription">
            <div>
              <head>f 9 <supplied>(3–13 June)</supplied></head>
              <pb n="9" type="folio"/>

              <gap reason="omitted"/>

              <table>
                <row>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>In the name of god Amen begininge at <rs ref="eats:227741"
                      type="Place_F_Playhouse">newing <lb/>ton</rs> my <rs ref="eats:25827"
                      type="Collective_Troupe">Lord Admerall<ex>es</ex> men</rs> &amp; my <rs
                      ref="eats:223085" type="Collective_Troupe">Lorde chamberlen<ex>es</ex>
                      <lb/>men</rs> As ffolowethe 1594</cell>
                </row>

                <row>
                  <cell><lb/></cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <cell>¶ 3 of Iune 1594</cell>
                  <cell>R<ex>eceued</ex> at <rs ref="eats:489229" type="Drama_TitledWork">heaster
                      &amp; asheweros</rs></cell>
                  <cell rend="right">viij s</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <cell>¶ 4 of Iune 1594</cell>
                  <cell>R<ex>eceued</ex> at <rs ref="eats:199979" type="Drama_TitledWork">the Iewe
                      of malta</rs></cell>
                  <cell rend="right">x s.</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <cell>¶ 5 of Iune 1594</cell>
                  <cell>R<ex>eceued</ex> at <rs ref="eats:199938" type="Drama_TitledWork"
                      >andronicous</rs></cell>
                  <cell rend="right">xij s.</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <cell>¶ 6 of Iune 1594</cell>
                  <cell>R<ex>eceued</ex> at <rs ref="eats:489210" type="Drama_TitledWork"
                      >cutlacke</rs></cell>
                  <cell rend="right">xj s.</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <cell>¶ 8 of Iune 1594 ne<note type="foot">ne: <hi rend="italic">evidently written
                        after first writing</hi></note></cell>
                  <cell>R<ex>eceued</ex> at <rs ref="eats:191047" type="Drama_TitledWork"
                      >bellendon</rs> X<note type="foot">X: <hi rend="italic">written over line
                        filler, evidently after first writing</hi></note>
                  </cell>
                  <cell rend="right">xvij s</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <cell> 9 of Iune 1594</cell>
                  <cell>R<ex>eceued</ex> at <rs ref="eats:489534" type="Drama_TitledWork"
                      >hamlet</rs></cell>
                  <cell rend="right">viij s.</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <cell>¶ 10 of Iune 1594</cell>
                  <cell>R<ex>eceued</ex> at heaster </cell>
                  <cell rend="right"> v s.</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <cell>¶ 11 of Iune 1594</cell>
                  <cell>R<ex>eceued</ex> at <rs ref="eats:489374" type="Drama_TitledWork">the
                      tamynge of A shrowe</rs></cell>
                  <cell rend="right">ix s.</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <cell>¶ 12 of Iune 1594</cell>
                  <cell>R<ex>eceued</ex> at andronicous</cell>
                  <cell rend="right">vij s.</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <cell>13 of Iune 1594</cell>
                  <cell>R<ex>eceued</ex> at the Iewe</cell>
                  <cell rend="right">iiij s.</cell>
                </row>
              </table>

              <gap reason="omitted"/>
            </div>
          </div>
          <div type="endnote">
            <p>For an image of the original MS, see the <title>Henslowe-Alleyn Digitisation
                Project</title>, MS 7, f <ref
                target="https://henslowe-alleyn.org.uk/catalogue/mss-7/009-recto/">9r.</ref></p>

            <p>Henslowe's customary abbreviation 'R'followed by the '-es' loop has been expanded
              here according to REED practice. Although Henslowe spells the word variously
              throughout the manuscript, 'Receued' appears in 1591 expenses (f 6v) and for example,
                <ref target="https://henslowe-alleyn.org.uk/catalogue/mss-7/016-recto/">January
                1596/7 (f 16)</ref>.</p>

            <p> For further details on the plays listed, see the <ref
                target="https://ereed.org/collections/nwbts/appendix/">Appendix</ref>. <rs
                ref="eats:129736" type="Person_Male">Henslowe</rs> drew a line following the entry
              on 13 June before continuing with his receipts from performances following, from 15
              June onward. <title>Hester and Ahasuerus</title>, <title>Hamlet</title>, <title>The
                Taming of a Shrew</title>, and <title>Titus Andronicus</title> do not appear again
              in the repertory recorded in the diary and scholars have generally agreed that the
              Admiral's and Chamberlain's Men did not continue together at the Newington playhouse
              after their brief run there ending 13 June 1594. </p>

            <p>For an abstract of the document and details of its transcription history,  see the
              related EMLoT <ref target="https://emlot.org/db/record/event/7863/index.html">event
                record</ref>.</p>
          </div>

        </body>
      </text>
      <text type="record" xml:id="nwbts-rid20" copyOf="rosep.xml#rosep-ridm93271400">
        <body>
          <p/>
        </body>
      </text>
      <text ana="taxon:LocalGov_County" type="record" xml:id="nwbts-rid17">
        <body>
          <head><rs ref="eats:2291" type="Place_County">Surrey</rs>, <rs ref="eats:227741" type="Place_F_Playhouse">Newington Butts Playhouse</rs>
            <date when-iso="1599">1599</date>
            <seg ana="taxon:NBSKCS">NBSKCS</seg></head>
          <div xml:lang="eng" type="transcription" xml:id="nwbts-rid17-transcription">
            <div>
              <head>f 294a v <supplied>(5 October)</supplied></head>
              <pb n="294a" type="folio" facs="#NBSKCS294av"/>

              <gap reason="omitted"/>

              <ab>Item <note type="marginal" place="margin_left">Cuckowe <lb/>fface <lb/>Salter
                  <lb/>miller <lb/>Iefferson <lb/>Harvy</note> we fynd that the <rs
                  ref="eats:357230" type="Place_F_WaterFeature">sewar</rs> leadinge from the houses
                where the <rs ref="eats:227741" type="Place_F_Playhouse">old playe house</rs> did
                stand att <rs ref="eats:231618" type="Place_PA_Settlement">Newington</rs> all
                alongest vnto the Bridge goyng from <rs ref="eats:226373" type="Place_PA_Settlement"
                  >Barmondsey</rs> cross the high waye vnto <rs ref="eats:490666" type="Place_F_Other ">sainct Thomas Watering<ex>es</ex></rs> is
                needefull to be cast clensed and scowred, and we fynd that <rs ref="eats:487187"
                  type="Person_Male">Richard Cuckow</rs>
                <rs ref="eats:487690" type="Person_Male">Robert fface</rs>, <rs ref="eats:488387"
                  type="Person_Male">Richard Salter</rs>
                <rs ref="eats:487764" type="Person_Male">Iohn miller</rs>, <rs ref="eats:487801"
                  type="Person_Male">Iohn Iefferson</rs> and <rs ref="eats:489252"
                  type="Person_Male">Thomas Harvy</rs> oughte to cast clense and scower the same We
                  p<ex>re</ex>sent the same to be done before <rs ref="eats:330339"
                  type="CalendarDay_Liturgical">Candlemas</rs> next vpon payne of every pole then vndone<table>
                  <row>
                    <cell/>
                    <cell rend="right">ij s. vj d.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                    <cell/>
                    <cell rend="right">done</cell>
                  </row>
                </table></ab>
            </div>
          </div>
          <div type="endnote">
            <p>For an abstract of the document and details of its transcription history,  see the
              related EMLoT <ref target="https://emlot.org/db/record/event/402/">event
              record</ref>.</p>
            <p>This final notice of the 'old playe house' in the Sewer Commission records indicates
              that the building had been demolished before 1599 and possibly around the time that
              <rs ref="eats:488277" type="Person_Male">Buck</rs> assumed the lease. 'St. Thomas à
              Waterings was situated close to the second milestone on the Old Kent Road, and was so
              called from a brook or spring, dedicated to St. Thomas à Becket.' See Edward Walford,
              'The Old Kent Road,' in <title>Old and New London: Volume 6</title> (London, 1878),
              248–255, <title>British History Online</title>
              <ref target="http://www.british-history.ac.uk/old-new-london/vol6/pp248-255"
                >http://www.british-history.ac.uk/old-new-london/vol6/pp248-255</ref>, [accessed 27
              July 2024]. </p>
          </div>
        </body>
      </text>
      <text type="record" xml:id="nwbts-rid2" copyOf="bghop.xml#bghop-ridp258075656">
        <body>
          <p/>
        </body>
      </text>
      <text ana="taxon:CentralGov_Courts" type="record" xml:id="nwbts-rid7">
        <body>
          <head><rs ref="eats:2291" type="Place_County">Surrey</rs>, <rs ref="eats:227741" type="Place_F_Playhouse">Newington Butts Playhouse</rs>
            <date when-iso="1577">1577</date>
            <seg ana="taxon:NBCRSH">NBCRSH</seg></head>
          <div xml:lang="eng" type="transcription" xml:id="nwbts-rid7-transcription">
            <div>
              <head>mb 3 <supplied>(Bill of complaint)</supplied></head>
              <pb n="3" type="membrane" facs="#NBCRSH3"/>

              <ab rend="center">To<note type="foot">To: <hi rend="italic">display initial</hi>
                  T</note> the Quenes most excellent <lb/>ma<ex>ies</ex>tie</ab>

              <ab>In<note type="foot">In: <hi rend="italic">display initial</hi> I</note> most
                humble wise shew<ex>e</ex>th vnto yo<ex>u</ex>r most excellent ma<ex>ies</ex>tie
                  yo<ex>u</ex>r ma<ex>ies</ex>ties humble and obedient Subiect <rs ref="eats:202508"
                  type="Person_Male">Ierom Savage</rs> that where one <rs ref="eats:488448"
                  type="Person_Male">Richarde</rs><note type="foot">Richarde: <hi rend="italic"
                    >written over erasure</hi></note>
                <rs ref="eats:488448" type="Person_Male">Tomson</rs> had by good conveyance for
                terme of xix<hi rend="superscript">te</hi> yeres in and to one <rs ref="eats:489100"
                  type="Place_F_Property">messuage</rs> w<ex>i</ex>th the
                  app<ex>ur</ex>tenan<ex>au</ex>nc<ex>es</ex> in <rs ref="eats:231618"
                  type="Place_PA_Settlement">Newington</rs> in the countie of <rs ref="eats:2291"
                  type="Place_County">Surrey</rs> wherin yo<ex>u</ex>r said Subiect now inhabiteth
                and he the said Thom<ex>a</ex>s beinge therof soo possessed co<ex>n</ex>veyed hys
                interest aforesaid therein to yo<ex>u</ex>r said Subiect by force whereof
                  yo<ex>u</ex>r said Subiect entered and was possessed accordingly &amp;
                  yo<ex>u</ex>r said Subiect havinge the p<ex>re</ex>miss<ex>es</ex> by such title
                was desirous to p<ex>ro</ex>cure further yeres as also to have estaite in hys owne
                right from him that claymed the inheritance of the p<ex>re</ex>misses That ys to say
                of one <rs ref="eats:487271" type="Person_Male">Richard Hick<ex>es</ex></rs> and
                therevpon yo<ex>u</ex>r said Subiect moved the said Richard Hick<ex>es</ex> who then
                affirmed to have the verie fee simple of the p<ex>re</ex>misses &amp; that he had
                full poer to graunte the same to yo<ex>u</ex>r said Orator for such yeres as they
                concluded to have the same for terme of 30 yeres &amp; therevpon for the some of x
                  li.<note type="foot">x li.: <hi rend="italic">written over erasure</hi></note>
                paid by yo<ex>u</ex>r said Orator the said Richard Hik<ex>es</ex> at or about <rs
                  ref="eats:72087" type="CalendarDay_Liturgical">thannunciac<ex>i</ex>on of our
                  Ladie</rs> in the xviij<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> yere<note type="foot">
                    xviij<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> yere: <hi rend="italic">1576</hi></note> of
                  yo<ex>u</ex>r ma<ex>ies</ex>t<ex>ies</ex> reigne dyd by hys sufficient deed lett
                the said messuage and one orchard and garden w<ex>i</ex>th
                  thapp<ex>ur</ex>ten<ex>au</ex>nc<ex>es</ex> for terme of 30 yeres then next
                followinge reseruinge yerely during the said terme ffoure mark<ex>es</ex> of good
                and lawfull money of England payable quarterlie at ffoure termes in the yere
                  y<ex>a</ex>t ys to say at the feast<ex>es</ex> of the <rs ref="eats:41188"
                  type="CalendarDay_Liturgical">Natiuitie of St Iohn Baptist</rs> &amp; <rs
                  ref="eats:42598" type="CalendarDay_Liturgical">St Mychell
                  tharca<ex>u</ex>ngell</rs> &amp; the <rs ref="eats:239365"
                  type="CalendarDay_Liturgical">natiuitie of o<ex>u</ex>r Lord God</rs> and
                  thannunciac<ex>i</ex>on of our Lady by even porc<ex>i</ex>ons And in the said
                lease ther was one condic<ex>i</ex>on or p<ex>ro</ex>uiso by y<ex>a</ex>t
                  w<ex>hi</ex>ch yt was p<ex>ro</ex>vided that yf the said Rent or any part therof
                were behind in p<ex>ar</ex>te or in all at any feast or day aforesaid wherin the
                said Rent ought to be paid &amp; by xiiij<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> daies after
                being lawfullie d‸<add place="above">e</add>maunded y<ex>a</ex>t then yt should be
                lawfull to &amp; for the said Richard hys heires &amp; assign<ex>es</ex> to enter
                and yt to have &amp; repossed<note type="foot">repossed: <hi rend="italic">for</hi>
                    repossessed<hi rend="italic">; abbreviation mark missing</hi></note> as in hys
                first &amp; former estate And by force of such Lease yo<ex>u</ex>r said subiect
                entred &amp; was possessed of now so yt ys &amp; yt may please yo<ex>u</ex>r most
                excellent ma<ex>ies</ex>tie y<ex>a</ex>t the said Richard Hik<ex>es</ex> sekinge to
                defeat yo<ex>u</ex>r said Subiect of the p<ex>re</ex>misses co<ex>n</ex>trarie to
                hys owne graunte &amp; to p<ex>re</ex>fer one <rs ref="eats:133645"
                  type="Person_Male">Peter Hunnyngborne</rs> hys sonne in law to the same first
                  p<ex>re</ex>tend that the said Peter had &amp; hath of the said Richard a former
                graunte before the said seconde lease &amp; publish the said lease wher ether ther
                ys no such lease or yf ther were any the same was antedated or made onely
                  upo<ex>n</ex> trust betwen the said p<ex>ar</ex>ties &amp; not to thuse of the
                said Peter but by <rs ref="eats:202471" type="CrimesMisdemeanors">fraude</rs> &amp;
                coven to deceive such to whome the said Richard should lett the
                  p<ex>re</ex>miss<ex>es</ex> and the said Richard &amp; Peter fearinge &amp;
                suspectinge that such form<ex>er</ex> lease as they published yf any ther be will
                not be sufficient to defeat such the estate of yo<ex>u</ex>r highnes subiect so made
                bona fide for good considerac<ex>i</ex>ons the said Richard by secret practise withe
                the said Peter as the said Peter <damage><gap unit="chars" extent="2"
                  /></damage>firmeth<note type="foot"><damage><gap unit="chars" extent="2"
                    /></damage>firmeth: <hi rend="italic">small hole in MS</hi></note> hath made
                secret estate to the said Peter of the reu<ex>er</ex>c<ex>i</ex>on of the
                  p<ex>re</ex>miss<ex>es</ex> to thend y<ex>a</ex>t he the said Peter by some arte
                &amp; practice might the so<ex>o</ex>ner cu<ex>me</ex> to hys determined
                  p<ex>ur</ex>posse to p<ex>ro</ex>cure the possession of the
                  p<ex>re</ex>miss<ex>es</ex> to him self &amp; to defeat by craft yo<ex>u</ex>r
                said Subiect<ex>es</ex> lease by reason that yo<ex>u</ex>r said subiect knew not of
                any such assurance as the said Peter now p<ex>re</ex>tendeth And so yt ys &amp; yt
                may please yo<ex>u</ex>r highnes y<ex>a</ex>t after the feast of
                  thannunciac<ex>i</ex>on of o<ex>u</ex>r Lady last past &amp; before the xiiij day
                after yo<ex>u</ex>r said subiect left ye said Rent due at the said feast
                w<ex>hi</ex>ch one <rs ref="eats:490599" type="Person_Male">Thom<ex>a</ex>s whase</rs><note type="foot">whase: h <hi
                    rend="italic">corrected over another letter</hi></note> whom yo<ex>ur</ex>
                  ma<ex>ies</ex>tie havinge occasion to go about hys affaires left in the said house
                  co<ex>m</ex>maundinge him to pay ye said Rent to ye said Richard Hik<ex>es</ex>
                before or at the said xiiij<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> day w<ex>hi</ex>ch the
                said Richard &amp; Peter vnderstandinge cam not to demaund the same Rent so that
                  xiij<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> daies passinge &amp; the said Thom<ex>a</ex>s
                  whase<note type="foot">whase: <hi rend="italic">corrected over erasure</hi></note>
                suspecting no fraude vpon the xiiij<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> day went to <rs
                  ref="eats:36947" type="Place_PA_Settlement">london</rs> aboute hys affaires as
                also hopinge to mett ther w<ex>i</ex>th the said Richard Hik<ex>es</ex> to pay the
                said some not knowinge that the some was to be renderet on the lande nor suspectinge
                such the practice of the said Richard and Peter &amp; yo<ex>u</ex>r said Subiect
                hopeth to p<ex>ro</ex>ve that by secret meanes vsed by the said Peter y<ex>a</ex>t
                the said Thom<ex>a</ex>s was p<ex>ro</ex>cured to go to the said cytty y<ex>a</ex>t
                day he the said Thom<ex>a</ex>s nothinge suspectinge such practice And true yt ys
                &amp; yt may please yo<ex>u</ex>r highnes y<ex>a</ex>t after y<ex>a</ex>t the said
                  Thom<ex>a</ex>s was dep<ex>ar</ex>ted to london the aforesaid honyngborne havinge
                knowledg therof came to the aforesaid messuage &amp; ther demaunded the said Rent
                  su<ex>m</ex>tymes as yt ys said in hys owne &amp; su<ex>m</ex>tymes in the name of
                ye said Richard &amp; for default of paym<ex>en</ex>t as he the said Peter reporteth
                made hys entrie into the said messuage and after ye said Thom<ex>a</ex>s cumminge to
                the said messuage w<ex>i</ex>thin half an houre after &amp; hearinge of the same
                demaunde retorned to the house of the said Peter in London imed‸<add place="above"
                  >i</add>ate the same day &amp; ther offered to pay the same Rent &amp; declared
                  y<ex>a</ex>t he had ye same longe before redy to haue paid yt by the
                  deliu<ex>er</ex>ye &amp; commaundem<ex>en</ex>t of yo<ex>u</ex>r
                  ma<ex>ies</ex>t<ex>ies</ex> said Subiect but at the first the ‸<add place="above"
                  >said</add> Peter refused to receive the same &amp; after ye same day
                yo<ex>u</ex>r highnes said Subiect likewise after came to the house of the said
                Peter &amp; made tender of the saide Rent w<ex>hi</ex>ch the said Peter awhyle
                refused Neu<ex>er</ex>thelesse the same Peter afterwardes the same day ‸<add
                  place="above">by his wif</add> receyved the same Rent &amp; she deliuered ‸<add
                  place="above">it</add> to the said Peter who yet hath the same &amp;
                  <del>held</del> the p<ex>re</ex>miss<ex>es</ex> notw<ex>i</ex>thstandinge the said
                Peter &amp; Richard by such co<ex>n</ex>tynuall practice seeke still to frustrate
                and make void the interest of yo<ex>u</ex>r said Subiect by such ther indirect &amp;
                extreame dealinge Notw<ex>i</ex>thstandinge the receipte of the said rente and for
                that in extremitie of law some p<ex>er</ex>ill<note type="foot">p<ex>er</ex>ill: <hi
                    rend="italic">corrected over erasure in fresh ink</hi></note> in the
                  p<ex>re</ex>miss<ex>es</ex> may insue to yo<ex>u</ex>r said Subiect <term
                  ref="gloss:onelesse-1">onelesse</term> the truthe in the
                  p<ex>re</ex>miss<ex>es</ex> may appere by the corporall othe of the said said<note
                  type="foot">said said: <hi rend="italic">dittography</hi></note> Richard &amp;
                Peter May yt ‸<add place="above">therefore</add> pleasse yo<ex>u</ex>r most
                excellent ma<ex>ies</ex>tie to graunt yo<ex>u</ex>r ma<ex>ies</ex>t<ex>ies</ex> wryt
                of Prevy seale to be directed to the said <del>Pete</del> Richard and Peter
                commaundinge them &amp; either of them therby at a c<ex>er</ex>taine day and vnder a
                  c<ex>er</ex>taine paine ther in to be limytted p<ex>er</ex>sonally to appere
                before yo<ex>u</ex>r ma<ex>ies</ex>t<ex>ies</ex> honorable court of
                  Request<ex>es</ex> then &amp; ther to aunswere the p<ex>re</ex>miss<ex>es</ex> And
                  yo<ex>u</ex>r ma<ex>ies</ex>t<ex>ies</ex> said Subiect shall dayly pray to god for
                the longe &amp; prosperus contynuance of yo<ex>u</ex>r ma<ex>ies</ex>t<ex>ies</ex>
                reigne etc</ab>

              <ab><seg type="signed" rend="right">E fenner</seg></ab>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="nwbts-rid7-mb2">
              <head>mb 2 <supplied>(10 May)</supplied>
                <supplied>(Answer of Peter Hunningborne)</supplied></head>
              <pb n="2" type="membrane" facs="#NBCRSH2"/>

              <ab rend="center">The<note type="marginal" place="margin_left">x<hi rend="superscript"
                    >o</hi> Die Maij A<ex>nn</ex>o R<ex>egi</ex>ne Elizabeth xix<hi
                    rend="superscript">o</hi></note><note type="foot">The: <hi rend="italic">in
                    display script</hi></note> answere of Peter Honingborne Def<ex>endan</ex>t to
                the Bill of Complaint of Ierom Savage Compl<ex>ainan</ex>t</ab>

              <ab>The<note type="foot">The: <hi rend="italic">display initial</hi> T</note> saide
                Defendant saithe That the saide Bill against him exhibited for the most parte of the
                matters therein conteyned is vncerteine vntrewe and insufficient in the lawe As he
                thinketh to be answered vnto not concerninge anie matter of Substaunce or effecte
                Worthie to tro<ex>u</ex>ble this Hono<ex>u</ex>rable Court w<ex>i</ex>thall and is
                sett fourthe and devised as he beleaveth by the Compl<ex>ainan</ex>t rather of
                malice and envey to greave Charge and vexe this Defend<ex>an</ex>t then for anie
                good grounde or Cause of svte Nevertheles if this Def<ex>endan</ex>t by order of
                this Courte shalbe compelled to make anie further answere vnto the ‸<add
                  place="above">said</add> vncerteine and insufficient Bill of Compl<ex>ain</ex>t
                Then the advantage and exception to the incertentie and insvfficiencye of the saide
                Bill vnto this Def<ex>endan</ex>t at all tymes hereafter saved for answere and
                  declarac<ex>i</ex>on of the treuth of suche thing<ex>es</ex> Conteyned in the
                saide Bill as Concerneth this def<ex>endan</ex>t Materiall to be answered vnto he
                saieth that as towchinge the messwage w<ex>i</ex>th the appurten<ex>au</ex>nces in
                the Countie of Sussex<note type="foot">Sussex: <hi rend="italic">likely for</hi>
                  Surrey</note> wherein the saide Compl<ex>ainan</ex>t saieth that he nowe dwelleth
                  w<ex>hi</ex>ch as he saieth he had of one Thomas<note type="foot">Thomas: <hi
                    rend="italic">for</hi> Richard<hi rend="italic">?</hi></note> Thomson in whome
                he supposethe a former possession of the said premisses, this Defend<ex>an</ex>t
                knowethe noe suche thinge, But in trewthe this Defend<ex>an</ex>t saiethe That one
                Richarde Thomson as this Defend<ex>an</ex>t thinketh had and held one messwage or
                Tenement nere <rs ref="eats:227741" type="Place_F_Playhouse">Newington
                    Butt<ex>es</ex></rs> in the Countie of Surr<ex>ey</ex> as Ten<ex>au</ex>nte to
                Richarde Hick<ex>es</ex> in the saide Bill of Complaynt named but how or by what
                title this defend<ex>an</ex>t knoweth not And this Defendant further saiethe that
                after the Departure of the saide Richarde Thomson beinge a <rs ref="eats:5732"
                  type="Collective_Occupations">silkewever</rs> as this Defend<ex>an</ex>t thinkethe
                The saied Compl<ex>ainan</ex>t occupied the same messwage or ten<ex>emen</ex>te and
                he so havinge the occupac<ex>i</ex>on of the saide house sought by all meanes that
                he coulde to obteyne of the saide Richarde Hick<ex>es</ex> to whome the premisses
                was by the <rs ref="eats:489184" type="Collective_Clergy">Cheif Landlorde</rs> of
                the premisses graunted for manie yeres yet to come a lease for Thirtie yeares of the
                saide Messwage or tenement<ex>e</ex> And the same Complainant thinckinge and
                entendinge as it semeth and as the said Complainant hym seulf saide to entrapp the
                saide Richarde Hick<ex>es</ex> being a symple and plaine dealinge man whom the saide
                complainant aswell therein as otherwaies hathe abused, did Cause to be inserted in
                the Indenture ‸<add place="above">of lease</add> a Coven<ex>au</ex>nt Whereby the
                saide Richarde did stand bounde that he had full power right and Aucthoritie to
                Demise and graunt the saide Messwage or ten<ex>emen</ex>te and other the premisses
                in the saide lease graunted, in suche sorte as in the same deed is expressed. And
                the saide Compl<ex>ainan</ex>t givinge but Tenne Pound<ex>es</ex> for suche his
                lease procured the saide Richard Hick<ex>es</ex> to seale a bond of a Hundered
                  Pound<ex>es</ex> to performe coven<ex>au</ex>nt<ex>es</ex> meaninge thereby to
                make him forfeit his bond ymediatlie after the sealing thereof. Whiche saide
                Indenture of Lease graunted by the said Richard Hick<ex>es</ex> to the saide
                  Compl<ex>ainan</ex>t was vppon Divers Condic<ex>i</ex>ons. That is to saie That if
                the yerelie rent of ffiftie Three shilling<ex>es</ex> and ffower Pence therefore
                reserved should be behind vnpaid in parte or in all, by the space of xiiij<hi
                  rend="superscript">tene</hi> Daies over or after anie feast or terme of paymente
                in the said Indenture of lease lymited and beinge lawfullie asked. Or if the saide
                  Compl<ex>ainan</ex>t his executors administrators or assignes should breake or
                make defaulte in performance of anie Covena<ex>u</ex>nte graunt Article or agrement
                in the saide Indenture mencioned W<ex>hi</ex>ch on his and their part<ex>es</ex> or
                  <del>of</del> on the behalf of anie of them were or oughte to be performed by the
                trew intent<ex>es</ex> and meanig<ex>es</ex><note type="foot">meanig<ex>es</ex>: <hi
                    rend="italic">for</hi> meaninges; <hi rend="italic">abbreviation mark
                    missing</hi></note> of the saide Indenture That then and from thensfourth the
                saide demise and lease should cease be fullie determined and of none effecte and
                that then and at all tymes after it should be lawfull to and for the saide Richarde
                  Hick<ex>es</ex> his executors and assignes into the saide tenement and other the
                premisses w<ex>i</ex>th Thappurtena<ex>u</ex>nc<ex>es</ex> wholie to reenter and the
                same as ‸<add place="above">in</add> his or there former estate to have againe
                retaine and repossede, And the said Complainant his executors and assignes and all
                others occupiynge the same premisses from thense vtterlie to expell amove and put
                oute forever, anie thinge in the saide Indenture of lease conteyned to the Contrarie
                  notw<ex>i</ex>thstandinge as by the saide Indenture of Demise more at large maie
                appeare after whiche saide Lease ‸<add place="above">to the said
                    Compl<ex>ainant</ex> mad</add> the saide Richarde Hick<ex>es</ex> beinge by
                  obligac<ex>i</ex>on vnder his hande and Seall Lawfullie and iustlie indebted to
                this Defend<ex>an</ex>t in the some of fiftie Pound<ex>es</ex> for the payment
                whereof he stoode bound to the said Defend<ex>an</ex>t in one obligac<ex>i</ex>on of
                one hundredth mark<ex>es</ex> and for non payment thereof beinge sved at the Comon
                lawe by this defendant and the matter reddie to come to triall by <term
                  ref="gloss:nysiprius-1">Nysi prius</term> fell to Composic<ex>i</ex>on
                w<ex>i</ex>th this defendant and for satisfac<ex>i</ex>on thereof amongest other
                  thing<ex>es</ex> the saide Richard Hick<ex>es</ex> did graunt the
                reverc<ex>i</ex>on of the said p<ex>re</ex>misses to the saide defend<ex>an</ex>t
                for Divers yeres yet to come Wherevnto the saide Compl<ex>ainan</ex>t consented and
                did acknowledge the saide Defend<ex>an</ex>t as his Landlord by vertue whereof the
                said Defend<ex>an</ex>t was possessed thereof accordinglie and afterward<ex>es</ex>
                this Defend<ex>an</ex>t cominge to the foresaid Messwage or Tenement as is
                aforesaide demised, gentlie demanded his rent on the ffowertenth daie after the
                ffeast daie of Thanunciac<ex>i</ex>on of oure Ladie Saint Marie the virgen in the
                Nynetenth yere of the Reigne of oure Soveraigne Ladie Elizabeth the Queenes
                  Ma<ex>ies</ex>tie<note type="foot">Nynetenth…Ma<ex>ies</ex>tie: <hi rend="italic"
                    >ie, 1577</hi></note> that nowe is Dewe at the saide ffeast of
                  Thanunciac<ex>i</ex>on of oure Ladie and there taried for the same one hole hower
                in the latter p<ex>ar</ex>te of the daie even vntell the sonne was sett and the daie
                finished and yet Could gett noe rent or other money dewe Wherevppon this defendant
                Imediatlie reentred w<ex>hi</ex>ch he neded not to have done for that the lease and
                interest of the saide Complainant by the said demaunde was mad void ipso facto)<note
                  type="foot">facto): <hi rend="italic">opening parens omitted likely before</hi>
                  which</note> w<ex>i</ex>thout anie reentrey and further this defendant saieth that
                he w<ex>i</ex>th workmen accordinge to a couenant and Condic<ex>i</ex>on conteyned
                in the saide lease came to viewe the reperac<ex>i</ex>ons, and Could not be suffered
                to enter and veiw accordinge to the saide Coven<ex>au</ex>nt and Condic<ex>i</ex>on
                but those that kepte the house vtterlie denies him so to doe and shutt the dore
                against him By reason whereof also the Lease was voide and Determined. And when this
                defendant Cometh thether meaninge to talke friendlie and deale Curtiouslie
                  w<ex>i</ex>th the saide Complainant, althoughe his <damage><gap unit="chars"
                    extent="2"/></damage>sert<ex>es</ex> be otherwise. The same Complanant giveth
                vnto the Defendant <rs ref="eats:45633" type="CrimesMisdemeanors">Threteninge
                    word<ex>es</ex> and fecheth his sword</rs> to thende as this defend<ex>an</ex>t
                is induced to beleave, to stricke this defendant. And the saide Compl<ex>ainan</ex>t
                braggeth and bosteth that he hathe suche freind<ex>es</ex> as shall Compell this
                  Defend<ex>an</ex>t to deale in suche sort as pleasethe him And in trewthe the
                  compl<ex>ainan</ex>t himsealf is a verrie lewed feallowe and liveth by noe other
                trade then playinge of <rs ref="eats:40453" type="Drama_Type">staige plaies</rs> and
                  <rs ref="eats:40398" type="Drama_Type">Interlevd<ex>es</ex></rs> to the knoledge
                of this defend<ex>an</ex>t and for his lewde and lose lief hath Comaundement from
                the ordenarye as is Crediblie reported to avoide out of that parishe w<ex>hi</ex>ch
                his lewed behavior would sone make an honest man werie of so weked <damage><gap
                    unit="chars" extent="3"/></damage><note type="foot"><damage><gap unit="chars"
                      extent="3"/></damage>: <hi rend="italic">38mm of text faded</hi></note> tenant
                And so muche the more because <del>the mor because</del> the honest neighboures in
                that place doe so mislike his behavior as they will not suffer hime to Dwell there
                anie longer althoughe as it is void And althoughe the defendant for his parte would
                be contented to allowe the same. W<ex>hi</ex>ch he cannot Convenientlie doe because
                in trewthe this defendant is in greate need of a house and therefore meanethe to
                dwell there him sealf whereof by the <damage><gap unit="chars" extent="3"
                  /></damage><note type="foot"><damage><gap unit="chars" extent="3"/></damage>: <hi
                    rend="italic">50mm of faded text followed by 75mm of line filler</hi></note> And
                bycause he cold not hold the same by him sealf he did sett a Bill on the dore to
                sell or doe awaie the same And this defend<ex>an</ex>t further saiethe that he did
                not practise anie measur to defeat the Compl<ex>ainan</ex>t of his Interest
                otherwise then by the demand of his saide Rent as Lawfullie it was for him to doe
                  w<ex>i</ex>thout that. that by anie secreat meanes vsed by the saide
                  defend<ex>an</ex>t that the said Thomas whast<note type="foot">whast: <hi
                    rend="italic">for</hi> whase</note>in the said Bill of Complaint named was
                procured to goe to the Cittie of London that daie Whereon the saide demaund was made
                as in the said Bill is most falselie and vntrulie surmised. ffor in verry trewth
                this defend<ex>an</ex>t tarried a great while for his rent Could get none or hard of
                anie suche fellowe. And w<ex>i</ex>thout that that the saide rent was that daie
                paied to this defend<ex>an</ex>t as in the said Bill is also vntrulie aledged. And
                  w<ex>i</ex>thout that that anie other matter or thinge Comprehended in the said
                Bill Materiall to be answered vnto And <add place="above">in</add> this answere not
                sufficientlie answered or confessed and avoided Denied or traversed as this
                  defend<ex>an</ex>t belaeaveth is trew in mann<ex>er</ex> and forme as in the said
                Bill is Contteyned All w<ex>hi</ex>ch matters this defend<ex>an</ex>t is reddie to
                Averr and prove as this honorable Court shall awarde And praieth to be dismissed
                  w<ex>i</ex>th his resonable cost<ex>es</ex> in this behalf wrongfullie
                sussteyned</ab>

              <ab><seg type="signed" rend="right">S ffuller</seg></ab>
            </div>
            <div>
              <head>mb 1 <supplied>(17 May)</supplied>
                <supplied>(Answer of Richard Hickes)</supplied></head>
              <pb n="1" type="membrane" facs="#NBCRSH1"/>

              <ab rend="center">The<note type="marginal" place="margin_left">xvij<hi
                    rend="superscript">o</hi> die maij A<ex>nn</ex>o R<ex>egi</ex>ne Elizabeth
                    xix<hi rend="superscript">o</hi></note> answere of Richard Hick<ex>es</ex>
                  defend<ex>an</ex>t to the Bill of Complaint of Ierome Savage Complanante</ab>

              <ab>The saide Defendant saiethe that the said Bill of Complainte against him exhibited
                for the moste p<ex>ar</ex>te of the matters therein Conteyned as concerne this
                defendant is vncerteyne vntrewe and insufficiente in the Lawe as he thincketh to be
                answered vnto not Conteyninge<note type="foot">Conteyninge: <hi rend="italic">4
                    minims for</hi> nin</note> any matter of substaunce or effecte Worthie to troble
                this honnorable Courte w<ex>i</ex>th all and is set fourth and devised by the
                complanant as he beleaveth rather of Crafte envye and mallice to entrape tharge<note
                  type="foot">tharge: <hi rend="italic">for</hi> charge <hi rend="italic"
                  >(?)</hi></note> and vexe this Defend<ex>an</ex>t then for anie good ground or
                Cause of sute Neverthelesse if this defendant by the order of this Honnorable Courte
                shalbe Compelled to make anie further answere vnto the said vncerteine and
                insufficient Bill of Complainte Then the Advantage and excepc<ex>i</ex>on to the
                incertenty and insufficyencye of the saide Bill vnto this Defendant at all tymes
                hereafter saved for answere and declarac<ex>i</ex>on of the truthe of suche
                  thing<ex>es</ex> Conteyned in the said Bill as concerneth this Defend<ex>an</ex>t
                materiall to be answered vnto he saiethe That as towchinge the messwage
                w<ex>i</ex>th Thappurten<ex>au</ex>nc<ex>es</ex> in Newington in the Countie of
                  Sussex<note type="foot">Sussex: <hi rend="italic">for</hi> Surrey</note> wherein
                the saied Compl<ex>ainant</ex> saieth that he nowe dwelleth w<ex>hi</ex>ch as he
                saieth he had of one Thomas<note type="foot">Thomas: <hi rend="italic">for</hi>
                  Richard</note> Thomson whome he supposeth a farmer in the possession of the saide
                premisses This Defendant knoweth noe suche thinge But in truthe this defendant
                saiethe That one Richard Thomson as this Defendaunt remembreth had and held one
                messwage or Tenement nere Newington Butt<ex>es</ex> in the Countie of
                  Surr<ex>ey</ex> as ten<ex>au</ex>nt to this defendant And this defendant further
                saiethe that after the departure of the saied Richard Thomson beinge a silkewever as this defendante
                remembreth The said Complanant occupied the saide messwage or Ten<ex>emen</ex>te and
                he so havinge the occupac<ex>i</ex>on of the saide house sought by all meanes that
                he could to obteyne of him this defendant to whom the premisses was by the Cheif
                Landlord of the premisses graunted for manie ye<ex>a</ex>res yet to come a lease for
                Thirtie yeres of the saide messwage or Tenemente And the same Compl<ex>ainant</ex>
                thinkinge and entendinge as it seameth as he hym sealf hath saied to entrape the
                said Defendant beinge a simple and plaine delinge man whom the Compl<ex>ainant</ex>
                as well therein as in other thing<ex>es</ex> hathe greatlie abused did cause to be
                  inse‸<add place="above">r</add>ted in the said Indenture of Lease a
                  Coven<ex>au</ex>nte whereby this defend<ex>an</ex>t did stand bounde that he had
                full power right and aucthoritie to Demise and graunt the said messwage, or tenement
                and other the premisses in the saide Indenture of Lease graunted in suche sort as in
                the saide Deed is expressed. And the same Complaynaunt givinge but Tenn
                  Pound<ex>es</ex> for such his lease procured the saide Defendaunt beinge simple
                and givinge over muche Credite to the feyer word<ex>es</ex> of the saide Complanant
                to seall a Bonde of a Hundered Pound<ex>es</ex> to p<ex>er</ex>forme the
                  coven<ex>au</ex>nt<ex>es</ex> And in trewth as it semeth the same Complanant ment
                to make this Defendant forfecte his bond ymedyatlie after the sealinge thereof Which
                saide Indenture of lease graunted by this defendante to the saide
                  Compl<ex>ainant</ex> was vppon divers Condic<ex>i</ex>ons that is to saie That if
                the yerelie rente of ffiftie Three shilling<ex>es</ex> and ffower Pence thereby for
                the premises reserved should be behinde vnpaied in part or in all by the space of
                ffourteane Daies over or after anie feast or terme of paymente in the saide
                Indenture of lease lymited and beinge Lawfullie asked. Or if the saide
                  Compl<ex>ainant</ex> his executo<ex>ur</ex>s administrato<ex>ur</ex>s or assignes
                should breake or make defaulte in p<ex>e</ex>rformaunce of anie Coven<ex>au</ex>nte
                article or Agremente in the saide Indenture mencioned w<ex>hi</ex>ch on his and
                their part<ex>es</ex> or on the behouf of anie of them were or ought to be
                  p<ex>er</ex>formed by the trewe entent and meaninge of the saide Indenture. That
                then and from thensfourth the saide demise and lease should cease be fullie
                determined and of none effecte And that then and at all tymes after it should be
                lawfull to and for this defendant his executo<ex>u</ex>rs and assignes into the
                saide tenement and other the premisses w<ex>i</ex>th
                  Thappurten<ex>au</ex>nc<ex>es</ex> wholie to reenter And the same as in his or
                there form<ex>er</ex> estate to have againe retaine and reposses. And the saide
                Complanant his executo<ex>u</ex>rs and assignes and all others occupiinge the same
                premisses from theise vtterlie to expell amove and put out forever Anie thinge in
                the saide Indenture of Lease conteyned to the Contrary notw<ex>i</ex>thstandinge As
                by the said Indenture of Demise more at large maie appeare, After w<ex>hi</ex>che
                saide lease to the saide Complanant made this defendant beinge before that by
                  obligac<ex>i</ex>on vnder his hande and Seale lawfullie lawfullie<note type="foot"
                  >lawfullie lawfullie: <hi rend="italic">dittography at the beginning of the
                    line</hi></note> and Iustlie indebted to Peter Honningborne one of the
                  defendant<ex>es</ex> in the saide Bill of Complainte named in the some of ffiftie
                  Pound<ex>es</ex> for the payment whereof he this defendaunt stoode bound to the
                saide Peter Honingborne by the saide obligac<ex>i</ex>on in one Hundereth
                  mark<ex>es</ex> And for none payment thereof beinge sved at the com<ex>m</ex>on
                Lawe by the saide Peter Honingborne and the matter redye to come to tryall by Nisi
                prius this Defend<ex>an</ex>t fell to Composic<ex>i</ex>on w<ex>i</ex>th the saide
                Peter Honingborne And for satisfac<ex>i</ex>on thereof amongest other
                  thing<ex>es</ex> this defendant did graunt aswell the reverc<ex>i</ex>on of the
                premisses as the reverc<ex>i</ex>on of Two other tenement<ex>es</ex> in the parrishe
                of <rs ref="eats:226240" type="Place_PA_Settlement">Saint Olaves</rs> in <rs
                  ref="eats:36966" type="Place_PA_Settlement">Southworke</rs> in the Countie of
                Surrey by this defendant before that demised to one <rs ref="eats:487886"
                  type="Person_Male">Thomas Cranage</rs> Ioynte to the saide Peter Honingborne for
                Divers yeres yet to come wherevnto the saide Complanant Consented and did
                acknowledge the saide Peter Honingborne as his Landlord as this defendant hathe bene
                Credeblie enformed And as this defendant hath gathered by the Complanant<ex>es</ex>
                owne word<ex>es</ex> By vertue whereof the said Peter Honingborne was possessed
                thereof accordingly And afterward<ex>es</ex> as this defendant hath herd the saide
                Peter Honingborne the ffowertenth Daie after the ffeast of Thanuncyac<ex>i</ex>on of
                our Ladie Saint Marie the Virgin in the xix<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> yere<note
                  type="foot"> xix<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> yere: <hi rend="italic"
                  >1577</hi></note> of the raigne of our Sovereigne Ladie the Queenes
                Ma<ex>ies</ex>tie that nowe is made his demaunde for the rent dewe at the feast
                aforesaide and for none payment thereof reentered And by reason of suche demaunde
                made the Complanant<ex>es</ex> lease voide as this defendant thinckethe And also
                this defendant hath herd it Credably reported that the said Peter Honingborne
                  w<ex>i</ex>th workmen accordinge to a Conven<ex>au</ex>nte and proviso conteyned
                in the saide Lease Came to the premises to viewe the reparac<ex>i</ex>ons thereof
                  w<ex>hi</ex>ch was to him denied and the Dore shutt against him ‸<add
                  place="above">w<ex>hi</ex>ch</add> was another Cause whereby the lease should be
                voide And the saide Peter Honingborne hath tolde this defend<ex>an</ex>t that he
                hath ben evill vsed and threatened by this said Complanant who make the great
                  Bragg<ex>es</ex> and saiethe he cane procure greate freind<ex>es</ex> to
                  Counten<ex>au</ex>nce his matter And to force the saide Peter Honingborne to yeald
                to him as is said And yet in trewthe the saide Complainant is a Verrie lewde fellowe
                and his Cheifeste Man<ex>ner</ex> of lyvinge is by playinge of interlud<ex>es</ex>
                and for his lewde and loase life hath ben presented to the ordenarie<note
                  type="foot">Ordenarye: <hi rend="italic">the archbishop's representative in the
                    deanery of Croydon</hi></note> and is Comaunded by the Ordenarye as is saide to
                avoide the parishe w<ex>hi</ex>ch his lewde behavor wolde sone make an honeste man
                wearye of so Wicked an Idell a Lyvinge tennaunte And so much the more bennefite the
                honest neighboures in that place doe so mislike his behavioure as they will not
                suffer him to Dwell there w<ex>hi</ex>ch he Cannot Convenyentlie doe bycause in
                truth the saide Peter Honingborne is in great need of a house And there fore
                meanethe to Dwell there him sealf And also the Complanant f<damage><gap unit="chars"
                    extent="2"/></damage>reth not greatlie thereof as it seamethe for he hathe sett
                a Bill on the Dore to sell his interest And this defendant also saiethe <damage><gap
                    unit="chars" extent="3"/></damage><note type="foot"><damage><gap unit="chars"
                      extent="3"/></damage>: <hi rend="italic">20mm of text faded; approximately 9
                    characters</hi></note> he did not Practise anie mean<ex>es</ex> to defeat the
                Complanant of his Interest in the p<ex>re</ex>misses but did graunt the
                  reverc<ex>i</ex>on of the premisses Bona fide to the saide Peter Honingborne as is
                aforesaide And if the saide Complanant hathe given Cause of forfeiture of his
                Interest in the p<ex>re</ex>misses this defendant cannot doe w<ex>i</ex>thall.
                  W<ex>i</ex>thout that. that anie other matter or thinge Comprehended in the saide
                Bill of Complainte apperteyninge to this defendant Materiall to be answered vnto and
                in this answere not sufficiently answered or confessed and avoided denied or
                traversed as this defend<ex>an</ex>t beleaveth is trewe in mann<ex>er</ex> and forme
                as in the saide Bill of Complainte is conteyned All w<ex>hi</ex>ch matters this
                Defendant is redie to averr and prove as this honnorable Courte shall awarde And soe
                asmuche as it evidentlie appearethe that there was or is noe iust Cause whie this
                  Defend<ex>an</ex>t showld be molested or trobled he praieth therefore to be
                dismissed. this Honnorable Courte w<ex>i</ex>th his resonable Cost and
                  Charg<ex>es</ex> by him wrongfullie susteyned</ab>

              <ab><seg type="signed" rend="right">S. ffuller</seg></ab>
            </div>
          </div>
          <div type="endnote">
            <p> Although the bill of complaint (mb 3) is not dated specifically, Savage's reference
              to the rent due by the feast of the Annunciation, 25 March, narrows the period to
              sometime in April or early May, before the answers of Hickes and Hunningborne were
              recorded. </p>
            <p>For an abstract of the document and details of its transcription history,  see the
              related EMLoT events records: <ref
                target="https://emlot.org/db/record/event/184/index.html">the bill</ref>, <ref
                target="https://emlot.org/db/record/event/7314/index.html">Hunningborne's
                answer</ref>, and <ref target="https://emlot.org/db/record/event/7313/index.html"
                >Hicks' reply</ref>.</p>
          </div>
        </body>
      </text>
      <text ana="taxon:CentralGov_PC" type="record" xml:id="nwbts-rid10">
        <body>
          <head><rs ref="eats:2291" type="Place_County">Surrey</rs>, <rs ref="eats:227912"
              type="Place_F_Residence">Richmond Palace</rs>
            <date when-iso="1578">1578</date>
            <seg ana="taxon:NBPCO7">NBPCO7</seg></head>
          <div xml:lang="eng" type="transcription" xml:id="nwbts-rid10-transcription">
            <div>
              <head>p 300 <supplied>(10 November) (Richmond)</supplied></head>
              <pb n="300" type="page" facs="#NBPCO7p300"/>

              <gap reason="omitted"/>

              <ab>A l<ex>ett</ex>re to <rs ref="eats:488066" type="Person_Male">Mr doctor
                  Fourthe</rs>
                <rs ref="eats:488028" type="Person_Male">Rob<ex>er</ex>t Lewseye</rs>, <rs
                  ref="eats:487941" type="Person_Male">Edward Bellingham</rs> &amp; <rs
                  ref="eats:487983" type="Person_Male">Barnard Randolphe Esquiers</rs>, to restraine
                  c<ex>er</ex>ten <rs ref="eats:8782" type="Entertainer_Type">players</rs>
                  w<ex>i</ex>t<ex>h</ex>in the Bouroghe of <rs ref="eats:36966"
                  type="Place_PA_Settlement">Southewarke</rs> and other places nere adioyning
                  w<ex>i</ex>t<ex>h</ex>in the Bouroghe of Southewarke and other places nere
                adioyning w<ex>i</ex>t<ex>h</ex>in that p<ex>ar</ex>te of <rs ref="eats:2291"
                  type="Place_County">Surreye</rs>, who by meanes of the alluring of the people
                  ‸<add place="above">to their <rs ref="eats:40453" type="Drama_Type"
                  >plaies</rs></add> doe augement the infection of ‸<add place="above">the
                  <!--plague--> in</add>
                <rs ref="eats:36947" type="Place_PA_Settlement">London</rs>; and if they shall not
                obeye their order to see them seuerely punished./</ab>

              <gap reason="omitted"/>
            </div>
            <div>
              <head>p 348 <supplied>(23 December) (Richmond)</supplied></head>
              <pb n="348" type="page" facs="#NBPCO7p348"/>

              <gap reason="omitted"/>

              <ab>A l<ex>ett</ex>er to the <rs ref="eats:131764" type="Person_Male">L<ex>ord</ex>
                  Maior</rs> and the <rs ref="eats:154215" type="Collective_Office">Iustices of
                    Midd<ex>lesex</ex></rs> and <rs ref="eats:160152" type="Collective_Office"
                  >Surrey</rs>, Requiring<note type="foot">Requiring: <hi rend="italic">2 minims
                    for</hi> in</note> them to suffer the exercise of playes w<ex>i</ex>thin the
                Cittie of London and ‸<add place="above">w<ex>i</ex>thin</add> the
                lib<ex>er</ex>ties, and to have regarde that suche orders as are p<ex>re</ex>scribed
                for the staying<note type="foot">staying: <hi rend="italic">2 minims for</hi>
                  in</note> of thinfection maie be duelie observed, so as ther growe no hurte<note
                  type="foot">hurte: u <hi rend="italic">written over</hi> a</note> vnto the soundre
                in their publicque assemblies./</ab>
            </div>
          </div>
          <div type="endnote">
            <p> Those named in the 10 November privy council letter were the JPs for Surrey. Edward
              Bellingham (<hi rend="italic">c</hi> 1545–1605), was appointed JP in <hi rend="italic"
                >c</hi> 1573, according to the <ref
                target="https://www.historyofparliamentonline.org/volume/1558-1603/member/bellingham-edward-1545-1605"
                  ><title>HPO</title></ref>, accessed 23 July 2024. Bernard Randolph, JP of Middlesex, was also appointed JP for
              Surrey in 1567 (see Appendix One of William Baxter Robison III, 'The Justices of the
              Peace of Surrey in National and County Politics, 1483–1570,' 2 vols, PhD thesis
              (Louisiana State University, 1983), 403). No further information has been found for
              'Mr doctor Fourthe' and 'Rob<ex>er</ex>t Lewseye.' </p>

            <p> Privy councillors listed as present at the 10 November meeting (p 381) were <rs
                ref="eats:444022" type="Person_Male">Sir Nicholas Bacon</rs> (1510–79), keeper of
              the Great Seal, 1558–79; <rs ref="eats:130613" type="Person_Male">Sir William
                Cecil</rs> (1520/21–98), first Baron Burghley, lord treasurer, 1572–98; <rs
                ref="eats:49811" type="Person_Nobility">Thomas Radcliffe</rs> (1526/7–83), eighth
              earl of Sussex, lord chamberlain of the Household, 1572–83; <rs ref="eats:173323"
                type="Person_Male">Henry Fitzalan</rs> (1512–80), twenty-fourth earl of Arundel; <rs
                ref="eats:488103" type="Person_Male">Sir James Croft</rs> (<hi rend="italic">c</hi>
              1518–90), comptroller of the Household, 1570-90; <rs ref="eats:130516"
                type="Person_Male">Sir Christopher Hatton</rs> (<hi rend="italic">c</hi> 1540–91),
              vice-chamberlain of the Household, 1577–87; and <rs ref="eats:121275"
                type="Person_Male">Sir Francis Walsingham</rs> (<hi rend="italic">c</hi> 1532–90),
              principal secretary, 1573–90.</p>

            <p> Privy councillors listed as present at the 23 December meeting (p 433) were <rs
                ref="eats:488164" type="Person_Male">Edward Clinton</rs> (1512–85), sixteenth earl
              of Lincoln, lord admiral, 1559–85; <rs ref="eats:12536" type="Person_Nobility">Ambrose
                Dudley</rs> (<hi rend="italic">c</hi> 1530–90), twenty-first earl of Warwick; <rs
                ref="eats:44753" type="Person_Nobility">Robert Dudley</rs> (1532/3–88), fourteenth
              earl of Leicester; <rs ref="eats:68527" type="Person_Gentry">Sir Francis Knollys</rs>
              (1511/12–96), treasurer of the Household, 1570–96; Sir James Croft (<hi rend="italic"
                >c</hi> 1518–90), comptroller of the Household, 1570–90; and Sir Francis Walsingham
                (<hi rend="italic">c</hi> 1532–90), principal secretary, 1573–90. </p>

            <p>For an abstract of the 10 November order and details of its transcription history, 
              see the related EMLoT <ref target="https://emlot.org/db/record/event/236/index.html"
                >event record</ref>.</p>
          </div>
        </body>
      </text>
      <text ana="taxon:CentralGov_PC" type="record" xml:id="nwbts-rid11">
        <body>
          <head><rs ref="eats:2111" type="Place_County">Middlesex</rs>, <rs ref="eats:375732"
              type="Place_F_Residence">Westminster Palace</rs>
            <date when-iso="1580">1580</date>
            <seg ana="taxon:NBPL13">NBPL13</seg></head>
          <div xml:lang="eng" type="transcription" xml:id="nwbts-rid11-transcription">
            <div>
              <head>p 10 <supplied>(13 May) (Westminster)</supplied></head>
              <pb n="10" type="page" facs="#NBPL13p10"/>

              <gap reason="omitted"/>

              <ab>A l<ex>ett</ex>re to the <rs ref="eats:160152" type="Collective_Office"
                    >Iustic<ex>es</ex> of peace</rs> of the Countie of <rs ref="eats:2291"
                  type="Place_County">Surr<ex>ie</ex></rs> that whereas therr l<ex>ordships</ex> do
                vnderstand that notw<ex>i</ex>thstandinge therr late order geuen to the <rs
                  ref="eats:489585" type="Person_Male">l<ex>ord</ex> maior</rs> to for bidd all <rs
                  ref="eats:40453" type="Drama_Type">playes</rs> w<ex>i</ex>thin and about the <rs
                  ref="eats:36947" type="Place_PA_Settlement">Cittie</rs> vntill <rs
                  ref="eats:42598" type="CalendarDay_Liturgical">Michalmas</rs> next for avoydinge
                of infection neu<ex>er</ex>theles certen <rs ref="eats:8782" type="Entertainer_Type"
                  >players</rs> do playe sunderie daies eu<ex>er</ex>y weeke at <rs
                  ref="eats:227741" type="Place_F_Playhouse">newington butt<ex>es</ex></rs> on that
                  p<ex>ar</ex>te of Surr<ex>ie</ex> w<ex>i</ex>thout the Iurisdicc<ex>i</ex>on of
                the said L<ex>or</ex>d Maior <rs ref="eats:173156" type="CrimesMisdemeanors"
                  >contrary to therr l<ex>ordships</ex> order</rs>. therr l<ex>ordships</ex> requier
                the Iustic<ex>es</ex> not only to enquier who they be that disobey therr
                  Comaundeme<ex>n</ex>t<note type="foot">Comaundeme<ex>n</ex>t: <hi rend="italic"
                    >blot over</hi> t</note> in that behalf and not only to forbidd them expresly
                for plying<note type="foot">plying: <hi rend="italic">likely for</hi> playing</note>
                in any of theis remote places nere vnto the Cittie vntill Michaelmas. but to haue
                regard that w<ex>i</ex>thin the precincte of Surr<ex>ie</ex> none be
                p<ex>er</ex>mitted to play if any do to comitt them and to adu<ex>er</ex>tise/
                &amp;c</ab>

              <gap reason="omitted"/>
            </div>
          </div>
          <div type="endnote">
            <p> The last recorded performance at court by the <rs ref="eats:12706" type="Collective_Troupe">earl of Warwick's players</rs> was 1
              January 1579/80 (for lxvj s. viij d., TNA: E351/542, f 8), but it is possible that the
              company was still in residence at Newington Butts in May of the same year. Ingram,
                <title>Business of Playing</title>, pp 174–5, and Johnson, <title>Shakespeare's Lost
                  Playhouse</title>, pp 89, 99, have speculated that the newly formed <rs ref="eats:50533" type="Collective_Troupe">earl of Oxford's
                    players</rs>, led by <rs ref="eats:180666" type="Person_Male">John</rs> and <rs ref="eats:180596" type="Person_Male">Laurence Dutton</rs>,
              may have used the playhouse next. How long <rs ref="eats:202508" type="Person_Male"
                >Jerome Savage</rs> continued his tenancy is unclear, but by June 1582 <rs
                ref="eats:133645" type="Person_Male">Peter Hunningborne</rs> is on record in the
              Cathedral Chapter Act Book with <ref
                target="https://ereed.org/records/nwbts-rid3/">a lease</ref> for the 'resydue of
              the garden <gap reason="omitted"/> and ground<ex>es</ex> adioyning to the play house,'
              indicating the existence of an even earlier lease.</p>

            <p> Savage had moved by 1582 to the parish of <rs ref="eats:225955"
                type="Place_PA_Settlement">St Peter Westcheap</rs>, London, where he was assessed on
              £3 3s of goods in a lay subsidy roll for that year (TNA: E179/251/16, f 79). The
              baptism of Anne, one of his four daughters, was recorded on 19 March 1581/2 in the St
              Peter Westcheap parish register (LMA: P69/PET4/A/001/MS06502). Suzan, another
              daughter, was baptized 28 November 1585, but no baptismal dates have been found for
              Elizabeth, Faith, or Daniel, all named in their father's will. Although the surname
              Savage does not appear in St Peter Westcheap Churchwardens' Accounts between 1577-83,
              there is mention of a 'Mr Savage' under the Wood Street subheading in the receipts for
              1583–4 (LMA: P69/PET4/B/006/MS00645/001, f 112). By November 1586 he was still
              resident there (TNA: E115/343/52, single sheet). He died soon after: his will is dated
              31 January 1586/7, with a probate date of 18 February (see TNA: PROB 11/70/119).</p>

            <p> The 'late order' refers to a plague order issued by the privy council to the JPs of
              Middlesex on 17 April 1580, to restrain plays on the outskirts of London until
              Michaelmas (TNA: PC2/12, p 812).</p>

            <p> Privy councillors listed as present at this meeting (p 10) were <rs
                ref="eats:488969" type="Person_Male">Sir Thomas Bromley</rs> (<hi rend="italic"
                >c</hi> 1530–87), lord chancellor, 1579-87; <rs ref="eats:130613" type="Person_Male"
                >Sir William Cecil</rs> (1520/21-98), first Baron Burghley, lord treasurer, 1572-98;
                <rs ref="eats:130516" type="Person_Male">Sir Christopher Hatton</rs> (<hi
                rend="italic">c</hi> 1540–91), vice-chamberlain of the Household, 1577–87; <rs
                ref="eats:121275" type="Person_Male">Sir Francis Walsingham</rs> (<hi rend="italic"
                >c</hi> 1532–90), principal secretary, 1573-90; and <rs ref="eats:489034"
                type="Person_Male">Thomas Wilson</rs> (<hi rend="italic">c</hi> 1523/4-81). </p>

            <p>For an abstract of the document and details of its transcription history,  see the
              related EMLoT <ref target="https://emlot.org/db/record/event/234/index.html">event
                record</ref>.</p>
          </div>
        </body>
      </text>
      <text ana="taxon:CentralGov_PC" type="record" xml:id="nwbts-rid9">
        <body>
          <head><rs ref="eats:2039" type="Place_County">Kent</rs>, <rs ref="eats:334708"
              type="Place_F_Residence">Greenwich Palace</rs>
            <date when-iso="1586">1586</date>
            <seg ana="taxon:NBPCL3">NBPCL3</seg></head>
          <div xml:lang="eng" type="transcription" xml:id="nwbts-rid9-transcription">
            <div>
              <head>p 84 <supplied>(11 May) (Greenwich)</supplied></head>
              <pb n="84" type="page" facs="#NBPCL3p84"/>

              <ab>A l<ex>ett</ex>re to the <rs ref="eats:160152" type="Collective_Office">Iustices
                  of Surrey</rs>: that according to suche direction as hathe ben geuen by their
                  L<ex>ordship</ex>s to the <rs ref="eats:165351" type="Person_Male">L<ex>ord</ex>
                  Maior</rs> to restraine and inhibite the vse of <rs ref="eats:40453"
                  type="Drama_Type">plaies</rs> and <rs ref="eats:40398" type="Drama_Type"
                  >interludes</rs> in publique places in and about the <rs ref="eats:36947"
                  type="Place_PA_Settlement">Cittie of London</rs>., in respect of the heat of the
                yeere now drawing on for thauoyding of the infection like to grow and increase by
                thordinarie assemblies of the people to those places they <add place="above"
                  >ar</add>
                <del>is</del>‸ also required in like sorte to take order y<ex>a</ex>t the playes
                &amp; assemblies of the people at the <rs ref="eats:228217" type="Place_F_Playhouse"
                  >Theater</rs> or anie other places about <rs ref="eats:227741" type="Place_F_Playhouse">Newington</rs> bee forthw<ex>i</ex>th restrained and
                forborne as aforesaid &amp;c.</ab>

              <gap reason="omitted"/>
            </div>
            <div>
              <head>p 86</head>
              <pb n="86" type="page" facs="#NBPCL3p86"/>

              <gap reason="omitted"/>

              <ab>A l<ex>ett</ex>re to the L<ex>ord</ex> Maior: his l<ex>ordship</ex> is desired
                according <del><damage><gap unit="chars" extent="3"/></damage></del> to his request
                made to their l<ex>ordship</ex>s by his l<ex>ett</ex>res of the vij<hi
                  rend="superscript">th</hi> of this p<ex>rese</ex>nt to geue order for the
                restrayning of playes and interludes w<ex>i</ex>thin and about the Cittie of London
                for thauoyding of infection feared to grow and increase this tyme of So<ex>m</ex>mer
                by the Comon assemblies of people at those places, and that their l<ex>ordship</ex>s
                haue taken the like order for the p<ex>ro</ex>hibiting of the vse of playes at the
                Theater &amp; thother places about newington out of his charge: and that according
                to his request their l<ex>ordship</ex>s haue geuen order for the reformeing of the
                disorder noted among the <rs ref="eats:38944" type="Collective_Occupations"
                  >millners</rs>. &amp;c.</ab>

              <gap reason="omitted"/>
            </div>
          </div>
          <div type="endnote">
            <p> The mayor's letter of 7 May has not yet been found.</p>

            <p> Privy councillors listed as present at the 11 May meeting (p 89) were <rs
                ref="eats:131578" type="Person_Male">John Whitgift</rs> (<hi rend="italic">c</hi>
              1530–1604), archbishop of Canterbury, 1583–1604; <rs ref="eats:130613"
                type="Person_Male">Sir William Cecil</rs> (1520/21–98), first Baron Burghley, lord
              treasurer, 1572–98; <rs ref="eats:168499" type="Person_Male">William Brooke</rs>
              (1527–97), tenth Lord Cobham, privy councillor, 1585–97; <rs ref="eats:144639"
                type="Person_Male">Sir Thomas Sackville</rs> (<hi rend="italic">c</hi> 1536–1608),
              first Baron Buckhurst, privy councillor, 1586–1608; <rs ref="eats:130516"
                type="Person_Male">Sir Christopher Hatton</rs> (<hi rend="italic">c</hi> 1540–91),
              lord chancellor, 1587–91; <rs ref="eats:68527" type="Person_Gentry">Sir Francis
                Knollys</rs> (1511/12–96), treasurer of the Household, 1570–96; and <rs
                ref="eats:121275" type="Person_Male">Sir Francis Walsingham</rs> (<hi rend="italic"
                >c</hi> 1532–90), principal secretary, 1573–90. </p>

            <p>For an abstract of the document and details of its transcription history,  see the
              related EMLoT <ref target="https://emlot.org/db/record/event/69/index.html">event
                record</ref>.</p>
          </div>
        </body>
      </text>
      <text ana="taxon:Manorial_Leases" type="record" xml:id="nwbts-rid5">
        <body>
          <head><rs ref="eats:2291" type="Place_County">Surrey</rs>, <rs ref="eats:227741" type="Place_F_Playhouse">Newington Butts Playhouse</rs>
            <date when-iso="1590">1590</date>
            <seg ana="taxon:NBCCDC">NBCCDC</seg></head>
          <div xml:lang="eng" type="transcription" xml:id="nwbts-rid5-transcription">
            <div>
              <head>ff 36v–7 <supplied>(30 November)</supplied></head>
              <pb type="folio" n="36v" facs="#NBCCDCf36v"/>

              <gap reason="omitted"/>

              <ab>This Indenture<note type="foot">This Indenture: <hi rend="italic">in display
                    script</hi></note> made the thirtieth day of November in the three and thirtith
                yeare of the raigne of o<ex>u</ex>r soveraigne Lady Elizabeth<note type="foot">three
                  and thirtith … Elizabeth: <hi rend="italic">ie, 1590</hi></note> by the grace of
                god of England ffraunce and Ireland Quene defendor<note type="marginal"
                  place="margin_left"><damage><gap unit="chars" extent="1"/></damage>rata in
                      New<damage><gap extent="2" unit="chars"/></damage>gton Richardo <damage><gap
                      unit="chars" extent="2"/></damage>ckucke dimiss<ex>a</ex><note type="foot"
                        >:<damage><gap unit="chars" extent="1"/></damage>rata … dimiss<ex>a</ex>:
                      <hi rend="italic">likely for </hi> Prata in Newington Richardo Cuckucke
                      dimiss<ex>a</ex><hi rend="italic">; 'Meadows in Newington demised to Richard
                      Cuckowe'; letters lost due to fire damage along the left
                  margin</hi></note></note> of the fayth etc. Betwene<note type="foot">Betwene: <hi
                    rend="italic">in display script</hi></note> the <rs ref="eats:489184"
                  type="Collective_Clergy">Deane</rs> and Chapiter of the Cathedrall and <rs
                  ref="eats:234616" type="Place_F_Church">metropoliticall Church of Christ of
                  Caunterbury</rs> of thone parte, And <rs ref="eats:487187" type="Person_Male"
                  >Rychard Cukcuk</rs> of the Bourrough of <rs ref="eats:36966"
                  type="Place_PA_Settlement">Southwark</rs> nere to the <rs ref="eats:36947"
                  type="Place_PA_Settlement">Cytty of London</rs>
                <rs ref="eats:21077" type="Collective_Occupations">Inhoulder</rs> of thothert
                  p<ex>ar</ex>te wytnesseth<note type="foot">wytnesseth: <hi rend="italic">in
                    display script</hi></note> that the sayd Deane and Chapiter as well for and in
                  consyderac<ex>i</ex>on of the Surrender of a lease of the kinges hereby againe
                demysed before this tyme made and graunted to one <rs ref="eats:486966"
                  type="Person_Male">Thomas Cukcuk</rs> of the sayd Bourrough of Southwarke
                <rs ref="eats:21077" type="Collective_Occupations">Inhoulder</rs> father of the sayd Rychard Cukcuk, w<ex>hi</ex>ch lease beareth date the
                last daye of September in the fower and twentith yeare<note type="foot">fower and
                  twentith yeare: <hi rend="italic">ie, 1582</hi></note> of the raigne of
                  o<ex>u</ex>r sayd soveraigne Lady Quene Elizabeth the interest and terme of yeares
                of and in w<ex>hi</ex>ch sayd lease before ‸<add place="above">&amp;</add> at the
                tyme of the sayd surrender was in the sayd Rychard Cukcuk, As also for divers other
                good and reasonable causes and considerac<ex>i</ex>ons then thervnto movinge have
                  w<ex>i</ex>th there mutuall assent and consent demised graunted and to ferme
                letten And by theise presentes for them and theire Successors doe demyse graunte and
                to ferme lett vnto the sayd Rychard Cukcuk All those theire thirtie and five acres
                one daye work one pearch and half a pearch of land and meadowe w<ex>i</ex>th
                  thapurtena<ex>u</ex>nc<ex>es</ex> severallye lying and being in the
                p<ex>ar</ex>ish of <rs ref="eats:231618" type="Place_PA_Settlement">Newington</rs>
                in the <rs ref="eats:2291" type="Place_County">County of Surrey</rs> Wherof tenn
                acres one rodd fower day work<ex>es</ex> and one pearch be called <rs
                  ref="eats:489100" type="Place_F_Property">Lurklane</rs> togeythers lyinge to the
                  Butt<ex>es</ex> of Newington against the West, to the land<ex>es</ex> of the sayd
                Deane and Chapiter there called litle pightell against the East, to the
                  land<ex>es</ex> of the late Abbey of Barmondsey called Mellfeild against the North
                and to the Orchard nowe or late of one <rs ref="eats:489458" type="Person_Male"
                  >Edmond Myddleton</rs> against the South and twoe acres and twoe dayes Worke and
                half a day work be called litle pyghtell and lye betwene the sayd landes called
                Lurklane and the land<ex>es</ex> of the sayd Deane and Chapiter called Stewefenne
                And nyne acres one rodd and fyve dayes worke be called Stewefenne lying to a garden
                there called Bell garden agaynst the North to a meadowe called Marlett<ex>es</ex>
                  meadowa<note type="foot">meadowa: <hi rend="italic">for</hi> meadow</note> against
                the South to the sayd Land<ex>es</ex> called the litle Pyghtell against the West and
                to the landes of the late pryo<ex>u</ex>r of and Covent of St Mary Overyes against
                the East And seaven acres and one rodd therof be called flex crost lying to the <rs
                  ref="eats:357230" type="Place_F_WaterFeature">common sewar</rs> agayinst the North
                to the land<ex>es</ex> late <rs ref="eats:490745" type="Person_Male">S<ex>i</ex>r
                  Henry Wyatt<ex>es</ex></rs> knight called Bramble Shott against the South to the
                  land<ex>es</ex> now or late of <rs ref="eats:489654" type="Person_Male">Stephen
                  Myddleton</rs> called Byrneyard And the sayd meadowe called Marleez meade against
                the East And seaven acres reasydue of the sayd land<ex>es</ex> severallye lyinge in
                a cloase called horsemongerland of the w<ex>hi</ex>ch seaven acres five acres lye
                together to the land<ex>es</ex> nowe or late of the sayd Edmond Myddleton towardes
                the East and South and to the land<ex>es</ex> of the sayd late pryo<ex>u</ex>r and
                Covent of St Mary Overyes called le Wyffym toward<ex>es</ex> the west and to the
                landes of the late <rs ref="eats:466544" type="Collective_Office"
                  >M<ex>aste</ex>r</rs> of <rs ref="eats:228350" type="Place_F_Hospital">St Thomas
                  Hospitall</rs> in Southwarke/ and the Cartway leadinge from and out of the sayd
                close called horsemongerland in to the kyng<ex>es</ex> hygh streate there
                  toward<ex>es</ex> the North and twoe acres reasydue of the sayd seaven acres lye
                togither to three acres of land late <rs ref="eats:489397" type="Person_Male">walter
                  kellet</rs> And before <rs ref="eats:489313" type="Person_Male">Rob<ex>er</ex>te
                  Gaynfforth Esquier</rs> toward<ex>es</ex> the East to three acres now or late of
                the sayd Edmond Myddletons toward<ex>es</ex> the West, And to the lands late <rs
                  ref="eats:489715" type="Person_Male">Rychard Baker</rs> and somtyme <rs
                  ref="eats:489802" type="Person_Male">Roger Poynte</rs> towardes the South and to
                the land<ex>es</ex> of the sayd Hospitall toward<ex>es</ex> the North Except and
                alwayes to the sayd Deane and Chapiter and theire Successors res<ex>er</ex>ved one
                Messuage or tennem<ex>en</ex>te heretofore by one <rs ref="eats:487271"
                  type="Person_Male">Rychard Hyck<ex>es</ex></rs> deceased erected and built vppon
                  p<ex>ar</ex>cell of the sayd land<ex>es</ex> now called<pb type="folio" n="37r"
                  facs="#NBCCDCf37r"/> the <rs ref="eats:227741" type="Place_F_Playhouse"
                  >playhowse</rs> w<ex>i</ex>th all howses gardens or orchard<ex>es</ex> thervnto
                adioyninge <damage><gap unit="chars" extent="1"/></damage> and in
                  thoccupac<ex>i</ex>on of one <rs ref="eats:133645" type="Person_Male">Peter
                  Honingborne</rs> or his assignes To ha<damage><gap unit="chars" extent="2"
                  /></damage><note type="foot">To ha<damage><gap unit="chars" extent="2"/></damage>:
                    <hi rend="italic">in display script</hi></note> occupye and enioye all the sayd
                land and meadowe w<ex>i</ex>t<ex>h</ex> thapurtena<ex>u</ex>nc<ex>es</ex> to the
                    s<damage><gap unit="chars" extent="3"/></damage> and his assignes (except before
                excepted) from the <rs ref="eats:42598" type="CalendarDay_Liturgical">feast of St
                  Mychaell tharch</rs><damage><gap unit="chars" extent="3"/></damage> before the
                date of theise present<ex>es</ex> vnto the full end of the terme of twenty and
                    <damage><gap unit="chars" extent="3"/></damage> from thence next ensuinge and
                fullye to be compleate and ended Yealding <damage><gap unit="chars" extent="3"
                  /></damage> payinge<note type="foot">payinge: <hi rend="italic">in display
                    script</hi></note> therfore yearlye to the sayd Deane and Chapiter and to theire
                    Suc<damage><gap unit="chars" extent="3"/></damage> the gate entringe to the
                foresayd tenn acres one Rodd fower dayework<ex>es</ex> and one pe<damage><gap
                    unit="chars" extent="3"/></damage> land called Lurklane five pound<ex>es</ex>
                fowertene shillinges and fower pence of law<damage><gap unit="chars" extent="3"
                  /></damage> money of England at fower vsuall termes in the yeare that is to say at
                the feast<ex>es</ex> of th<damage><gap unit="chars" extent="3"/></damage>
                <rs ref="eats:239365" type="CalendarDay_Liturgical">of o<ex>u</ex>r Lord Christ</rs>
                <rs ref="eats:72087" type="CalendarDay_Liturgical">Thanuntiac<ex>i</ex>on of St Mary
                  the Virgin</rs>
                <rs ref="eats:41188" type="CalendarDay_Liturgical">the Natiuitie of St Iohn</rs>
                <damage><gap unit="chars" extent="3"/></damage> and St Mychaell tharchangell by even
                  porc<ex>i</ex>ons to be payde And<note type="foot">And: <hi rend="italic">in
                    display script</hi></note> the sayd Rychard <damage><gap unit="chars" extent="3"
                  /></damage> for him his executors administrators and assignes
                  Covena<ex>u</ex>nt<ex>es</ex> and graunteth to and <damage><gap unit="chars"
                    extent="3"/></damage> the sayd Deane and Chapiter and theire Successors by
                theise p<ex>re</ex>sent<ex>es</ex> that he the sa<damage><gap unit="chars"
                    extent="2"/></damage> Rychard Cukcuk his exectuors administrators and assignes
                shall duringe and by all th<damage><gap unit="chars" extent="3"/></damage> terme
                from tyme to tyme as oft as nede shall require at his and theire proper
                    cost<damage><gap unit="chars" extent="3"/></damage> expences, Skowre, repayre,
                maynteyne susteyne and amend the <rs ref="eats:357230" type="Place_F_WaterFeature"
                  >Common sewar</rs>
                <damage><gap unit="chars" extent="3"/></damage>inge to the sayd Landes or any of
                them, and the brydge or bridges over the same sewar <damage><gap unit="chars"
                    extent="3"/></damage> be/ and also pay all Skott<ex>es</ex> taxes, and
                ymposytions to be sett or ymposed vppon the sa<damage><gap unit="chars" extent="2"
                  /></damage> land<ex>es</ex> and lykwyse kepe the hedges dytches and enclosures
                well dyked fenced and enclosed and the same sewar bridges hedges and dytches well
                repayred amended dyked fro <damage><gap unit="chars" extent="3"/></damage> enclosed
                and fenced in the end of the sayd terme to the sayd Deane and Chapiter and theire
                successors shall leave and yeld vpp And<note type="foot">And: <hi rend="italic">in
                    display script</hi></note> yf it happen the sayd yearlye rent or ferme of fyve
                poundes fowertene shillinges and fower pence of lawfull money of england to be
                behind and vnpayd in p<ex>ar</ex>te or in all by the space of twentye dayes next
                after any fest of the feast<ex>es</ex> abovesayd in w<ex>hi</ex>ch it ought to be
                payd (yf it be lawfullie required and demaunded Or yf such p<ex>er</ex>son or
                  p<ex>er</ex>sons to whose vse and possession this p<ex>re</ex>sent lease and terme
                of yeares shall remaine and come, by bargayne, sale devyse legacy or otherwise by or
                from the sayd Rychard Cukcuk doe not eyther w<ex>i</ex>thin one whole yeare next
                after thavinge and enioyinge of this lease and terme of yeares, make Surrender of
                this sayd lease and of the terme of yeres therin then to come to the sayd Deane and
                Chapiter and theire Successessors so that he or they may then or within
                  covenient<note type="foot">covenient: <hi rend="italic">for</hi> convenient<hi
                    rend="italic">; abbreviation mark missing</hi></note> tyme after, receyve of the
                sayd Deane and Chapiter and theire successors a lyke good sufficient and lawfull
                newe lease of all the predemysed p<ex>re</ex>misses for so many yeares as shalbe
                then to come of the terme aforesayd conteininge in it the like word<ex>es</ex> of
                demise Covena<ex>u</ex>nt<ex>es</ex> and condic<ex>i</ex>ons
                  res<ex>er</ex>vac<ex>i</ex>ons and all other articles as is aforesayd for the
                  w<ex>hi</ex>ch lease so to be graunted nofyne nor other paym<ex>en</ex>t shalbe
                required or demaunded but only the ordinary fees for sealinge and wrytinge of the
                same/ Or w<ex>i</ex>thin the tyme aforesayd give sygnificac<ex>i</ex>on and notice
                to the sayd Deane and Chapiter and theire successors of his and there possession and
                interest of and in this p<ex>re</ex>sent demyse and terme of yeares and thervppon by
                  paym<ex>en</ex>t of the rent or otherwyse become tennaunt to the sayd Deane and
                Chapiter and theire Successors And doe then also make paym<ex>en</ex>t to theire
                officers of such ordinary fees and dutyes as are accustomed to be payd for the
                sealinge and writinge of a lease w<ex>hi</ex>ch doth passe vnder theire common
                seale, That then and from thence forth this p<ex>re</ex>sent Indenture lease and
                terme of yeares and every clause and article therin above one the behalf of the sayd
                Deane and Chapiter and theire Successors made and graunted shalbe vtterlye voyde
                frustrate and of nowe effect, any thinge in theise p<ex>re</ex>sent<ex>es</ex>
                before mencioned to the contrary hereof in any wyse notw<ex>i</ex>thstandinge
                  In<note type="foot">In: <hi rend="italic">in display script</hi></note> wytnes
                wherof to one p<ex>ar</ex>te of this Indenture remayninge w<ex>hi</ex>ch the sayd
                Rychard Cukcuk the sayd Deane and Chapiter have sett theire common seal<ex>es</ex>
                And to thother p<ex>ar</ex>te remayninge w<ex>hi</ex>ch the sayd Deane and Chapiter
                the sayd Rychard Cukcuk hath sett his seale./ Dated in the Chapiter howse of the
                sayd Deane and Chapiter the day and yeare first above written./</ab>

              <gap reason="omitted"/>
            </div>
          </div>
          <div type="endnote">
            <p>The Canterbury Cathedral Chapter Act Book, CCA: CCA-DCc-CA/3, f 146v, also records
              this lease of thirty-five acres in Newington to Richard Cuckowe for twenty-one years
              on 30 November 1590, but without the details provided in the text of the lease itself.
              Cuckowe's father Thomas had apparently been granted the lease previously on 30
              September 1582, but no evidence has yet been found to corroborate the transfer from
              Richard Hickes. Register/V4 (1570–1609) and V5 (1580–82) have been checked, with no
              results for transfer of the lease. However, any further search for leases of Lurklane
              between 1579 and 1582 is frustrated by damage to the manuscripts. U5 (1565–72), U7
              (1579–84), and the Chapter Registers U7 (1579–84) and U8 (1584–9) are presently unfit
              for production.</p>
            <p>Both Richard and Thomas Cuckowe (Cukcuk) were innholders in Southwark. Thomas Cuckowe
              died in 1589, a parishioner of St Olave, and was buried on 8 June 1589 (LA: P71/OLA,
              1583–1627, first noted by Ingram, <title>Business of Playing</title>, p 156, n 17). As
              the <ref target="https://ereed.org/records/nwbts-rid15/">3 November 1578 Sewer
                Commission survey</ref> makes clear, Thomas Cuckowe had previously been a tenant on
              Hickes' land and immediate neighbour of Jerome Savage. Ingram also noted that Richard
              would become a vestryman and churchwarden of St Mary's Church, Newington. As a member
              of vestry, his name first appears in 1609, Southwark Archives: MN/1/1/1, f 2v; in 1610
              and 1611 he became churchwarden, f 2A.</p>
            <p>The text of the indenture below corroborates the <ref
                target="https://ereed.org/records/nwbts-rid3/">1582 lease</ref> evidence that
              Richard Hickes' son-in-law, Peter Hunningborne, had taken possession of the playhouse
              and property known as Lurklane before this date.</p>
            <p> The edge of folio 37 has been badly damaged by fire, with consequent loss of letters
              indicated by '<damage><gap unit="chars" extent="3"/></damage>.' </p>
          </div>
        </body>
      </text>
      <text type="record" xml:id="nwbts-rid21" copyOf="rosep.xml#rosep-ridm92855896">
        <body>
          <p/>
        </body>
      </text>
      <text ana="taxon:Manorial_Leases" type="record" xml:id="nwbts-rid6">
        <body>
          <head><rs ref="eats:2291" type="Place_County">Surrey</rs>, <rs ref="eats:227741" type="Place_F_Playhouse">Newington Butts Playhouse</rs>
            <date when-iso="1595">1595</date>
            <seg ana="taxon:NBCCDC">NBCCDC</seg></head>
          <div xml:lang="eng" type="transcription" xml:id="nwbts-rid6-transcription">
            <div>
              <head>ff 265v–6 <supplied>(5 April)</supplied></head>
              <pb type="folio" n="265v" facs="#NBCCDCf265v"/>

              <ab>This<note type="marginal" place="margin_left"><damage><gap unit="chars" extent="1"
                    /></damage>enement<ex>um</ex> vocat<ex>um</ex>
                  <damage><gap unit="chars" extent="3"/></damage>kelane prope <damage><gap
                      unit="chars" extent="1"/></damage>outhwarke Paulo Buck dimiss<ex>um</ex><note
                    type="foot"><damage><gap unit="chars" extent="1"
                      /></damage>enement<ex>um</ex>…dimiss<ex>um</ex>: <hi rend="italic">'The
                      tenement called Lurklane near Southwark demised to Paul Buck'; letters lost to
                      fire damage along the left margin</hi></note></note> Indenture<note
                  type="foot">This Indenture: <hi rend="italic">in display script</hi></note> made
                the fifte daie of Aprill in the seauen and thirtith yeare of the raigne of our
                Soveraigne Ladye Elizabeth<note type="foot">seauen and thirtith yeare … Ladye
                  Elizabeth: <hi rend="italic">ie, 1595</hi></note> by the grace of God Queen of
                Englande ffraunce and Irelande defendor of the faithe &amp;c Betwene<note
                  type="foot">Betwene: <hi rend="italic">in display script</hi></note> the <rs
                  ref="eats:489184" type="Collective_Clergy">Deane</rs> and chapiter of the
                Cathedrall and <rs ref="eats:234616" type="Place_F_Church">Metropoliticall Church of
                  Christ of Canterburye</rs> of the one parte and <rs ref="eats:488277"
                  type="Person_Male">Paule Bucke</rs> of <del>the</del>
                <rs ref="eats:36947" type="Place_PA_Settlement">Cittie of London</rs> gent of the
                other parte wytnesseth<note type="foot">wytnesseth: <hi rend="italic">in display
                    script</hi></note> that whereas the said Deane and Chapiter by theire Indenture
                of Demise bearinge date the six and twentith daie of November in the Nynth yeare of
                the raigne of our said Soveraigne Ladye Queene Elizabeth<note type="foot">Nynth
                  yeare … Elizabeth: <hi rend="italic">ie, 1566</hi></note> did demise to <rs
                  ref="eats:487271" type="Person_Male">Richard Hick<ex>es</ex></rs> one of the
                yeomen of her Ma<ex>ies</ex>ties garde. All the thinges by theis present<ex>es</ex>
                hereafter demised To<note type="foot">To: <hi rend="italic">display initial</hi>
                  T</note> haue and to hould to the said Richarde Hick<ex>es</ex> his executors and
                assignes from the <rs ref="eats:42598" type="CalendarDay_Liturgical">feast of St
                  Mychaell tharchangell</rs> then last past before the date of the saide Indenture
                vnto thend and terme of three scoare yeares. w<ex>hi</ex>ch said terme and the
                interest therein by good conveyaunce in lawe is sithence come to the handes and
                possession of the said Paule Buck. All w<ex>hi</ex>ch he the said Paule Buck hath
                surrendered to the said Deane and Chap<damage><gap unit="chars" extent="3"
                  /></damage><note type="foot">Chap<damage><gap unit="chars" extent="3"/></damage>:
                    <hi rend="italic">characters lost in binding</hi></note><pb type="folio"/>
                  Nowe<note type="foot">Nowe: <hi rend="italic">in display script</hi></note>
                therefore the said Deane and Chapiter for and in Considerac<ex>i</ex>on of
                    <damage><gap unit="chars" extent="3"/></damage> said Surrender and for other
                good causes and Considerac<ex>i</ex>ons haue demised <damage><gap unit="chars"
                    extent="3"/></damage> graunted and to ferme letten. And by theis
                  present<ex>es</ex> for them and theire suc<damage><gap unit="chars" extent="3"
                  /></damage> doe demise graunte and to ferme let vnto the saide Paule Bucke All
                that theire M<damage><gap unit="chars" extent="3"/></damage> howse and
                  tenem<ex>en</ex>t latelie builded by the foresaide Richarde Hickes vpon a parcell
                    <damage><gap unit="chars" extent="3"/></damage> scituat and ‸<add place="above"
                  >beinge</add> in <rs ref="eats:231618" type="Place_PA_Settlement">newington</rs>
                neere <rs ref="eats:36966" type="Place_PA_Settlement">Southwarke</rs> in the countee
                of <rs ref="eats:2291" type="Place_County">Surr<ex>ey</ex></rs> called <rs
                  ref="eats:489100" type="Place_F_Property">Lurklane</rs>
                <damage><gap unit="chars" extent="3"/></damage> letten as aforesaide to the saide
                Richarde Hickes amonge other landes togeither <damage><gap unit="chars" extent="3"
                  /></damage> or garden plott as it is nowe inclosed out of the saide lande called
                Lurklane All <damage><gap unit="chars" extent="3"/></damage> howse and garden
                conteyneth in length alonge by the landes of the saide Deane and cha<damage><gap
                    unit="chars" extent="3"/></damage> the tenure of the saide Richarde Hickes or
                his assignes towardes the northe fortye and six <damage><gap unit="chars" extent="3"
                  /></damage> like length alonge by the <rs ref="eats:357230"
                  type="Place_F_WaterFeature">Common Sewer</rs> there towardes the south ffortie
                fower yard<damage><gap unit="chars" extent="3"/></damage> bradth alonge by the
                Queens high waie there towardes the west thirtie six yardes And <damage><gap
                    unit="chars" extent="3"/></damage> breadh<note type="foot">breadh: <hi
                    rend="italic">for</hi> breadth</note> alonge by the landes of the saide Deane
                and Chapiter towardes the East twentie <damage><gap unit="chars" extent="3"
                  /></damage> To haue and<note type="foot">To haue and: <hi rend="italic">in display
                    script</hi></note> to houlde all the saide Messuage and tennement w<ex>i</ex>th
                    thappurtenanc<damage><gap unit="chars" extent="3"/></damage> the saide Paule
                Buck his executors and assignes from the feaste of Ste Michaell th<damage><gap
                    unit="chars" extent="3"/></damage> last past before the date of theis
                  present<ex>es</ex> vnto the full end of the ‸<add place="above">terme</add> of
                twoe and thirtie yeares <damage><gap unit="chars" extent="3"/></damage> thence next
                ensuinge and fullie to bee compleate and ended yeldinge and<note type="foot"
                  >yeldinge and: <hi rend="italic">in display script</hi></note> paying
                    th<damage><gap unit="chars" extent="3"/></damage> yearlie to the saide Deane and
                chapiter and there successors or to theire lawfull assign<damage><gap unit="chars"
                    extent="3"/></damage> assignes the some of twelue shillinges of good and laufull
                monney of englande at the feastes <damage><gap unit="chars" extent="3"/></damage>
                <rs ref="eats:72087" type="CalendarDay_Liturgical">thanuntiac<ex>i</ex>on of the
                  blessed</rs>
                <del>Wirgin</del> ‸<add place="above"><rs ref="eats:72087"
                    type="CalendarDay_Liturgical">virgin</rs></add>
                <rs ref="eats:72087" type="CalendarDay_Liturgical">marye</rs> and St Michaell
                tharckaungell by even portions <damage><gap unit="chars" extent="3"/></damage> bee
                paide duringe the saide terme/ And the sayde<note type="foot">And the sayde: <hi
                    rend="italic">in display script</hi></note> Paule Buck for him his executors
                    admi<damage><gap unit="chars" extent="3"/></damage>strators and assignes
                Couenaunteth and graunteth to and with the saide Deane and Chapiter and <damage><gap
                    unit="chars" extent="3"/></damage> there Successors by theis presentes. That he
                the saide Paule Bucke his executors adminis<damage><gap unit="chars" extent="3"
                  /></damage>tors and assignes at his and theire owne proper Costes Charges and
                expences shall in all thing<damage><gap unit="chars" extent="3"/></damage> duringe
                all the saide terme repaire vphoulde maintaine and sustaine the saide messuage and
                    tenn<damage><gap unit="chars" extent="3"/></damage>ment and other the premisses
                and the same well and sufficientlie repaired into the handes of the <damage><gap
                    unit="chars" extent="3"/></damage> saide Deane and Chapiter and theire
                successors, in thende of the saide terme to leave and yelde vp <damage><gap
                    unit="chars" extent="3"/></damage> And yf it <del>shall</del> happen<note
                  type="foot">And yf … happen: <hi rend="italic">in display script</hi></note> the
                saide yearelye rent or ferme of twelue shillinges or anie <damage><gap unit="chars"
                    extent="3"/></damage> parte thereof to bee behinde and vnpaide by the space of
                one monneth next after anie of the daye<damage><gap unit="chars" extent="2"
                  /></damage> of paymente abouesaide, in which it ought to <note type="foot">to: <hi
                    rend="italic">followed by ink blot</hi></note> be paide/ Or yf the
                  Reparac<ex>i</ex>on of the saide messu<damage><gap unit="chars" extent="3"
                  /></damage> or tennement and other the premisses <hi rend="italic">(blank)</hi> by
                theis presentes demised be not w<ex>i</ex>thin the space of one whole yeare next
                after monicion and warninge given by the Deane Receyvor general <del>and</del> or
                Surveyor of the landes and possessions of the saide Deane and Chapiter and theire
                successors for the tyme beinge to the saide Paule Buck his executors or assignes or
                to the occupiers occupiers<note type="foot">occupiers occupiers: <hi rend="italic"
                    >dittography at beginning of line</hi></note> of the premisses for the due and
                needefull kepinge and repairinge thereof well and sufficientlye donne made
                mayntayned and repaired That then and from thence foorth this present Indenture amd
                every Clause and article therein vpon the behalfe of the saide deane and
                    Chap<damage><gap unit="chars" extent="3"/></damage> above graunted to be
                vtterlye frustrate and of no force or effect anie thinge before mencio<damage><gap
                    unit="chars" extent="3"/></damage> to the contrarye notwithstandinge/ In wytnes
                  whereof<note type="foot">In wytnes whereof: <hi rend="italic">in display
                    script</hi></note> to one parte of this Indenture remayninge with the saide
                Paule Bucke the saide Deane and Chapiter haue set there common seale and to the
                other parte remayninge w<ex>i</ex>th the sayd Deane and ‸<add place="above"
                    >chapit<ex>er</ex></add>
                <del>chapiter</del> the saide Paule Bucke hath set his seale. Dated in the Chapiter
                howse of the saide Deane and Chapiter the daie and yeare first aboue written/</ab>

              <gap reason="omitted"/>
            </div>
            <div>
              <head>ff 266–6v <supplied>(6 April)</supplied></head>
              <pb type="folio" n="266" facs="#NBCCDCf266r"/>

              <gap reason="omitted"/>

              <ab>This<note type="marginal" place="margin_left">residuu<ex>m</ex>
                    p<ex>ar</ex>cell<ex>e</ex> terre ib<ex>ide</ex>m Paulo Buck
                    dimiss<ex>um</ex><note type="foot">residuu<ex>m</ex> … dimiss<ex>um</ex>: <hi
                      rend="italic">'The remainder of a parcel of land demised to Paul
                    Buck'</hi></note></note> Indenture<note type="foot">This Indenture: <hi
                    rend="italic">in display script</hi></note> Made the Sixt daie of Aprill in the
                seauen and thirtith yeare <damage><gap unit="chars" extent="3"/></damage> the raigne
                of our Soueraigne Ladie Elizabeth by the grace of God Queene of Englande
                    ffran<damage><gap unit="chars" extent="2"/></damage> and Irelande defendor of
                the faith &amp;tc. Betwene<note type="foot">Betwene: <hi rend="italic">in display
                    script</hi></note> the deane and Chapiter of the Cath<damage><gap unit="chars"
                    extent="3"/></damage> and Metropoliticall Church of Christe of Canterburye of
                the one parte And Paule Bucke of of<note type="foot">of of: <hi rend="italic"
                    >dittography at beginning of line</hi></note> London gent of the other parte/
                  Wytnesseth<note type="foot"> Wytnesseth: <hi rend="italic">in display
                  script</hi></note> that whereas the saide Deane and Ch<damage><gap unit="chars"
                    extent="3"/></damage> by there Indenture of demise vnder theire common seale
                bearinge date the fifte daie of Ap<damage><gap unit="chars" extent="3"/></damage> in
                the seauen and thirtith yeare of the raigne of our saide Soueraigne Ladye Queene
                    Eliza<damage><gap unit="chars" extent="3"/></damage> haue letten <del>vn</del>to
                the saide Paule Bucke. One Messuage or tennement scituat and beinge in Newington
                neere Southwarke in the Countie of Surr<ex>ey</ex> latelie builded vpon a parcell of
                    land<damage><gap unit="chars" extent="1"/></damage> there called Lurklane by one
                Richarde Hickes deceased togeither with a garden or garden <damage><gap unit="chars"
                    extent="3"/></damage> as it was then enclosed in w<ex>hi</ex>ch lease certaine
                  content<ex>es</ex> of the lande therein enclosed are set downe w<ex>hi</ex>ch doe
                not conteyne the whole lande as it was inclosed by the saide Richarde
                    Hic<damage><gap unit="chars" extent="3"/></damage> and as it nowe remayneth by
                fortye and eyght yardes in length and thirtie seaven yar<damage><gap unit="chars"
                    extent="3"/></damage> and an half in breadth or <del>abor</del> there
                  about<ex>es</ex> That wee the saide Deane and chapiter h<damage><gap unit="chars"
                    extent="3"/></damage> demised graunted and to ferme letten, And by theis
                presentes doe demise graunte and to <damage><gap unit="chars" extent="3"/></damage>
                let to the saide Paule Bucke the residue of the full content of the landes inclosed
                    <damage><gap unit="chars" extent="3"/></damage>
                <pb n="266v" facs="#NBCCDCf266v"/> saide garden and garden plott not fullie sett
                downe in the saide former lease as it was inclosed and taken in by the saide
                Richarde Hickes in his lyfe time bearinge the content of ffourtie and eight yardes
                towardes the north and south and in breadth towardes the East ffortie and twoe
                yardes and in like breadth to the west thirtie and three yardes be it more or less
                To haue and to houlde<note type="foot">To haue … houlde: <hi rend="italic">in
                    display text</hi></note> the saide residue of the garden or garden plotte
                aforesaide to the saide Paule Buck his executors and assignes from the feaste of
                  Thanu<ex>n</ex>tiacion of the blessed Virgin Marye last past before the date of
                theis presentes vnto the full ende of the terme of twentie and one yeares from
                thence next ensuinge and fullie to bee compleate and ended yeldinge and Payinge<note
                  type="foot">yeldinge and Payinge: <hi rend="italic">in display text</hi></note>
                therefore yearelye duringe the saide terme to the saide Deane and chapiter and
                theire successors the some of twoe shillinges of good and laufull monney of Englande
                at the feaste of St Michaell<note type="foot">Michaell: e <hi rend="italic">written
                    over</hi></note> tharchaungell onelie And yf it happen<note type="foot"> And …
                  happen: <hi rend="italic">in display text</hi></note> the saide yearlie rent or
                ferme of twoe shillinges to be behinde and unpaide in parte or in all by the space
                of eight and twentye dayes next after the feaste abouesaide in w<ex>hi</ex>ch it
                  ough<note type="foot">ough: <hi rend="italic">for</hi> ought</note> to be paide,
                That then and from thencefoorth this presente Indenture and lease and everye Clause
                and article therein aboue on the behalfe of the saide Dean and chapiter and theire
                Successors made and graunted shalbe vtterlie voide frustrated and of none effecte
                anie thinge in theis presentes before mencioned to the contrary hereof in anie wise
                notwithstandinge/ In wytnes Whereof<note type="foot"> In wytnes Whereof: <hi
                    rend="italic">in display text</hi></note> to one parte of this Indenture
                remayninge with the saide Paule Buck the saide Dean and Chapiter haue set theire
                common seale And to the other parte remayninge w<ex>i</ex>th the saide Deane and
                Chapiter the saide Paule Buck his seale hath set Dated in the Chapiter howse of the
                saide deane and chapiter the daie and yeare first aboue written</ab>

              <gap reason="omitted"/>
            </div>
          </div>
          <div type="endnote">
            <p>It is worth noting that the playhouse is not specifically mentioned in this new
              lease. Because the 5 April version contained errors in the dimensions of the property,
              Paul Buck evidently was quick to request the revised version of 6 April. Redemise of
              these thirty-five acres, formerly owned by Hickes, was negotiated in exactly the same
              terms on 1 November 1596. It exempted the property of Lurklane and repeated the error
              in the phrasing regarding the playhouse, though by this time it was no longer
              functioning as such, if indeed it was still standing. See CCA-DCc-Register/W, ff
              292–2v, and Ingram, <title>Business of Playing</title>, pp 157–8, 176–7.</p>

            <p>For an abstract of the document and details of its transcription history,  see the
              related EMLoT records: <ref target="https://emlot.org/db/record/event/7591/index.html"
                >5 April</ref> and <ref target="https://emlot.org/db/record/event/7592/index.html">6
                April</ref>.</p>
          </div>
        </body>
      </text>
      <text ana="taxon:Manorial_Leases" type="record" xml:id="nwbts-rid26">
        <body>
          <head><rs ref="eats:2291" type="Place_County">Surrey</rs>, <rs ref="eats:227741"
              type="Place_F_Playhouse">Newington Butts Playhouse</rs>
            <date from-iso="1566" to-iso="1567">1566–7</date>
            <seg ana="taxon:NBCCA1">NBCCA1</seg></head>
          <div xml:lang="eng" type="transcription" xml:id="nwbts-rid26-transcription">
            <div>
              <head>f 68 <supplied>(between 25 September 1566 and March 1566/7)</supplied></head>
              <pb n="68" type="folio" facs="#NBCCA1f68"/>



              <ab><gap reason="omitted"/><lb/>It<ex>e</ex>m. where <rs ref="eats:487271"
                  type="Person_Male">Rychard hick<ex>es</ex></rs> h<damage><gap unit="chars"
                    extent="3"/></damage><lb/>the churches Land<ex>es</ex> at Ne<damage><gap
                    unit="chars" extent="3"/></damage><lb/>for terme of yeres yet to com<ex>m</ex>e
                    <damage><gap unit="chars" extent="3"/></damage><lb/> Richard hyck<ex>es</ex>
                hath built <damage><gap unit="chars" extent="3"/></damage>
                <lb/>vppon one p<ex>ar</ex>cell of the sa<damage><gap unit="chars" extent="3"
                  /></damage>
                <lb/><rs ref="eats:489100" type="Place_F_Property">Lurkelane</rs> which with a
                    <damage><gap unit="chars" extent="3"/></damage>
                <lb/>therevnto Lande<note type="foot">Lande: <hi rend="italic">1 minim for</hi>
                  n</note> conteyn<damage><gap unit="chars" extent="3"/></damage>
                <lb/>highwaye leading from <damage><gap unit="chars" extent="3"/></damage>
                <lb/><rs ref="eats:231618" type="Place_PA_Settlement">newyngton</rs>
                <add place="above">xliiij</add>
                <del>xxiij</del> yard<ex>es</ex>
                <damage><gap unit="chars" extent="3"/></damage>
                <lb/>in lyke length in the fy<damage><gap unit="chars" extent="3"/></damage>
                <lb/>xliiij yard<ex>es</ex> and vppon th<damage><gap unit="chars" extent="3"
                  /></damage>
                <lb/>South. xiiij yard<ex>es</ex> yt ys ag<damage><gap unit="chars" extent="3"
                  /></damage>
                <lb/>Rychard shall haue a leas<damage><gap unit="chars" extent="3"/></damage>
                <lb/>and garden as yt is now <damage><gap unit="chars" extent="3"/></damage>
                <lb/>for lx yeres to begynne at <damage><gap unit="chars" extent="3"/></damage>
                <lb/>payeng therefore yerely aft<damage><gap unit="chars" extent="3"/></damage>
                <lb/>fully to be det<ex>er</ex>myned at <damage><gap unit="chars" extent="3"
                  /></damage>
                <lb/>shilling<ex>es</ex> and bearing <damage><gap unit="chars" extent="3"/></damage>
                <lb/>howse and inclosures th<damage><gap unit="chars" extent="3"/></damage>
                <lb/>hyck<ex>es</ex> or ‸<add place="above">his</add> assignes when <damage><gap
                    unit="chars" extent="3"/></damage>
                <lb/>a new lease of the foresai<damage><gap unit="chars" extent="3"/></damage>
                <lb/>w<ex>i</ex>t<ex>h</ex> hym in a former lea<damage><gap unit="chars" extent="3"
                  /></damage>
                <lb/>his assignes <damage><gap unit="chars" extent="2"/></damage>all n<damage><gap
                    unit="chars" extent="3"/></damage>
                <lb/>dymyse <damage><gap unit="chars" extent="3"/></damage></ab>
            </div>

          </div>
          <div type="endnote">
            <p>Although it is REED's usual practice to display continous prose in paragraph form,
              here we have chosen to retain the original line divisions to more accurately represent
              the damage to the MS.</p>
          </div>
        </body>
      </text>
      <text ana="taxon:Manorial_Leases" type="record" xml:id="nwbts-rid27">
        <body>
          <head><rs ref="eats:2291" type="Place_County">Surrey</rs>, <rs ref="eats:227741"
              type="Place_F_Playhouse">Newington Butts Playhouse</rs>
            <date when-iso="1573">1573</date>
            <seg ana="taxon:NBCCA2">NBCCA2</seg></head>
          <div xml:lang="eng" type="transcription" xml:id="nwbts-rid27-transcription">
            <div>
              <head>ff 32v–3v <supplied>(29 September)</supplied></head>
              <pb type="folio" n="32v" facs="#NBCCA2f32v"/>

              <gap reason="omitted"/>

              <ab>This Indenture made<note type="foot">This … made: <hi rend="italic">in display
                    script</hi></note> The xxix<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> daye of September in
                fyvetenth yeare of the Raigne of our Soveraigne Ladye Elizabeth by the grace of god
                Quene of Englande ffraunce and Irelande Defendo<ex>ur</ex> of the faithe &amp;c.
                Betwene the <rs ref="eats:489184" type="Collective_Clergy">deane</rs> and Chapter of
                the Cathedrall and <rs ref="eats:234616" type="Place_F_Church">metropoliticall
                  Churche of chr<ex>ist</ex>e in Canterburye</rs> of thone p<ex>ar</ex>tye. And <rs
                  ref="eats:487271" type="Person_Male">Richard Hickes</rs> one of the yeomen of the
                Quenes maiesties garde on thother p<ex>ar</ex>tye. Wytnessethe that the sayde Deane
                and Chapter haue dymised graunted and to farme letten and by theis
                  p<ex>rese</ex>nt<ex>es</ex> doe dymise graunt and to ferme lett vnto the sayd
                Richard Hickes all those there thyrtye and five Acres one daye woorke one
                  p<ex>er</ex>che and half a p<ex>er</ex>che of Lande and medowe
                  w<ex>i</ex>t<ex>h</ex> the appurtena<ex>u</ex>nc<ex>es</ex> severally lying and
                being in the p<ex>ar</ex>ishe of <rs ref="eats:231618" type="Place_PA_Settlement"
                  >Newyngton</rs> in the Countye of <rs ref="eats:2291" type="Place_County"
                  >Surrye</rs> Whereof tenne Acres one Rodde fower days works and a p<ex>er</ex>che
                ben called <rs ref="eats:489100" type="Place_F_Property">Lurkelane</rs> together
                lying in the Butt<ex>es</ex> of Newington against the west to the landes of the
                sayde deane and Chapter there called little pyghtell against the East, to the
                  land<ex>es</ex> of the late Abbye of Barmondsey called <del>mettl</del> melferlde
                against the Northe and to the orchard of the heyres of <rs ref="eats:489458"
                  type="Person_Male">Edmonde myddleton</rs> against the Southe, And two acres too
                days woorke and halfe a days woorke ben called little pightell and lye between the
                sayde Landes called Lurkelane and the Landes of the sayde deane &amp; Chapter called
                Stewfenne, And nyne Acres one Rodde and five days worke ben called Stewfenne lying
                to a garden there called Bellgarden against the North to a medowe called marleez
                medow against the Southe to the sayde Landes called the lyttell pightell <pb n="33"
                  facs="#NBCCA2f33"/> against the west and to the Landes of the Late Prior and
                Covent of <damage><gap unit="chars" extent="3"/></damage> Overyes against the east,
                and seven acres and one Rodd thereof bene ca<damage><gap unit="chars" extent="3"
                  /></damage> Lying <damage><gap unit="chars" extent="1"/></damage><note type="foot"
                      ><damage><gap unit="chars" extent="1"/></damage>: <hi rend="italic">a single
                    ascending stroke, likely for deletion</hi></note> in the <rs ref="eats:357230"
                  type="Place_F_WaterFeature">Comon Sewer</rs> against the Northe to the Landes
                    someth<damage><gap unit="chars" extent="3"/></damage>
                <rs ref="eats:490745" type="Person_Male">Henry wyatt knight</rs> called Bramble
                Shott against the Southe to <damage><gap unit="chars" extent="3"/></damage> nowe or
                Late <rs ref="eats:489654" type="Person_Male">Stephen Myddleton</rs> called
                Barynarde against the <damage><gap unit="chars" extent="3"/></damage> the medowe
                called marles meede against the east <del>and the west</del><damage><gap
                    unit="chars" extent="3"/></damage> acres Residue of the sayde Land<ex>es</ex>
                severally lye in a close call<damage><gap unit="chars" extent="3"/></damage> Lande
                of the which seven acres fyve acres lye together to the Land<damage><gap
                    unit="chars" extent="3"/></damage> of the heyres of the sayed Edmonde Mydeleton
                towardes the <damage><gap unit="chars" extent="3"/></damage> Southe and to the
                Landes of the sayde Late Prior and Covent of <damage><gap unit="chars" extent="3"
                  /></damage> Marye Overyes called the wiffen towardes the west and to the
                    L<damage><gap unit="chars" extent="3"/></damage> the Late <rs ref="eats:466544"
                  type="Collective_Office">m<ex>aste</ex>r</rs> of <rs ref="eats:228350"
                  type="Place_F_Hospital">St Thomas Hospitall</rs> in <rs ref="eats:36966"
                  type="Place_PA_Settlement">Sowthewark</rs> and th<damage><gap unit="chars"
                    extent="3"/></damage> waye Leading from and owt of the sayde close called
                    horsmon<damage><gap unit="chars" extent="3"/></damage> into the highe streate
                there towardes the Northe and two acres to<damage><gap unit="chars" extent="3"
                  /></damage> of the sayde seven acres lye together to three acres of Lande sowthe
                    <damage><gap unit="chars" extent="3"/></damage> walter kettell and before that
                  <rs ref="eats:489313" type="Person_Male">Robert Gaineffourthe Esquyer</rs> to
                    <damage><gap unit="chars" extent="3"/></damage> the east <del>and</del> ‸<add
                  place="above">to</add> three acres of Lande of the heyres of the sayde
                    Edmo<damage><gap unit="chars" extent="3"/></damage> myddeleton towardes the
                west, And the Landes Late Richarde <damage><gap unit="chars" extent="3"/></damage>
                and somtyme <rs ref="eats:489802" type="Person_Male">Roger Poynt<ex>es</ex></rs>
                towardes the southe and to the Landes of the<damage><gap unit="chars" extent="3"
                  /></damage> hospitall towardes the Northe. To haue and to hold all the sayde
                    <damage><gap unit="chars" extent="3"/></damage> and medowe
                  w<ex>i</ex>t<ex>h</ex> the appurtena<ex>u</ex>nces to the sayde Richarde Hickes
                his executours <damage><gap unit="chars" extent="3"/></damage> and assignes from the
                date of the date of theys p<ex>rese</ex>ntes vnto the full ende an<damage><gap
                    unit="chars" extent="1"/></damage> terme of Twentye and one Yeares next
                  ens<del>y</del>uyng and fullyes to be <damage><gap unit="chars" extent="1"
                  /></damage> complete and ended Yelding and paying therefore Yearelye to the sayde
                    <damage><gap unit="chars" extent="1"/></damage> deane and Chapter and there
                successours fyve poundes fowerteene shill<damage><gap unit="chars" extent="3"
                  /></damage> fower pence of Lawfull monye of Englande at the feastes of the <rs
                  ref="eats:239365" type="CalendarDay_Liturgical">byrthe of our Lorde god</rs>, <rs
                  ref="eats:72087" type="CalendarDay_Liturgical">theanu<ex>n</ex>cyac<ex>i</ex>on of
                    St mary the virgyn</rs> the <rs ref="eats:41188" type="CalendarDay_Liturgical"
                      >Natyuyty of St Iohn Baptist</rs> and <rs ref="eats:42598"
                  type="CalendarDay_Liturgical">St Mychell Tharcungell</rs> by even
                porc<ex>i</ex>ons during the sayde terme And the sayde Richard Hickes for him his
                    executo<damage><gap unit="chars" extent="2"/></damage> admi<ex>ni</ex>strators
                and assignes Covena<ex>u</ex>ntethe and grauntethe to and w<ex>i</ex>t<ex>h</ex> the
                sayde de<damage><gap unit="chars" extent="2"/></damage> and Chapter and there
                successours by theis presentes, That he the sayde Richard his executors
                  admi<ex>ni</ex>strato<ex>ur</ex>s and assignes shall during and by <damage><gap
                    unit="chars" extent="2"/></damage> the sayde terme from tyme to tyme as ofte as
                neede shall Require at h<damage><gap unit="chars" extent="3"/></damage> there
                propper costes and expenses scowar repayre, maynteyne susteyne <damage><gap
                    unit="chars" extent="3"/></damage> Amende the Com<ex>m</ex>on Sewer belonging to
                the sayde Landes or anye o<damage><gap unit="chars" extent="3"/></damage> and the
                bridge or bridges over the same Sewer if any be and <damage><gap unit="chars"
                    extent="3"/></damage> hedges dyches and enclosures suffycyently dyked fensed and
                    e<damage><gap unit="chars" extent="3"/></damage> shall also beare all manner of
                skottes Lotes Taxes and Cess<damage><gap unit="chars" extent="3"/></damage> to be
                cessed or Taxed vpon the sayde Landes during the s<damage><gap unit="chars"
                    extent="3"/></damage> the same Sewer bridge or bridges hedges and dyches
                    <damage><gap unit="chars" extent="3"/></damage> sufficientlye Repayred amended
                dyked skowered enclosed <damage><gap unit="chars" extent="3"/></damage> the sayde
                Landes Clearlye discharged of all s<damage><gap unit="chars" extent="3"/></damage>
                and other encombraunces in thende of the sayde <damage><gap unit="chars" extent="3"
                  /></damage>
                <pb n="33v" facs="#NBCCA2f33v"/> yelde vp. And if it happen the sayde yearely Rent
                or farme of fyve poundes fowerteene shillinges ‸<add place="above">of</add> fower
                pence to be behynde and vnpayde, in parte or in all by the space of fowerteene dayes
                next after any of the feaste or feastes aboue sayde in whiche it ought to be payed
                Or if the abovenamyd Richard Hick<ex>es</ex> his executours or assigned or any of
                them during the terme abouesayde doe dymyse sett lett or Alleyne the Landes before
                dymysed or any part thereof to any p<ex>ar</ex>son or parsones other then to the
                  Tena<ex>u</ex>nte whiche from tyme to tyme during the sayde terme shall occupy
                inhabyte and dwell in the sayde messuag and ten<ex>eme</ex>nte of the sayde deane
                and Chapter sytuate and being in the <rs ref="eats:226240"
                  type="Place_PA_Settlement">p<ex>ar</ex>ishe of Saynte Olave</rs> in the Borrowe of
                Southewark called the flowerdeluce whiche the sayde Rcharde hathe and enyoyethe by
                Lease from the sayde Deane and Chapter w<ex>i</ex>t<ex>h</ex>out Lycens of the sayde
                deane and Chapter and there Successours <del>if</del> first hade and atteyned Or if
                suche p<ex>ar</ex>son or p<ex>ar</ex>sons to whose vse and possession this present
                lease and terme of yeares or any p<ex>ar</ex>te thereof shall Remayne and come by
                bargayne sale devyse legacye or other wyse from the sayde Richarde hickes do not
                  w<ex>i</ex>thin one halfe yeare next after the having and enioying of the lease
                and terme of yeares mak surrender of this present Lease and of the terme of yeares
                therein then to come to the sayde Deane and Chapter and there successours so that he
                or they may then Receyve of the same deane and Chapter at the time <del>and</del> of
                suche Surrender a good suffycyent and Lawfull newe Lease of all the premisses for so
                manye yeares as shalbe then to come of the terme aforesayde w<ex>i</ex>t<ex>h</ex>
                lyke covena<ex>u</ex>nt<ex>es</ex> condic<ex>i</ex>ons Reservac<ex>i</ex>ons of
                  Rent<ex>es</ex> ‸<add place="above">so</add> all other <del>Rent<ex>es</ex></del>
                  ‸<add place="above">Articles as is</add> aforesayde for the whiche so to be
                graunted no fyne nor other payment shalbe Requyred or demaunded but onelye
                Thordynary fees for sealing and wryting of the same That then and from thenceforthe
                this present Indenture and Lease and everye clause and Article therein above on the
                behalf of the sayde deane and Chapter and there successo<ex>u</ex>rs made and
                graunted shalbe vtterly voyde frustrate and <del>ost</del> of none effect any thinge
                before menc<ex>i</ex>oned to the con<ex>tra</ex>rye hereof in any wise
                  Notw<ex>i</ex>t<ex>h</ex>standinge In wytnes<note type="foot">In wytnes: <hi
                    rend="italic">in display script</hi></note> whereof to one p<ex>ar</ex>te of
                this Indenture Remayning w<ex>i</ex>t<ex>h</ex> the sayde Richard hickes the sayde
                deane and Chapter haue putte there com<ex>m</ex>on seale And to thother
                p<ex>ar</ex>te Remayning w<ex>i</ex>t<ex>h</ex> the sayde deane and Chapter the
                sayde Richard hickes haue put to his seale. dated in the Chapter howse of the sayde
                deane and Chapter the daye and yeare fyrst above wryten.</ab>

              <gap reason="omitted"/>
            </div>
          </div>
        </body>
      </text>
    </group>
    <back>
      <div type="appendix" xml:id="appendix">
        <head>Inventory of Plays Performed at Newington Butts</head>
        <div>
          <p> This inventory of plays associated with the <rs ref="eats:227741"
              type="Place_F_Playhouse">playhouse at Newington</rs> includes only those on record.
            For plays performed at court by the <rs ref="eats:12706" type="Collective_Troupe">Earl
              of Warwick's Men</rs>, 1575–80, see the <ref
              target="https://ereed.org/collections/nwbts/playhouse/">Introduction: History of
              the Playhouse</ref>. </p>
          <p> I have followed the annotated catalogue <title>British Drama 1533–1642</title>, vols
            2–3, edited by Martin Wiggins and Catherine Richardson, as my authority for the title,
            authors, troupes, genre and status listed below. Further details of date, plot, roles,
            staging, sources, performance history and more for each play are provided – as far as
            possible – in that source, according to a numbering system provided here, by volume. See
            also Wiggins' 'Introduction,' vol 1, for the scope and limitations, content, format and
            arrangement of the catalogue. </p>
          <p> Others have published their own inventories of plays performed at Newington, with
            predictable variations in the titles included and in the interpretation of Henslowe's
            diary records. See for example, Chambers, <title>Elizabethan Stage</title>, vol 2, pp
            118–27, 143–7, 165–71; Johnson, <title>Shakespeare's Lost Playhouse</title>, pp 124–204.
            For the Admiral's Men in particular, see Andrew Gurr, 'Appendix 1,' <title>Shakespeare's
              Opposites: The Admiral's Company 1594–1625</title> (Cambridge, 2009), 201–53. </p>
          <p> The ongoing collaborative work of contributors to the <ref
              target="https://lostplays.folger.edu"><title>Lost Plays Database</title></ref> is a
            further valuable contribution to repertory studies. </p>
          <table rend="padded">
            <row>
              <cell><hi rend="smallcaps">Title</hi></cell>
              <cell><hi rend="smallcaps">Author</hi></cell>
              <cell><hi rend="smallcaps">Troupe</hi></cell>
              <cell><hi rend="smallcaps">Status</hi></cell>
              <cell><hi rend="smallcaps"><hi rend="italic"><title>British
                Drama</title></hi></hi></cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell><lb/></cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell><hi rend="bold">Biblical Plays</hi></cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell><hi rend="italic"><title>Esther and Ahasuerus</title></hi></cell>
              <cell>unknown</cell>
              <cell>Admiral's<lb/>Chamberlain's</cell>
              <cell>lost</cell>
              <cell>Vol 2: 1567–1589, no 801</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell><lb/></cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell><hi rend="bold">Comedy</hi></cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>Probably:</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell><hi rend="italic">The Taming of the Shrew</hi></cell>
              <cell>William<lb/>Shakespeare</cell>
              <cell>Admiral's<lb/>Chamberlain's</cell>
              <cell>Extant</cell>
              <cell>Vol 3: 1590–1597, no 916</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell><lb/></cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>Possibly:</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell><hi rend="italic">The Taming of the Shrew</hi></cell>
              <cell>Unknown</cell>
              <cell>Admiral's<lb/>Chamberlain's</cell>
              <cell>Extant</cell>
              <cell>Vol 3: 1590–1597, no 955</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell><lb/></cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell><hi rend="bold">History</hi></cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell><hi rend="italic">Belin Dun</hi></cell>
              <cell>Unknown</cell>
              <cell>Admiral's<lb/>Chamberlain's</cell>
              <cell>Lost</cell>
              <cell>Vol 3: 1590–1597, no 956</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell><lb/></cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell><hi rend="italic">Guthlac</hi></cell>
              <cell>Unknown</cell>
              <cell>Admiral's<lb/>Chamberlain's</cell>
              <cell>Extant</cell>
              <cell>Vol 3: 1590–1597, no 858</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell><lb/></cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell><hi rend="bold">Tragedy</hi></cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell><hi rend="italic">Hamlet</hi></cell>
              <cell>Thomas Kyd<lb/>attributed</cell>
              <cell>Admiral's<lb/>Chamberlain's</cell>
              <cell>Lost</cell>
              <cell>Vol 2: 1567–1589, no 814</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell><lb/></cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell><hi rend="italic">The Jew of Malta</hi></cell>
              <cell>Christopher<lb/>Marlowe</cell>
              <cell>Admiral's<lb/>Chamberlain's</cell>
              <cell>Extant</cell>
              <cell>Vol 2: 1567–1589, no 828</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell><lb/></cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell><hi rend="italic">Titus Andronicus</hi></cell>
              <cell>William<lb/>Shakespeare</cell>
              <cell>Admiral's<lb/>Chamberlain's</cell>
              <cell>Extant</cell>
              <cell>Vol 3: 1590–1597, no 928</cell>
            </row>
          </table>
        </div>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
